<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cbeta-org/xml-p5/master/schema/cbeta-p5.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cb="http://www.cbeta.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="B07na005">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
			<title level="s">Supplement to the Dazangjing</title>
			<title level="s" xml:lang="zh-Hant">大藏經補編</title>
			<title level="m" xml:lang="zh-Hant">大藏經補編第七冊．編輯說明</title>
            <title>Supplement to the Dazangjing, Electronic version, No. a005 大藏經補編第七冊．編輯說明</title>
            <title xml:lang="zh-Hant">大藏經補編數位版, No. a005 大藏經補編第七冊．編輯說明</title>
			<author>藍吉富</author>
			<respStmt>
                <resp>Electronic Version by</resp>
                <name>CBETA</name>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
            <edition>XML TEI P5</edition>
			<respStmt xml:id="resp1"><resp>corrections</resp><name>orig</name></respStmt>
        </editionStmt>
        <extent>1卷</extent>
		<publicationStmt>
            <idno type="CBETA">
                <idno type="canon">B</idno>.<idno type="vol">7</idno>.<idno type="no">a005</idno>
            </idno>
            <distributor>
				<name>財團法人佛教電子佛典基金會 (CBETA)</name>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><email>service@cbeta.org</email></addrLine>
                </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
                <p>Available for non-commercial use when distributed with this header intact.</p>
            </availability>
        	<date>2025-04-21 15:07:31 +0800</date>
		</publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
			<bibl>大藏經補編</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p xml:lang="en" cb:type="ly">Input by CBETA(first version), Input by CBETA(second version)</p>
            <p xml:lang="zh-Hant" cb:type="ly">CBETA 人工輸入（版本一），CBETA 人工輸入（版本二）</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
            <punctuation resp="#resp1"><p>新式標點</p></punctuation>
        </editorialDecl>
        <tagsDecl>
            <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <tagUsage gi="rdg">
                    <listWit>
						<witness xml:id="wit.cbeta">【CB】</witness>
						<witness xml:id="wit.orig">【補編】</witness>
					</listWit>
                </tagUsage>
            </namespace>
        </tagsDecl>
    	</encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="zh-Hant">Chinese (Traditional)</language>
        </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2021-01-15">
            <name>Ray Chou 周邦信</name>Created initial TEI XML P5a version with bm2p5a.py
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><body>
<milestone unit="juan" n="1"/>
<pb ed="B" xml:id="B07.a005.a001a" n="a001a"/>
<lb ed="B" n="a001a01"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu type="其他" level="1">Editorial Explanation</cb:mulu><head>Editorial Explanation</head>
<lb ed="B" n="a001a02"/><lb ed="B" n="a001a03"/><p xml:id="pB07pa001a0301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">This volume contains a compilation of sixteen sutras and treatises. The nature of these sixteen Buddhist texts is not uniform. Broadly speaking, they can be divided into the following categories:</p>
<lb ed="B" n="a001a04"/><p xml:id="pB07pa001a0401" style="margin-left:4em;text-indent:-2em">1. Chinese translations of Southern (Theravāda) scriptures: from the Southern “Turning the Wheel of Dharma” Sutta to the “Mindfulness of Breathing” Sutta, plus the “Abhidhamma Summary Treatise” at the end of the volume—these eleven works are all Southern Buddhist texts.
<lb ed="B" n="a001a05"/>Among them, only the Mahāparinirvāṇa Sūtra translated by Ba Zhou and the Mindfulness of Breathing Sutta translated by Tang Yongtong are somewhat longer; the remaining texts are all very short.
<lb ed="B" n="a001a06"/>Moreover, they come from different collections—some from the Khuddaka Nikāya (e.g., the Mangala Sutta), some from the Dīgha Nikāya (e.g., the Mahāparinirvāṇa Sūtra), and some from the Majjhima Nikāya (e.g.,
<lb ed="B" n="a001a07"/>the Mindfulness of Breathing Sutta)—so their canonical classifications are not all the same. These scriptures are compiled here primarily because they are not included in the Northern Transmission canon.
<lb ed="B" n="a001a08"/>However, some of them are also quite important in their own right—for example, the Mahāparinirvāṇa Sūtra, the Dhammapada, and the Mindfulness of Breathing Sutta are all key sources for the study of Early Buddhism.
<lb ed="B" n="a001a09"/>In addition, the Abhidhamma Summary Treatise at the end of the volume is an introductory essential text that summarizes Southern Buddhist thought and should not be overlooked.</p>
<lb ed="B" n="a001a10"/><p xml:id="pB07pa001a1001" style="margin-left:4em;text-indent:-2em">2. Chinese translations of Tibetan Buddhist texts: this refers to the Sutra on Recollection of the Three Jewels translated by Master Fazun, and the Bhagavatī Mother “Wisdom Gone to the Other Shore” Heart Sūtra translated by Master Gonga.
<lb ed="B" n="a001a11"/>Both works include commentaries. The Sutra on Recollection of the Three Jewels is an introductory book for beginners in Buddhism; the Bhagavatī Mother “Wisdom Gone to the Other Shore” Heart Sūtra is a new translation of the Heart Sūtra.
<lb ed="B" n="a001a12"/>This Tibetan transmission version can be collated against more than ten other different translations of the Heart Sūtra, and should help in understanding the doctrinal meaning of the Prajñā (Prajñāpāramitā) scriptures.</p>
<lb ed="B" n="a001a13"/><p xml:id="pB07pa001a1301" style="margin-left:4em;text-indent:-2em">3. Japanese Buddhist texts: this refers to Buddhist works written in Chinese by ancient Japanese scholars; here only the “Poisonous-Words Heart Sūtra” is included.
<lb ed="B" n="a001a14"/>This book is also called “Poisonous-Words Annotated Heart Sūtra,” originally a Zen-style commentary on the Heart Sūtra written in the 18th century by the famous Japanese Zen monk Hakuin Ekaku.
<lb ed="B" n="a001a15"/>Later, Nantianbang Dengzhou (i.e., “Zhongyuan Dengzhou”) added “teaching talks” (“teaching talks” meaning guidance pointing out the central aim and main points).
This volume contains the teaching-talk version by Nantianbang Dengzhou.</p>
<lb ed="B" n="a001a16"/><p xml:id="pB07pa001a1601" style="margin-left:4em;text-indent:-2em">4. Buddhist commentaries by eminent modern Chinese masters: two works are included—“Lectures/Exposition on the Diamond Sūtra” and “Essential Collected Notes on the Amitābha Sūtra.”
<lb ed="B" n="a001a17"/>The former is a renowned commentary on the Diamond Sūtra since the Republican era; the latter provides a detailed explanation of the content of the Amitābha Sūtra and is also worth noting.</p></cb:div>
</body>
<back>
</back></text></TEI>

