<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cbeta-org/xml-p5/master/schema/cbeta-p5.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cb="http://www.cbeta.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="J24nB137">
<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
			<title level="s">Jiaxing Canon (Shinwenfeng Edition)</title>
			<title level="s" xml:lang="zh-Hant">嘉興大藏經（新文豐版）</title>
			<title level="m" xml:lang="zh-Hant">趙州和尚語錄</title>
			<title>Jiaxing Canon (Shinwenfeng Edition), Electronic version, No. B137 趙州和尚語錄</title>
			<title xml:lang="zh-Hant">嘉興大藏經（新文豐版）數位版, No. B137 趙州和尚語錄</title>
			<author>唐 從諗說　文遠記　大參重校　明聲重刻</author>
			<respStmt>
				<resp>Electronic Version by</resp>
				<name>CBETA</name>
			</respStmt>
		</titleStmt>
		<editionStmt>
			<edition>XML TEI P5</edition>
			<respStmt xml:id="resp1"><resp>corrections</resp><name>CBETA</name></respStmt>
			<respStmt xml:id="resp2"><resp>corrections</resp><name>CBETA.maha</name></respStmt>
		</editionStmt>
		<extent>3卷</extent>
		<publicationStmt>
			<idno type="CBETA">
				<idno type="canon">J</idno>.<idno type="vol">24</idno>.<idno type="no">B137</idno>
			</idno>
			<distributor>
				<name>財團法人佛教電子佛典基金會 (CBETA)</name>
				<address>
					<addrLine><email>service@cbeta.org</email></addrLine>
				</address>
			</distributor>
			<availability>
				<p>Available for non-commercial use when distributed with this header intact.</p>
			</availability>
			<date>2025-01-30 02:11:07 +0800</date>
		</publicationStmt>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>嘉興大藏經（新文豐版）</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	</fileDesc>
	<encodingDesc>
		<projectDesc>
			<p xml:lang="en" cb:type="ly">Input by CBETA(first version), Input by CBETA(second version), Punctuated text as provided by Mr. Li Ming-Fang</p>
			<p xml:lang="zh-Hant" cb:type="ly">CBETA 人工輸入（版本一），CBETA 人工輸入（版本二），李明芳大德提供新式標點</p>
		</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl>
			<punctuation resp="#resp1"><p>新式標點</p></punctuation>
		</editorialDecl>
		<tagsDecl>
			<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
				<tagUsage gi="rdg">
					<listWit>
						<witness xml:id="wit.cbeta">【CB】</witness>
						<witness xml:id="wit.orig">【嘉興】</witness>
					</listWit>
				</tagUsage>
			</namespace>
		</tagsDecl>
		<charDecl>
			<char xml:id="CB01323">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB01323</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[車*度]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping type="unicode">U+2834F</mapping>
				<mapping cb:dec="984363" type="PUA">U+F052B</mapping>
			</char>
			<char xml:id="CB03308">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB03308</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[口*發]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping type="unicode">U+35F6</mapping>
				<mapping cb:dec="986348" type="PUA">U+F0CEC</mapping>
			</char>
			<char xml:id="CB03514">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB03514</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[口*部]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping type="unicode">U+2D298</mapping>
				<mapping cb:dec="986554" type="PUA">U+F0DBA</mapping>
			</char>
			<char xml:id="CB05283">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB05283</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[飢-几+追]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping type="unicode">U+4B54</mapping>
				<mapping cb:dec="988323" type="PUA">U+F14A3</mapping>
			</char>
			<char xml:id="CB15831">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB15831</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[竺-二+廢]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping type="unicode">U+426C</mapping>
				<mapping cb:dec="998871" type="PUA">U+F3DD7</mapping>
			</char>
			<char xml:id="CB16341">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB16341</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[泳-永+(虒-儿+几)]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping type="unicode">U+3D32</mapping>
				<mapping cb:dec="999381" type="PUA">U+F3FD5</mapping>
			</char>
		</charDecl>
	</encodingDesc>
	<profileDesc>
		<langUsage>
			<language ident="en">English</language>
			<language ident="zh-Hant">Chinese (Traditional)</language>
		</langUsage>
	</profileDesc>
	<revisionDesc>
		<change when="2013-05-20">
			<name>CW</name><name>Ray Chou 周邦信</name>P4 to P5 conversion by p4top5a.py, intended for publication
		</change>
		<change when="2008-06-23T10:49:08">
			Zhou Bang-Xin (ed.) Created initial TEI XML version with BASICX.BAT
		</change>
	</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><body>
<milestone n="1" unit="juan"/>
<pb n="0357a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0357a"/>
<lb n="0357a01" ed="J"/><cb:div type="xu"><cb:mulu level="1" type="序">Preface</cb:mulu><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Preface to the Recarved Record of Patriarch Zhaozhou</cb:mulu><head><note type="community" resp="dota2nub">Machine translation using ChatGPT 5.2</note>Preface to the Recarved Record of Patriarch Zhaozhou</head>
<lb n="0357a02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0357a0201">I have heard of one who could ruin households and scatter estates, and at eighteen was skilled
<lb n="0357a03" ed="J"/>in wielding the Tai'e sword; who let guest and host seize one another, and before worthies and sages
<lb n="0357a04" ed="J"/>made a play of every encounter: if not a single thing is brought forth, he simply tells one to put it down;
<lb n="0357a05" ed="J"/>when not a single thought arises, he points and says it is Mount Sumeru.
<lb n="0357a06" ed="J"/>Each time he picks up a single blade of grass and calls it the sixteen-foot golden body;
<lb n="0357a07" ed="J"/>with but a single tooth in his mouth, he fully knows all the flavors of the world.
<lb n="0357a08" ed="J"/>The turnip of Zhenzhou, people in all quarters idly say, is precisely his transmitted teaching;
<lb n="0357a09" ed="J"/>A Qingzhou cloth robe; students, do not seek the target within words.
<lb n="0357a10" ed="J"/>A plain and honest old fellow, killing and giving life according to the moment, suddenly surpassing those
<lb n="0357a11" ed="J"/>who wield sticks and shouts; with a soft tongue of three inches, freely
<lb n="0357a12" ed="J"/>at ease in all directions, when did he ever use strange words or bizarre speech? It is like
<lb n="0357a13" ed="J"/>pressing down a gourd on water, lowering the hand and pressing east, pressing west; in the room hangs
<lb n="0357a14" ed="J"/>a precious mirror, letting commoners come or sages come. When raising up the supreme
<lb n="0357a15" ed="J"/>vehicle of the lineage, if one speaks of Buddha-recitation he would rinse his mouth for three days; well able to drag
<lb n="0357a16" ed="J"/>mud and carry water, answering being and nonbeing. The true son of Nanquan,<note place="inline">As asked, so it follows.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0357a1601" n="0357a1601"/><anchor xml:id="beg0357a1601" n="0357a1601"/><anchor xml:id="end0357a1601"/></note>
<lb n="0357a17" ed="J"/>the grandson of Mazu, was only this old man alone
<lb n="0357a18" ed="J"/>indeed. In his manifested traces, worms entered his mouth and he ate chaff
<pb n="0357b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0357b"/>
<lb n="0357b01" ed="J"/>and was at peace; in the turning of karmic recompense, a bright pearl emerged from the sea and the two
<lb n="0357b02" ed="J"/>kings made offerings. If so, how could he not be an ancient Buddha manifested
<lb n="0357b03" ed="J"/>for the benefit of beings? It is a pity his recorded sayings could not all be transmitted,
<lb n="0357b04" ed="J"/>and students obtained only one fascicle, truly like tasting one morsel from a cauldron,
<lb n="0357b05" ed="J"/>or drinking a single drop from the sea. But the old printing, after many years, has characters
<lb n="0357b06" ed="J"/>blurred and indistinct, so our disciple Mingsheng brought forth the resolve to recut and make it known
<lb n="0357b07" ed="J"/>for later generations. This truly repays the Patriarch's kindness and deeply accords with this old
<lb n="0357b08" ed="J"/>worn one's intention. Admiring his aspiration, I have casually appended a few words. As for<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0357b0801" n="0357b0801"/><anchor xml:id="beg0357b0801" n="0357b0801"/><anchor xml:id="end0357b0801"/>
<lb n="0357b09" ed="J"/>his complete functioning and great activity, my poor intelligence cannot explain it; reaching depths and
<lb n="0357b10" ed="J"/>penetrating subtleties, there are naturally masters of broad understanding for that.</p>
<lb n="0357b11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0357b1101">Yunmen, 27th generation transmitter of the orthodox Caodong lineage,
<lb n="0357b12" ed="J"/>written by Sanmu Yuancheng, abbot of Xiansheng Monastery</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0357b13" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357b14" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357b15" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357b16" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357b17" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357b18" ed="J"/>
<pb n="0357c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0357c"/>
<lb n="0357c01" ed="J"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Prince Zhao composed a portrait eulogy for the Master</cb:mulu><head>Prince Zhao composed a portrait eulogy for the Master</head>
<lb n="0357c02" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0357c0201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Moon over the blue stream, a clear mirror at the center. My master, my transformation, Zhaozhou under heaven.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0357c03" ed="J"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Two elegies mourning Monk Zhaozhou</cb:mulu><head>Two elegies mourning Monk Zhaozhou</head>
<lb n="0357c04" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0357c0401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The Master left the waters and stirred the hearts of kings and lords; the seal-light sank, the fly-whisk was put away; in the blue sky mist veils the pine ridges<g ref="#CB16341"/>
<lb n="0357c05" ed="J"/>and moon, on the vast deep waves cover the ferrying boat. One lamp suddenly goes out and Mara rejoices; both eyes grow dim again and fellow practitioners
<lb n="0357c06" ed="J"/>grieve. Though one be a lucid traveler beyond the clouds, whenever gazing at the bottle and seat, tears still flow.</l></lg>
<lb n="0357c07" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0357c0701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The Buddha-sun tilts west, the Patriarch-seal jewel is lost; the cinnabar pool sinks, the moon sinks in radiance, shadows spread through the abbot's room with furnace smoke
<lb n="0357c08" ed="J"/>in gloom; wind rises in the meditation hall, the pine tones are faint. A single sandal once came and left traces of transformation; in what place of the five Indias shall we again
<lb n="0357c09" ed="J"/>meet his return? The disciple who understands emptiness cuts off sorrow and joy, yet still sheds tears before the snowy curtain.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0357c10" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357c11" ed="J"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Names of donors for the printing</cb:mulu><head>Names of donors for the printing</head>
<lb n="0357c12" ed="J"/><list rend="no-marker"><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1201">Bhikshus<list rend="no-marker"><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1203">Linghao</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1205">Dayong</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1207">Wuwei</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1209">Zhixing</item></list></item>
<lb n="0357c13" ed="J"/><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1301">Upasaka<list rend="no-marker"><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1304">Shen Qi</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1306">Zhang Xingyao</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1309">Mingheng</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1311">Wu Xianzhang</item>
<lb n="0357c14" ed="J"/><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1401">Wu Xianqi</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1404">Ge Yongtai</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1407">Haifu</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1409">Mingshi</item>
<lb n="0357c15" ed="J"/><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1501">Jiang Zhuzhou</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1504">Mingzhao</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1506">Mingjiao</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1508"><unclear></unclear><unclear></unclear></item></list></item>
<lb n="0357c16" ed="J"/><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1601">Upasika, greatly virtuous<list rend="no-marker"><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1606">Lady Huang</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1608"><unclear></unclear>Lady</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1610">Mingyi</item>
<lb n="0357c17" ed="J"/><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1701">Lady Zhang</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1703">Mingli</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1705">Lady Ge</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1707">Lady Liu</item>
<lb n="0357c18" ed="J"/><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1801">Guangming</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1803">Lady Wu</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1805">Lady Shen</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1807">Lady Zhang</item>
<lb n="0357c19" ed="J"/><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1901">Lady Li</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1903">Lady Xu</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1905">Lady Fan</item><item xml:id="itemJ24p0357c1907">Mingpu</item></list></item></list></cb:div></cb:div>
<lb n="0357c20" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357c21" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357c22" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357c23" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357c24" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357c25" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357c26" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357c27" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357c28" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357c29" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0357c30" ed="J"/>
<pb n="0358a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0358a"/>
<lb n="0358a01" ed="J"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Recorded Sayings</cb:mulu><cb:juan n="1" fun="open"><cb:mulu n="1" type="卷"></cb:mulu><cb:jhead>Recorded Sayings of Monk Zhaozhou, Upper Scroll</cb:jhead></cb:juan>
<lb n="0358a02" ed="J"/><byline cb:type="other">Recorded by the disciple Wenyuan, a student of the Way</byline>
<lb n="0358a03" ed="J"/><byline cb:type="other">Re-collated by Dacan, the Daoist Liren<g ref="#CB01323"/></byline>
<lb n="0358a04" ed="J"/><byline cb:type="other">Recut by Mingsheng, disciple of Yunmen</byline>
<lb n="0358a05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358a0501">The Master asked Nanquan, What is the Way? Quan said, Ordinary mind is it. The Master said, Can it still be directed toward
<lb n="0358a06" ed="J"/>or pursued? Quan said, If you intend it, you deviate. The Master said, If one does not intend, how does one know it is the Way? Quan said, The Way does not belong to knowing
<lb n="0358a07" ed="J"/>or not knowing. Knowing is false awareness; not knowing is blankness. If one truly reaches the undoubting Way, it is like
<lb n="0358a08" ed="J"/>great empty space, vast and open and unobstructed. How could one force right and wrong upon it? At these words the Master suddenly awakened to the mysterious meaning,
<lb n="0358a09" ed="J"/>his mind like a bright moon.</p>
<lb n="0358a10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358a1001">Nanquan ascended the hall. The Master asked, Does the bright side accord, or does the dark side accord? Quan immediately returned to his room. The Master then left the
<lb n="0358a11" ed="J"/>hall and said, This old master, once I asked him, was left with no words to answer. The head monk said, Do not
<lb n="0358a12" ed="J"/>say the master had no words; it is only that you do not understand. The Master struck him and then said, This blow ought to be
<lb n="0358a13" ed="J"/>for the old man in the abbot's seat to take.</p>
<lb n="0358a14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358a1401">The Master asked Nanquan, Where does one who knows there is such a thing go? Quan said, To the patron's house in front of the mountain
<lb n="0358a15" ed="J"/>to become a water buffalo. The Master said, Thank you, master, for the instruction. Quan said, Last night at the third watch
<lb n="0358a16" ed="J"/>the moon came to the window.</p>
<lb n="0358a17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358a1701">While the Master served as stove attendant at Nanquan's, the assembly was on a communal work shift picking vegetables. The Master shouted inside the hall, Fire!
<lb n="0358a18" ed="J"/>Fire! The whole assembly rushed at once to the monks' hall, and the Master then shut the hall door. The assembly had no
<lb n="0358a19" ed="J"/>reply. Quan then tossed the key through the window into the hall, and the Master opened the door.</p>
<lb n="0358a20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358a2001">The Master was drawing water at Nanquan's well tower. Seeing Nanquan pass by, he grabbed a post and hung up his feet,
<lb n="0358a21" ed="J"/>saying, Save me! Save me! Nanquan climbed the ladder and said, One, two, three, four, five. After a little while the Master
<lb n="0358a22" ed="J"/>came down, bowed in thanks, and said, I thank master for just now saving me.</p>
<lb n="0358a23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358a2301">Nanquan's east and west halls were disputing over a cat. Quan came into the hall, lifted up the cat, and said, If you can speak it,
<lb n="0358a24" ed="J"/>I will not cut it; if you cannot speak it, I will cut it. The assembly's responses all failed to meet Quan's meaning, and at once
<lb n="0358a25" ed="J"/>he cut the cat. By evening the Master returned from outside. During greetings, Quan then raised
<lb n="0358a26" ed="J"/>the earlier matter and said, How would you have saved the cat? The Master then put one sandal on
<lb n="0358a27" ed="J"/>his head and went out. Quan said, If you had been there, the cat would have been saved.</p>
<lb n="0358a28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358a2801">The Master asked Nanquan, Difference I will not ask about. What is sameness? Quan placed both hands on the ground, and the Master
<lb n="0358a29" ed="J"/>kicked him over, then returned to the Nirvana Hall crying, Regret! Regret! Hearing this, Quan sent someone to ask, Regret what
<lb n="0358a30" ed="J"/>exactly? The Master said, I regret not giving him two more kicks.</p>
<pb n="0358b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0358b"/>
<lb n="0358b01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358b0101">Nanquan passed by the bathhouse and saw the bath attendant tending the fire. He asked, What are you doing? The man said, Heating the bath.
<lb n="0358b02" ed="J"/>Quan said, Remember to come call the water buffalo for a bath. The bath attendant replied, Yes. That evening, the attendant entered
<lb n="0358b03" ed="J"/>the abbot's room. Quan asked, What are you doing? He said, Inviting the water buffalo to bathe. Quan said, Did you bring rope
<lb n="0358b04" ed="J"/>and halter or not? The bath attendant had no reply. The Master came to greet Quan, and Quan told him the story. The Master said, I have
<lb n="0358b05" ed="J"/>a word. Quan immediately said, Did you bring rope and halter? The Master stepped forward and suddenly grabbed Quan's nose and pulled. Quan
<lb n="0358b06" ed="J"/>said, Yes, yes, but too rough.</p>
<lb n="0358b07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358b0701">The Master asked Nanquan, Beyond the four propositions and apart from the hundred negations, please speak, Master. Quan then returned to his room. The Master
<lb n="0358b08" ed="J"/>said, This old master is usually so glib, but when actually questioned, he cannot set forth a single word. The attendant
<lb n="0358b09" ed="J"/>said, Do not say the master has no words. The Master slapped him. Nanquan then shut the abbot's
<lb n="0358b10" ed="J"/>room door, made a ring of ashes around it, and asked the monks, If you can speak it, I will open the door. Many gave responses
<lb n="0358b11" ed="J"/>but none accorded with Quan's meaning. The Master said, Blue heaven! Blue heaven! Quan then opened the door.</p>
<lb n="0358b12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358b1201">The Master asked Nanquan, Mind is not Buddha, wisdom is not the Way. Is there still fault in this or not? Quan said,
<lb n="0358b13" ed="J"/>There is. The Master said, Where is the fault? Please speak, Master. Quan was about to raise it, and the Master immediately left.</p>
<lb n="0358b14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358b1401">The Master ascended the hall and told the assembly: This matter is exact and direct; even great people of immeasurable stature cannot get out of it. This old monk
<lb n="0358b15" ed="J"/>once went to Guishan, where a monk asked, What is the Patriarch's meaning in coming from the West? Guishan said, Bring me
<lb n="0358b16" ed="J"/>the chair. If one is truly a lineage master, one must receive people with the fundamental matter. Then a monk asked:
<lb n="0358b17" ed="J"/>What is the Patriarch's meaning in coming from the West? The Master said, The cypress tree in the courtyard. The student said, master, do not
<lb n="0358b18" ed="J"/>use an object to instruct people. The Master said, I am not using an object to instruct people. He said, What is the Patriarch's meaning in coming from the West?
<lb n="0358b19" ed="J"/>The Master said, The cypress tree in the courtyard. The Master also said, Ninety years ago this old monk saw under Master Mazu
<lb n="0358b20" ed="J"/>more than eighty good teachers, every one of them a true adept, unlike the teachers of today
<lb n="0358b21" ed="J"/>who grow branches upon branches, all greatly far removed from the sages. Each generation is worse than the
<lb n="0358b22" ed="J"/>last. For example, Nanquan always said, One must proceed among those of a different kind. But how do you understand that? Now
<lb n="0358b23" ed="J"/>yellow-mouthed youngsters stand at crossroads spinning vines of talk, angling for food and seeking bows, gathering
<lb n="0358b24" ed="J"/>three or five hundred people, saying, I am a good teacher, you are students.</p>
<lb n="0358b25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358b2501">A monk asked, What is a pure monastery? The Master said, A girl with hair in two horns. What is the person in the monastery?
<lb n="0358b26" ed="J"/>The Master said, A girl with hair in two horns who is pregnant.</p>
<lb n="0358b27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358b2701">A monk asked, I have heard that master personally saw Nanquan, is that so? The Master said, Zhenzhou produces big radishes.</p>
<lb n="0358b28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358b2801">A monk asked, Where is master's native place? The Master pointed with his hand and said, West, and farther west.</p>
<lb n="0358b29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358b2901">A monk asked, The dharma has no separate dharma; what is dharma? The Master said, Outer emptiness, inner emptiness, inner-and-outer emptiness.</p>
<lb n="0358b30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358b3001">A monk asked, What is the Buddha's true Dharma-body? The Master said, What more is there to dislike?</p>
<pb n="0358c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0358c"/>
<lb n="0358c01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c0101">A monk asked, What is the mind-ground Dharma gate? The Master said, The pattern-board of past and present.</p>
<lb n="0358c02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c0201">A monk asked, What is host within guest? The Master said, This mountain monk does not ask about wives. What is guest within host?
<lb n="0358c03" ed="J"/>The Master said, This old monk has no father-in-law.</p>
<lb n="0358c04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c0401">A monk asked, What is the abiding permanence of all dharmas? The Master said, This old monk does not avoid speaking of the ancestors. The monk asked again,
<lb n="0358c05" ed="J"/>and the Master said, Today I will not answer.</p>
<lb n="0358c06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c0601">The Master ascended the hall and said: Brothers, do not stand long. If there is business, discuss it; if there is none, go sit beneath your robe and bowl
<lb n="0358c07" ed="J"/>and investigate thoroughly. When this old monk traveled, aside from the two meal times, which were places for mixed use of effort, all the rest
<lb n="0358c08" ed="J"/>had no other place to apply mind. If it is not like this, leaving home is far indeed.</p>
<lb n="0358c09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c0901">A monk asked, Among all things, what is the hardest? The Master said, In mutual cursing, I yield you catching mouths; in mutual spitting, I yield you
<lb n="0358c10" ed="J"/>splashing water.</p>
<lb n="0358c11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c1101">A monk asked, What about when it does not stop day or night? The Master said, Among monks there are no such twice-taxed commoners.</p>
<lb n="0358c12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c1201">A monk asked, What is the one phrase? The Master said, If you cling to one phrase, it will age you. The Master also said, If
<lb n="0358c13" ed="J"/>all your life you never leave the monastery grove and do not speak for ten years or five, no one will call you mute, and later<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0358c1301" n="0358c1301"/><anchor xml:id="beg0358c1301" n="0358c1301"/><anchor xml:id="end0358c1301"/>
<lb n="0358c14" ed="J"/>even the Buddha will be unable to do anything with you. If you do not believe it, cut off this old monk's head.</p>
<lb n="0358c15" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c1501">The Master ascended the hall and said: Brothers, you are right in the third grievance. Therefore it is said, Only change the place where your former
<lb n="0358c16" ed="J"/>conduct was carried out; do not change the former person. You and I each left home on our own; lately with nothing to do, you furthermore
<lb n="0358c17" ed="J"/>ask about Chan and ask about the Way, thirty or twenty people gathering their heads to ask, just as if I owed them Chan and the Way.
<lb n="0358c18" ed="J"/>You call me a good teacher, but I am one receiving the cudgel together with you. This old monk does not joke for pleasure; I fear I may burden
<lb n="0358c19" ed="J"/>the ancient ones, and so I speak east and speak west.</p>
<lb n="0358c20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c2001">A monk asked, How should one use mind throughout the twelve hours? The Master said, You are used by the twelve hours; this old monk uses
<lb n="0358c21" ed="J"/>the twelve hours. Which hour are you asking about?</p>
<lb n="0358c22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c2201">A monk asked, What is the host of Zhaozhou? The Master barked, You barrel-hooping fellow. The student answered, Yes.
<lb n="0358c23" ed="J"/>The Master said, Hoop the barrel according to the rule.</p>
<lb n="0358c24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c2401">A monk asked, What is the student's fundamental matter? The Master said, The tree shakes and birds scatter; fish are startled and the water turns muddy.</p>
<lb n="0358c25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c2501">A monk asked, What is a person of little spirit? The Master said, This old monk is not equal to you. The student said, I do not claim victory.
<lb n="0358c26" ed="J"/>The Master said, Then why are you of little spirit?</p>
<lb n="0358c27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c2701">A monk asked, The supreme Way is not difficult, only it dislikes choosing and picking. Is this a den for people of the time? The Master said, Once someone asked me this,
<lb n="0358c28" ed="J"/>and for five years straight I could not sort it out.</p>
<lb n="0358c29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0358c2901">An official asked, When Danxia burned the wooden Buddha, why did the monastery steward's eyebrows and beard fall out? The Master said:
<lb n="0358c30" ed="J"/>In your household, who is it that turns the raw into cooked? The official said, The servant. The Master said, Then that is indeed his
<pb n="0359a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0359a"/>
<lb n="0359a01" ed="J"/>special skill.</p>
<lb n="0359a02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a0201">A monk asked, When the seer Vimukta held Sudhana's hand and he saw Buddhas in motes of dust, how was it? The Master then grasped the monk's
<lb n="0359a03" ed="J"/>hand and said, What do you see?</p>
<lb n="0359a04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a0401">A nun asked, What is the conduct of a śramaṇa? The Master said, Do not bear children. The nun said, master, do not engage
<lb n="0359a05" ed="J"/>with me. The Master said, If I were to engage with you, what would I amount to?</p>
<lb n="0359a06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a0601">A monk asked, What is the host of Zhaozhou? The Master said, A field-granary slave.</p>
<lb n="0359a07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a0701">A monk asked, What is the king asking for xian-tuo-po? The Master said, Tell me, what do you say this old monk wants?</p>
<lb n="0359a08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a0801">A monk asked, What is the mystery within mystery? The Master said, What mystery within mystery are you talking about? Seven within seven, eight within eight.</p>
<lb n="0359a09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a0901">A monk asked, What is xian-tuo-po? The Master said, In quiet places, svaha.</p>
<lb n="0359a10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a1001">A monk asked, What is dharma and non-dharma? The Master said, East, west, south, north. The student said, How should one understand it? The Master
<lb n="0359a11" ed="J"/>said, Up, down, and the four corners.</p>
<lb n="0359a12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a1201">A monk asked, What is the mystery within mystery? The Master said, If that monk were still here, he would be seventy-four or seventy-five.</p>
<lb n="0359a13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a1301">A monk asked, When the king asks for xian-tuo-po, then what? The Master suddenly rose, bowed, and folded his hands.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0359a1301" n="0359a1301"/><anchor xml:id="beg0359a1301" n="0359a1301"/><anchor xml:id="end0359a1301"/></p>
<lb n="0359a14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a1401">A monk asked, What is the Way? The Master said, I dare not, I dare not.</p>
<lb n="0359a15" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a1501">A monk asked, What is dharma? The Master said, Chik chik, she she.</p>
<lb n="0359a16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a1601">A monk asked, How far is Zhaozhou from Zhenfu? The Master said, Three hundred. The student said, How far from Zhenfu to Zhaozhou
<lb n="0359a17" ed="J"/>is it? The Master said, Not separated.</p>
<lb n="0359a18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a1801">A monk asked, What is the mystery within mystery? The Master said, How long has mystery been here? The student said, Mystery has been here a long time.
<lb n="0359a19" ed="J"/>The Master said, Good thing you met this old monk, otherwise mystery would have killed this many-times-born one.</p>
<lb n="0359a20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a2001">A monk asked, What is the student's self? The Master said, Do you still see the cypress tree in the courtyard?<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0359a2001" n="0359a2001"/><anchor xml:id="beg0359a2001" n="0359a2001"/><anchor xml:id="end0359a2001"/></p>
<lb n="0359a21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a2101">The Master ascended the hall and said: If you are one who has long practiced, nothing is not real, nothing is not spanning ancient and present;
<lb n="0359a22" ed="J"/>if you are newly entered among the assembly, you too must investigate principle before it will do. Do not chase after this side's three hundred, five
<lb n="0359a23" ed="J"/>hundred, one thousand, with the two assemblies at the side and the monasteries praising, What a fine abbot. But when asked about the Buddha
<lb n="0359a24" ed="J"/>Dharma, it is just like frying sand to make rice: nothing can be done with it, nothing can be put in the mouth; yet they say others
<lb n="0359a25" ed="J"/>are wrong and I am right, their faces flushed red. This truly comes from worldly people uttering unlawful words. Those who truly wish to understand
<lb n="0359a26" ed="J"/>this meaning, do not let this old monk down.</p>
<lb n="0359a27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359a2701">A monk asked, In the world, speaking Dharma for all sages all belongs to draped forms; how doesmaster instruct people?
<lb n="0359a28" ed="J"/>The Master said, Where do you see this old monk? The student said, Please speak, master. The Master said, The whole hall of monks and teachers
<lb n="0359a29" ed="J"/>does not understand this monk's words. Another monk asked, Please speak, master. The Master said, You speak,
<lb n="0359a30" ed="J"/>and I will listen.</p>
<pb n="0359b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0359b"/>
<lb n="0359b01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359b0101">A monk asked, When true transformation leaves no trace and there is no teacher and disciple, how is it? The Master said, Who told you to come ask? The student
<lb n="0359b02" ed="J"/>said, It was no one else. The Master then struck him.</p>
<lb n="0359b03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359b0301">A monk asked, How is this matter discerned? The Master said, I blame you. The student said, How can it be discerned? The Master said, I
<lb n="0359b04" ed="J"/>blame you for not discerning. The student said, Should one preserve and verify it or not? The Master said, Preserve it or not, see for yourself.</p>
<lb n="0359b05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359b0501">A monk asked, What is a person without knowledge and understanding? The Master said, What matter are you talking about?</p>
<lb n="0359b06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359b0601">A monk asked, What is the meaning of coming from the West? The Master got down from the meditation seat. The student said, Is that it or not? The Master said, This old
<lb n="0359b07" ed="J"/>monk has not yet spoken.</p>
<lb n="0359b08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359b0801">A monk asked, The Buddha-Dharma is long enduring; how should one use mind? The Master said, Did you see the Former Han and Later Han grasp and hold
<lb n="0359b09" ed="J"/>the empire? At death they did not get even half a coin.</p>
<lb n="0359b10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359b1001">A monk asked, People of the world prize jewels; what does a śramaṇa prize? The Master said, Quickly shut your mouth.
<lb n="0359b11" ed="J"/>The student said, If I shut my mouth, is that right or not? The Master said, If your mouth is not shut, how can you discern it?</p>
<lb n="0359b12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359b1201">A monk asked, What is Zhaozhou's one phrase? The Master said, Not even half a phrase. The student said, Is there not even master
<lb n="0359b13" ed="J"/>here? The Master said, This old monk is not one phrase.</p>
<lb n="0359b14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359b1401">A monk asked, How can one avoid being deluded by circumstances? The Master dropped one foot down, and the monk immediately took off a shoe. The Master drew back
<lb n="0359b15" ed="J"/>his foot, and the monk had no words.</p>
<lb n="0359b16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359b1601">A lay official asked, When the Buddha was in the world, all beings took refuge in Buddha. After the Buddha's nirvana, all
<lb n="0359b17" ed="J"/>beings take refuge in what? The Master said, There are not yet any beings. The student said, I am asking right now. The Master said:
<lb n="0359b18" ed="J"/>What Buddha are you still looking for?</p>
<lb n="0359b19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359b1901">A monk asked, Is there anyone who does not repay the four favors and the three realms or not? The Master said, Yes. The student said, Who is it?
<lb n="0359b20" ed="J"/>The Master said, You father-killing fellow, count yourself as only lacking this one question.</p>
<lb n="0359b21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359b2101">A monk asked, What is master's meaning? The Master said, A place with no setting forth.</p>
<lb n="0359b22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359b2201">The Master ascended the hall and said: Brothers, just amend the past and cultivate the future. If you do not amend, there are plenty of places that will stick to you.
<lb n="0359b23" ed="J"/>This old monk has been here more than thirty years, and not once has a Chan master come here. Even if
<lb n="0359b24" ed="J"/>one does come, after one night and one meal he hurries off, chasing after some soft warm place.
<lb n="0359b25" ed="J"/>A monk asked, If suddenly a Chan master comes, what should one say to him? The Master said, A thousand-caty crossbow is not cocked for
<lb n="0359b26" ed="J"/>a mouse. The Master said, Brothers, if one comes from the south, then unload him; if
<lb n="0359b27" ed="J"/>one comes from the north, then load him. Therefore it is said: If those near the top ask the Way, they lose the Way; if those near
<lb n="0359b28" ed="J"/>the bottom ask the Way, they attain the Way. Brothers, when an upright person speaks deviant Dharma, the deviant Dharma also follows the upright;
<lb n="0359b29" ed="J"/>when a deviant person speaks right Dharma, the right Dharma also follows the deviant. In other places, hard to see and easy to recognize; here with me, easy
<lb n="0359b30" ed="J"/>to see and hard to recognize.</p>
<pb n="0359c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0359c"/>
<lb n="0359c01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c0101">A monk asked, A person who cannot get hold of good and evil, can he be liberated alone or not? The Master said, Not liberated alone. The student said:
<lb n="0359c02" ed="J"/>Why not liberated alone? The Master said, Right within good and evil.</p>
<lb n="0359c03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c0301">A nun asked, Leaving aside what is said above, please instruct me, master. The Master barked, Smothered and broken iron bottle.
<lb n="0359c04" ed="J"/>The nun brought an iron bottle filled with water and said, Please answer, master. The Master laughed at her.</p>
<lb n="0359c05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c0501">A monk asked, If the world turns into a black pit, on what road does this one fall? The Master said, Not taking a share. The student
<lb n="0359c06" ed="J"/>said, Who is the one not taking a share? The Master said, A field-granary slave.</p>
<lb n="0359c07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c0701">A monk asked, Only when there is no speech and no intention does it count as a phrase. Since there is no speech, what is called a phrase? The Master said:
<lb n="0359c08" ed="J"/>High yet not precarious, full yet not overflowing. The student said, Right now is master full or overflowing? The Master said:
<lb n="0359c09" ed="J"/>What can I do about your asking me?</p>
<lb n="0359c10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c1001">A monk asked, What is the numinous one? The Master said, On clean ground, a heap of shit. The student said, Please give the master's
<lb n="0359c11" ed="J"/>true meaning. The Master said, Do not bother this old monk.</p>
<lb n="0359c12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c1201">A monk asked, The Dharma-body is non-acting and does not fall into categories; is speech about it permitted or not? The Master said, How would you speak?
<lb n="0359c13" ed="J"/>The student said, Then in that case it cannot be spoken. The Master laughed at him.</p>
<lb n="0359c14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c1401">A monk asked, What is Buddha? What are sentient beings? The Master said, Sentient beings are Buddha, and Buddha is
<lb n="0359c15" ed="J"/>sentient beings. The student said, Of the two, which one is the sentient being? The Master said, Ask, ask.</p>
<lb n="0359c16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c1601">A monk asked, The great Way has no root; how does one respond in chant? The Master said, You just respond in chant. He said, If it has no root, then how
<lb n="0359c17" ed="J"/>can it be? The Master said, Since it is rootless, where can it bind you?</p>
<lb n="0359c18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c1801">A monk asked, Can one truly practicing avoid being measured by ghosts and spirits or not? The Master said, They can measure him. He said, The fault
<lb n="0359c19" ed="J"/>lies where? The Master said, The fault lies in the seeking. He said, Then in that case there is no practice? The Master said:
<lb n="0359c20" ed="J"/>Practice.</p>
<lb n="0359c21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c2101">A monk asked, The lone moon hangs in the sky; from where does its light arise? The Master said, From where does the moon arise?</p>
<lb n="0359c22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c2201">A monk asked, I have heard master say: The Way does not belong to practice, only do not be defiled. What is non-defilement?<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0359c2201" n="0359c2201"/><anchor xml:id="beg0359c2201" n="0359c2201"/><anchor xml:id="end0359c2201"/>
<lb n="0359c23" ed="J"/>The Master said, Examine inside and outside. He said, Does one examine oneself too or not? The Master said, Examine. He said, What fault does oneself<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0359c2301" n="0359c2301"/><anchor xml:id="beg0359c2301" n="0359c2301"/><anchor xml:id="end0359c2301"/>
<lb n="0359c24" ed="J"/>have, to examine oneself? The Master said, What business do you have?</p>
<lb n="0359c25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c2501">The Master ascended the hall and said: This matter is like a bright jewel in the palm: when a Hu comes, a Hu appears; when a Han comes, a Han appears. This old
<lb n="0359c26" ed="J"/>monk uses a blade of grass as a sixteen-foot golden body, and uses the sixteen-foot golden body as a blade of grass.
<lb n="0359c27" ed="J"/>Buddha is affliction, affliction is Buddha. A monk asked, For whom does Buddha become affliction? The Master
<lb n="0359c28" ed="J"/>said, For all people he becomes affliction. He said, How can one avoid it? The Master said, What use is avoidance?</p>
<lb n="0359c29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0359c2901">The Master instructed the assembly, Here this old monk receives people with the fundamental matter. If you want this old monk to follow<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0359c2901" n="0359c2901"/><anchor xml:id="beg0359c2901" n="0359c2901"/><anchor xml:id="end0359c2901"/>
<lb n="0359c30" ed="J"/>their faculties and capacities in receiving them, the Three Vehicles and the Twelve Divisions of Teaching already receive them well enough. If they do not
<pb n="0360a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0360a"/>
<lb n="0360a01" ed="J"/>understand, whose fault is it? Later, when you meet a true adept, you can also say this old monk did not wrong him. Whenever<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0360a0101" n="0360a0101"/><anchor xml:id="beg0360a0101" n="0360a0101"/><anchor xml:id="end0360a0101"/>
<lb n="0360a02" ed="J"/>anyone asks, receive him with the fundamental matter.</p>
<lb n="0360a03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360a0301">A monk asked, From ancient times until now, mind itself is Buddha. If not mind itself, is a student still permitted to discuss it or not?
<lb n="0360a04" ed="J"/>The Master said, Set aside mind itself for the moment; what is there to discuss?</p>
<lb n="0360a05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360a0501">A monk asked, If an ancient mirror is not polished, does it still reflect or not? The Master said, Former life is cause, this life is result.</p>
<lb n="0360a06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360a0601">A monk asked, Before the three blades fall, how is it? The Master said, Dense and bristling. He said, After they fall, how is it? The Master said:
<lb n="0360a07" ed="J"/>Far and open.</p>
<lb n="0360a08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360a0801">A monk asked, What is a person beyond the three realms? The Master said, Cannot be caged or covered.</p>
<lb n="0360a09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360a0901">A monk asked, Before Niutou met the Fourth Patriarch, a hundred birds brought flowers in offering; after meeting him, why did the hundred birds
<lb n="0360a10" ed="J"/>no longer bring flowers in offering? The Master said, Responding to the world, not responding to the world.</p>
<lb n="0360a11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360a1101">A monk asked, What is it like when white clouds are at ease? The Master said, How could it compare to spring wind idle everywhere?</p>
<lb n="0360a12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360a1201">A monk asked, What is the white ox in the open field? The Master said, Under moonlight no color is needed. He said, What does it eat?
<lb n="0360a13" ed="J"/>The Master said, From ancient to present none can chew it. He said, Please answer, Master. The Master said, This old monk answers like this.</p>
<lb n="0360a14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360a1401">The Master instructed the assembly: If mind intends, it at once errs. A monk then asked, What about when mind does not intend? The Master struck him twice
<lb n="0360a15" ed="J"/>and said, Is it that this old monk has let you down, Ācārya?</p>
<lb n="0360a16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360a1601">A monk asked, Whenever there is question and answer, it falls into the faculty of mind; if it does not fall into the faculty of mind, how does the Master respond? The Master said, Ask.
<lb n="0360a17" ed="J"/>The student said, Then please speak, Master. The Master said, Do not make right and wrong here.</p>
<lb n="0360a18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360a1801">A monk asked, When the dragon girl personally offered to the Buddha, what exactly did she offer? The Master made an offering gesture with both hands.</p>
<lb n="0360a19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360a1901">The Master instructed the assembly: Here the Buddha-Dharma, if called difficult is easy, if called easy is difficult. Elsewhere it is hard to see
<lb n="0360a20" ed="J"/>and easy to know; here with this old monk it is easy to see and hard to know. If you can understand it, you may roam freely under heaven. Suppose
<lb n="0360a21" ed="J"/>someone asks, From where do you come? If you say to him, From Zhaozhou, that slanders Zhaozhou; if
<lb n="0360a22" ed="J"/>you say, Not from Zhaozhou, that buries yourself. Everyone, how will you answer him? A monk<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0360a2201" n="0360a2201"/><anchor xml:id="beg0360a2201" n="0360a2201"/><anchor xml:id="end0360a2201"/>
<lb n="0360a23" ed="J"/>asked, If whatever meets the eye slanders master, how can one avoid slandering? The Master said, If you say not slandering, already
<lb n="0360a24" ed="J"/>that is slander.</p>
<lb n="0360a25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360a2501">A monk asked, What is the right path of practice? The Master said, If you understand practice, that is enough. If you do not understand practice,
<lb n="0360a26" ed="J"/>you fall unevenly into others' cause and effect. He also said, I will teach you what to say. If someone asks, just say to him:
<lb n="0360a27" ed="J"/>Zhaozhou comes. If he then asks, What Dharma does Zhaozhou teach? just say to him: When cold, speak of
<lb n="0360a28" ed="J"/>cold; when hot, speak of heat. If he further asks, I am not asking about that matter, then simply say: What matter are you asking about?
<lb n="0360a29" ed="J"/>If he asks again, What Dharma does Zhaozhou teach? then say to him: When master came, he did not tell me to pass on
<lb n="0360a30" ed="J"/>messages. If you want to know Zhaozhou's matter, just go and ask him yourself.</p>
<pb n="0360b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0360b"/>
<lb n="0360b01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360b0101">A monk asked, What about when one does not look before or after? The Master said, Setting aside not looking before or after, whom are you asking?</p>
<lb n="0360b02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360b0201">The Master instructed the assembly: Kāśyapa transmitted to Ānanda. Tell me, to whom did Bodhidharma transmit?
<lb n="0360b03" ed="J"/>A monk asked, Then when the Second Patriarch obtained the marrow, how was it? The Master said, Do not slander the Second Patriarch. The Master also said:
<lb n="0360b04" ed="J"/>Bodhidharma also had words: Those outside get the skin, those inside get the bones. Tell me, those still further inside
<lb n="0360b05" ed="J"/>what do they get?
<lb n="0360b06" ed="J"/>A monk asked, What is the principle of obtaining the marrow? The Master said, Just recognize the skin. Here with this old monk, marrow
<lb n="0360b07" ed="J"/>is not even established. He said, What is marrow then? The Master said, Like this, you have not even touched the skin.</p>
<lb n="0360b08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360b0801">A monk asked, So grand and imposing, is this not the master's proper position? The Master said, Do you know there is one who does not consent
<lb n="0360b09" ed="J"/>to it? The student said, Then is there another position? The Master said, Who is the separate one? The student said, Who is the not-
<lb n="0360b10" ed="J"/>separate one? The Master said, Shout as you please.</p>
<lb n="0360b11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360b1101">A monk asked, A top-top person turns with one nudge; what when a bottom-bottom person comes? The Master said, Are you top-
<lb n="0360b12" ed="J"/>top or bottom-bottom? He said, Please answer, master. The Master said, The words have not yet found their master. He said, I have come seven
<lb n="0360b13" ed="J"/>thousand li to come here; do not make it mind-activity. The Master said, Judging by this one question of yours, can mind-activity be avoided?
<lb n="0360b14" ed="J"/>This monk stayed one night and then left.</p>
<lb n="0360b15" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360b1501">A monk asked, What about one who does not continue what comes from the side? The Master said, Who? The student said, Huiyan. The Master said, Asked what?
<lb n="0360b16" ed="J"/>The student said, One who does not continue what comes from the side. The Master stroked him with his hand.</p>
<lb n="0360b17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360b1701">A monk asked, What is the matter beneath the patched robe? The master said, Do not deceive yourself.</p>
<lb n="0360b18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360b1801">A monk asked, If suchness and ordinary and holy are all dream-talk, what is true speech? The master said, If I say more, then there are
<lb n="0360b19" ed="J"/>two. The student said, Leave the two aside for now; what is true speech? The master said, Om lin.<g ref="#CB03514"/><g ref="#CB03308"/></p>
<lb n="0360b20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360b2001">A monk asked, What is Zhaozhou? The master said, East gate, west gate, south gate, north gate.</p>
<lb n="0360b21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360b2101">A monk asked, What is samadhi? The master said, Not fixed. The student said, Why not fixed? The master said, A living thing,
<lb n="0360b22" ed="J"/>a living thing.</p>
<lb n="0360b23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360b2301">A monk asked, What about when one does not follow all forms of being? The master said, You should learn just so. He said, Is this not then the student’s
<lb n="0360b24" ed="J"/>proper matter? The master said, Follow, follow.</p>
<lb n="0360b25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360b2501">A monk asked, The ancients, in thirty years, drew one bow and loosed two arrows, and only shot half a sage. Today
<lb n="0360b26" ed="J"/>I ask the master to shoot the whole one. The master then got up and left.</p>
<lb n="0360b27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360b2701">The master addressed the assembly, The highest Way is not difficult; it only avoids picking and choosing. As soon as there are words, there is choosing. This old
<lb n="0360b28" ed="J"/>monk is not in clarity. Where then do you see the Patriarch? A monk asked, Since you, master,
<lb n="0360b29" ed="J"/>are not in clarity, what place are you protecting? The master said, I do not know either. The student said, master,
<lb n="0360b30" ed="J"/>since you yourself do not know, why say you are not in clarity? The master said, You have asked the matter; now bow
<pb n="0360c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0360c"/>
<lb n="0360c01" ed="J"/>and withdraw.</p>
<lb n="0360c02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360c0201">The master addressed the assembly, The Dharma is originally unborn, so now there is no extinction. Do not further say: speaking is birth,
<lb n="0360c03" ed="J"/>not speaking is silence. All of you, how is the principle of nonbirth and nonextinction? A monk asked, Is grass
<lb n="0360c04" ed="J"/>nonborn and nonextinct? The master said, This fellow only recognizes dead words.</p>
<lb n="0360c05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360c0501">A monk asked, The highest Way is not difficult; it only avoids picking and choosing. As soon as there are words, there is choosing. How then does the master
<lb n="0360c06" ed="J"/>instruct people? The master said, Why not quote the ancients all the way through? The student said, I only said as far as
<lb n="0360c07" ed="J"/>there. The master said, Just this: The highest Way is not difficult; it only avoids picking and choosing.</p>
<lb n="0360c08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360c0801">Ascending the hall, the master addressed the assembly, Reading sutras is in birth and death; not reading sutras is also in birth and death.
<lb n="0360c09" ed="J"/>Everyone, how do you get out? A monk then asked, What if one leaves neither of the two behind?
<lb n="0360c10" ed="J"/>The master said, If it is real, then yes; if not real, how could you get out of birth and death?</p>
<lb n="0360c11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360c1101">A monk asked, What is it when the sharpness is at the edge of a keen sword? The master said, This old monk is the keen sword; where is the sharpness
<lb n="0360c12" ed="J"/>located?</p>
<lb n="0360c13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360c1301">A monk asked, When great danger arrives, how does one avoid it? The master said, Just right.</p>
<lb n="0360c14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360c1401">Ascending the hall, after a long pause, the master said, Has the whole assembly come yet? They replied, They have all come. The master said, Wait for one more
<lb n="0360c15" ed="J"/>person to come, then I will speak. A monk said, When no one comes, then please tell us, master. The master said, It is very hard
<lb n="0360c16" ed="J"/>to find such a person.</p>
<lb n="0360c17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360c1701">The master addressed the assembly, When mind arises, all dharmas arise; when mind ceases, all dharmas cease. You people,
<lb n="0360c18" ed="J"/>what do you make of this? A monk then asked, What about when there is neither arising nor ceasing? The master said, I allow
<lb n="0360c19" ed="J"/>you that one question.</p>
<lb n="0360c20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360c2001">During an interview, the master said, Bright yet not bright, the way is dim and about to dawn, at which end are you? The monk said:
<lb n="0360c21" ed="J"/>Not at either end. The master said, Then you are in the middle? He said, If one is in the middle, then one is at
<lb n="0360c22" ed="J"/>both ends. The master said, This monk has been with this old monk for quite some time, yet in speaking like this he still cannot
<lb n="0360c23" ed="J"/>get out of the three phrases. And even if you did get out, you would still be within the three phrases. What do you do then? The monk
<lb n="0360c24" ed="J"/>said, I can use the three phrases. The master said, Why did you not say so sooner?</p>
<lb n="0360c25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360c2501">A monk asked, What is the all-sided way? The master said, Leave aside Vajra Zen.</p>
<lb n="0360c26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360c2601">The master addressed the assembly, A patch-robed monk must sit clear through the heads of the reward-body and transformation-body Buddhas, only then will it do. A monk asked, The one who sits clear through
<lb n="0360c27" ed="J"/>the heads of the reward-body and transformation-body Buddhas, what kind of person is that? The master said, Not your realm.</p>
<lb n="0360c28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0360c2801">The master addressed the assembly, The great Way is right before your eyes, yet it is hard to see. A monk then asked, What form is there before us
<lb n="0360c29" ed="J"/>for the student to behold? The master said, Whether you are south of the river or north of the river, as you please. The student said, master, do you not
<lb n="0360c30" ed="J"/>have a skillful means for people? The master said, What did you just ask?</p>
<pb n="0361a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0361a"/>
<lb n="0361a01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361a0101">A monk asked, Upon entering the Dharma-realm, is there still knowing or not? The master said, Who enters the Dharma-realm? The student said, Then
<lb n="0361a02" ed="J"/>having entered the Dharma-realm, is there no knowing? The master said, It is not cold ashes and dead wood; embroidered flowers appear
<lb n="0361a03" ed="J"/>in hundreds of forms. The student said, Is there then functioning at the place of entering the Dharma-realm or not? The master said, What involvement is there?
<lb n="0361a04" ed="J"/>tread."</p>
<lb n="0361a05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361a0501">A monk asked, If it is the ground of ultimate reality, from what place does it come? The master said, Venerable, please state it<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0361a0501" n="0361a0501"/><anchor xml:id="beg0361a0501" n="0361a0501"/><anchor xml:id="end0361a0501"/>
<lb n="0361a06" ed="J"/>once more.</p>
<lb n="0361a07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361a0701">A monk asked, When the myriad conditions all arise, is there one who cannot be deluded or not? The master said, There is. The student said, What is
<lb n="0361a08" ed="J"/>the one who cannot be deluded? The master said, Do you still believe there is Buddha-Dharma? The student said, I believe there is Buddha-Dharma.
<lb n="0361a09" ed="J"/>The ancients have spoken of it; what is the one who cannot be deluded? The master said, Why not ask this old monk?
<lb n="0361a10" ed="J"/>The student said, I already asked. The master said, Deluded.</p>
<lb n="0361a11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361a1101">A monk asked, I wonder whether people of old and people of today are close to one another or not? The master said, Close, yes close,
<lb n="0361a12" ed="J"/>but not one body. The student said, Why not the same? The master said, The dharma-body does not preach Dharma. The student said:
<lb n="0361a13" ed="J"/>If the dharma-body does not preach Dharma, do you, master, teach people or not? The master said, I answer over in Hui. The student
<lb n="0361a14" ed="J"/>said, Then how can you say the dharma-body does not preach Dharma? The master said, I rescue your father over in Hui, and he still
<lb n="0361a15" ed="J"/>never shows his head.</p>
<lb n="0361a16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361a1601">A student asked, “If someone’s practice is ‘not meeting anyone,’ is there still any mutual turning, or not?” The teacher said, “If you can size it up, then there’s mutual turning.” The student<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0361a1601" n="0361a1601"/><anchor xml:id="beg0361a1601" n="0361a1601"/><anchor xml:id="end0361a1601"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0361a1602" n="0361a1602"/><anchor xml:id="beg0361a1602" n="0361a1602"/><anchor xml:id="end0361a1602"/>
<lb n="0361a17" ed="J"/>said, “If you can’t size it up, what mutual turning are you talking about?” The teacher said, “If you don’t put it that way, then it’s just you.” The student<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0361a1701" n="0361a1701"/><anchor xml:id="beg0361a1701" n="0361a1701"/><anchor xml:id="end0361a1701"/>
<lb n="0361a18" ed="J"/>“Then why do you hide yourself?” The teacher said, “I’m looking at you right now, talking with you.” The student said, “Then why say it doesn’t ‘turn’?” The teacher said, “That’s exactly how it should be."
<lb n="0361a19" ed="J"/>Why do you hide yourself? The master said, Right now I am plainly talking with you. The student said, Then why
<lb n="0361a20" ed="J"/>say it does not turn? The master said, It should be just so.<note type="community" resp="ewk">Translation improved</note></p>
<lb n="0361a21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361a2101">The master addressed the assembly, To teach one who can be taught is a matter of this life; to teach one who cannot be taught is
<lb n="0361a22" ed="J"/>an enemy in the third life. If one does not teach, one fears letting all beings fall. Teaching too is enmity.
<lb n="0361a23" ed="J"/>Do you then teach or not? A monk said, I teach. The master said, Do all beings then see you
<lb n="0361a24" ed="J"/>or not? The student said, They do not. The master said, Why do they not? The student said, No form. The master said, Right
<lb n="0361a25" ed="J"/>now, do you see this old monk or not? The student said, master is not a sentient being. The master said, If you know your own fault,
<lb n="0361a26" ed="J"/>that will do.</p>
<lb n="0361a27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361a2701">The master addressed the assembly, The dragon girl offers with intimate heart; it is entirely a natural matter. A monk asked, Since it is a natural offering,
<lb n="0361a28" ed="J"/>why then? The master said, If she did not offer, how would one know it is natural?</p>
<lb n="0361a29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361a2901">The master addressed the assembly, Among eight hundred fellows who make Buddhas, to find one person of the Way is hard indeed.</p>
<lb n="0361a30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361a3001">A monk asked, In a place with no Buddha and no person, is there still cultivation or not? The master said, Aside from those two,
<pb n="0361b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0361b"/>
<lb n="0361b01" ed="J"/>there are hundreds of thousands of millions. The student said, When the person of the Way comes, where are they? The master said, Then you
<lb n="0361b02" ed="J"/>are not cultivating. The monk bowed. The master said, There is a great place to settle you.</p>
<lb n="0361b03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361b0301">A monk asked, What is it when the white clouds do not descend? The master said, This old monk does not understand the upper image. The student said, Is there really no
<lb n="0361b04" ed="J"/>host and guest? The master said, This old monk is host, you are guest; where are the white clouds?</p>
<lb n="0361b05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361b0501">A monk asked, What is it when great skill seems clumsy? The master said, The timber fit for beams is lost.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0361b0501" n="0361b0501"/><anchor xml:id="beg0361b0501" n="0361b0501"/><anchor xml:id="end0361b0501"/></p>
<lb n="0361b06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361b0601">The master addressed the assembly, The single word Buddha is one I do not like to hear. A monk asked, Do you still teach people, master?
<lb n="0361b07" ed="J"/>The master said, I do. The student said, How do you teach people? The master said, Not knowing the mysterious meaning, one vainly thinks of stillness.
<lb n="0361b08" ed="J"/>The student said, If it is mysterious, what is the meaning? The master said, I do not hold the root text. The student said, This
<lb n="0361b09" ed="J"/>is the mysterious; what is the meaning? The master said, Answering you is the meaning.</p>
<lb n="0361b10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361b1001">The master addressed the assembly, Each has their own Chan, each has their own Way. If suddenly someone asks you, How
<lb n="0361b11" ed="J"/>is Chan and how is the Way? how will you answer him? A monk then asked, Since each has Chan and Way, why from ancient times
<lb n="0361b12" ed="J"/>down to now all this talk and speech? The master said, For your wandering soul. The student said, I wonder how one teaches
<lb n="0361b13" ed="J"/>people? The master then withdrew and said nothing.</p>
<lb n="0361b14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361b1401">The master addressed the assembly, Do not pass your time idly; recite Buddha, recite Dharma. A monk then asked, What is the student’s own
<lb n="0361b15" ed="J"/>recitation? The master said, Who is the one reciting? The student said, Without companion. The master shouted, You donkey.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0361b1501" n="0361b1501"/><anchor xml:id="beg0361b1501" n="0361b1501"/><anchor xml:id="end0361b1501"/></p>
<lb n="0361b16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361b1601">Ascending the hall, the master addressed the assembly, If it is the first phrase, then take the patriarchs and Buddhas as teacher; with the second phrase, take humans and gods
<lb n="0361b17" ed="J"/>as teacher; with the third phrase, self-rescue has no remedy. A monk asked, What is the first phrase? The master
<lb n="0361b18" ed="J"/>said, Take the patriarchs and Buddhas as teacher. The master also said, Very good, start from the beginning. The student asked again, and the master said:
<lb n="0361b19" ed="J"/>There go humans and gods again.</p>
<lb n="0361b20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361b2001">The master addressed the assembly, It is not that he does not bring it; it is not that this old monk does not respond. A monk said:
<lb n="0361b21" ed="J"/>With what do you respond, master? The master gave a long sigh. The monk said, Using that as your response,
<lb n="0361b22" ed="J"/>do you not fail the student? The master said, If just now you approved me, then I fail you; if
<lb n="0361b23" ed="J"/>you do not approve me, then I do not fail you.</p>
<lb n="0361b24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361b2401">The master addressed the assembly, Tonight this old monk will answer questions; whoever can ask, come forward. As soon as a monk<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0361b2401" n="0361b2401"/><anchor xml:id="beg0361b2401" n="0361b2401"/><anchor xml:id="end0361b2401"/>
<lb n="0361b25" ed="J"/>came out and bowed, the master said, All along I have thrown a brick to draw jade, and got only a clod.</p>
<lb n="0361b26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361b2601">A monk asked, Does a dog have Buddha-nature or not? The master said, No. The student said, From all Buddhas above down to
<lb n="0361b27" ed="J"/>ants below, all have Buddha-nature; why does a dog not? The master said, Because it has karmic consciousness-nature
<lb n="0361b28" ed="J"/>present.</p>
<lb n="0361b29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361b2901">A monk asked, What is the dharma-body? The master said, The responsive body. He said, I am not asking about the responsive body. The master said, You
<lb n="0361b30" ed="J"/>just attend to the responsive body.</p>
<pb n="0361c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0361c"/>
<lb n="0361c01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361c0101">A monk asked, What is it when the bright moon hangs in the sky? The master said, What is your name, venerable? The student said, Zhuanjia. The master
<lb n="0361c02" ed="J"/>said, Where is the bright moon in the sky?</p>
<lb n="0361c03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361c0301">A monk asked, What is it right at sixteen? The master said, East east, west west. The student said, What is
<lb n="0361c04" ed="J"/>east east, west west? The master said, It cannot be found.</p>
<lb n="0361c05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361c0501">A monk asked, What if the student does not understand at all? The master said, I understand even less. He said, Do you still know,
<lb n="0361c06" ed="J"/>or not? The master said, I am not wood; how could I not know? He said, Excellent not understanding. The master
<lb n="0361c07" ed="J"/>clapped his hands and laughed at him.</p>
<lb n="0361c08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361c0801">A monk asked, What is a person of the Way? The master said, I would say, a Buddha-person.</p>
<lb n="0361c09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361c0901">A monk asked, Whenever there are words and phrases, raising hands or moving feet, all of it falls into the student’s net. Apart from this, please
<lb n="0361c10" ed="J"/>master, speak. The master said, This old monk has eaten the meal, but has not yet had tea.</p>
<lb n="0361c11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361c1101">Magistrate Ma asked, master, do you still cultivate practice or not? The master said, If this old monk cultivated practice, it would be a disaster
<lb n="0361c12" ed="J"/>affair. He said, Since master does not cultivate, whom do you teach to cultivate? The master said, Magistrate, are you a
<lb n="0361c13" ed="J"/>person who cultivates? He said, How am I called a cultivator? The master said, If you do not cultivate, how did you get thrown
<lb n="0361c14" ed="J"/>into the kingly office among men? Fed into this red-frozen crimson ground, with no term for release? The magistrate then
<lb n="0361c15" ed="J"/>shed tears, bowed, and gave thanks.</p>
<lb n="0361c16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361c1601">The master instructed the assembly, saying, "Venerable, it is not that you did not bring it; this old monk is not one who does not respond." He also said:
<lb n="0361c17" ed="J"/>Venerable, do not raise your fist or join your palms; this old monk will not answer with the Chan seat or the whisk.</p>
<lb n="0361c18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361c1801">A monk asked, What is the place where thought and memory do not reach? The master said, Come over to this side. He said, Coming over to this side is
<lb n="0361c19" ed="J"/>exactly the reachable place. What is the place thought does not reach? The master raised his hand and said, What do you call this?
<lb n="0361c20" ed="J"/>He said, I call it a hand. What do you call it, master? The master said, I too can say a hundred names. He said:
<lb n="0361c21" ed="J"/>I cannot match master in a hundred names, but what do you call it then? The master said, Then this is your place where thought and memory
<lb n="0361c22" ed="J"/>do not reach. The monk bowed. The master said, I will teach you the place where thought and memory do reach. He said, What is it? The master
<lb n="0361c23" ed="J"/>said, Shakyamuni’s teaching and the Patriarchs’ teaching are your teachers. He said, Patriarchs and Buddhas, the ancients already spoke of them. What then
<lb n="0361c24" ed="J"/>is the place thought and memory do not reach? The master again raised his finger and said, What do you call this? The monk was silent for a long while. The master
<lb n="0361c25" ed="J"/>said, Why not speak it right on the spot? What more is there to doubt?</p>
<lb n="0361c26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361c2601">A monk asked, What is your family style, master? The master said, This old monk is hard of hearing. Ask louder. The monk asked again,
<lb n="0361c27" ed="J"/>and the master said, You ask about my family style, but I recognize yours.</p>
<lb n="0361c28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0361c2801">A monk asked, What when the myriad conditions all arise? The master said, The myriad conditions all arise. He said, One question and one answer is
<lb n="0361c29" ed="J"/>arising. What is non-arising? The master said, The Chan seat is the non-arising one. As the monk was just about to bow, the master
<lb n="0361c30" ed="J"/>said, Do you remember the question and answer? He said, I remember. The master said, Try to state it. The monk was about to speak.</p>
<pb n="0362a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0362a"/>
<lb n="0362a01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a0101">A monk asked, What is the Buddha before us? The master said, The one in the hall. He said, That is the form-Buddha; what
<lb n="0362a02" ed="J"/>is Buddha? The master said, Mind itself is. He said, Mind itself is still limited. What is Buddha? The master
<lb n="0362a03" ed="J"/>said, No-mind is. The student said, Do you allow the student to choose between mind and no-mind or not? The master said, Mind and
<lb n="0362a04" ed="J"/>no-mind have both already been chosen by you. What more do you want this old monk to say?</p>
<lb n="0362a05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a0501">A monk asked, I have come from far away to rely on the master; I wonder what your family style is? The master said, I do not speak it to people. The student said, Why
<lb n="0362a06" ed="J"/>do you not speak it to people? The master said, That is my family style. The student said, Since master does not speak it to
<lb n="0362a07" ed="J"/>people, what about those who come from the four seas to rely on you? The master said, Are you saying I am not a sea? The student said, I wonder
<lb n="0362a08" ed="J"/>what the matters within the sea are like? The master said, This old monk has hooked one.</p>
<lb n="0362a09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a0901">A monk asked, What kind of person is it that patriarchs and Buddhas cannot approach? The master said, Not patriarchs, not Buddhas. The student said, But
<lb n="0362a10" ed="J"/>what about their not being able to approach? The master said, I tell you: not patriarchs, not Buddhas, not sentient beings, not
<lb n="0362a11" ed="J"/>things, is that enough? The student said, Then what is it? The master said, If it has a name, then it is patriarchs, Buddhas, sentient beings,
<lb n="0362a12" ed="J"/>and so on. The student said, It cannot just be left at that, can it? The master said, I have not yet let you go.</p>
<lb n="0362a13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a1301">A monk asked, What is the ordinary mind? The master said, Foxes, wolves, and wild jackals.</p>
<lb n="0362a14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a1401">A monk asked, By what expedient can one hear what has never been heard? The master said, Leave what has never been heard aside for now; what have you ever heard
<lb n="0362a15" ed="J"/>in the first place?</p>
<lb n="0362a16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a1601">A monk asked, I have heard the teaching speak of the wish-fulfilling jewel that follows forms; what is the original color? The master called the monk by name, and the monk
<lb n="0362a17" ed="J"/>The monk answered. The master said, Come over to this side. The monk then came over and asked again, What is original color? The master said:
<lb n="0362a18" ed="J"/>For now, just follow the colors along.</p>
<lb n="0362a19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a1901">A monk asked, Does a person of ordinary mind still receive instruction or not? The master said, I do not pass through another's gate.
<lb n="0362a20" ed="J"/>The student said, If so, then would that not sink the person over there? The master said, Excellent ordinary mind.</p>
<lb n="0362a21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a2101">A monk asked, What is the thing to be safeguarded in practice? The master said, Through the end of future ages, it cannot be picked out.</p>
<lb n="0362a22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a2201">A monk asked, What is a person of great cultivation? The master said, The temple officers are.</p>
<lb n="0362a23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a2301">A monk asked, When a student has just arrived and knows nothing at all of the gate and threshold, what then? The master said, What is your name, Reverend?
<lb n="0362a24" ed="J"/>The student said, Huinan. The master said, Fine indeed, not knowing.</p>
<lb n="0362a25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a2501">A monk asked, This student wants to learn, yet he slanders the master; how can he avoid slandering? The master said, What is your name?
<lb n="0362a26" ed="J"/>The student said, Daojiao. The master said, Go sit quietly, you rice bin.</p>
<lb n="0362a27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a2701">A monk asked, What is the master's great meaning? The master said, No great, no small. The student said, Is that then the master's
<lb n="0362a28" ed="J"/>great meaning? The master said, If there is the slightest bit, then for ten thousand kalpas it will not do.</p>
<lb n="0362a29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a2901">A monk asked, All dharmas are originally at rest, but people themselves make trouble. Whose words are these? The master said, Step out and you die.</p>
<lb n="0362a30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362a3001">A monk asked, Not Buddha, not thing, not sentient being, this is a cutting statement. What is an uncutting
<pb n="0362b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0362b"/>
<lb n="0362b01" ed="J"/>statement? The master said, Above heaven and below heaven, I alone am honored.</p>
<lb n="0362b02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b0201">A monk asked, What is Vairocana's perfect circle? The master said, This old monk left home from youth and has never had failing eyes.
<lb n="0362b03" ed="J"/>The student said, Does the master still teach people or not? The master said, May you always see Vairocana's perfect circle.</p>
<lb n="0362b04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b0401">A monk asked, While Buddhas and patriarchs were present, they transmitted to one another. After Buddhas and patriarchs are gone, who transmits? The master said, From ancient times
<lb n="0362b05" ed="J"/>until now it all falls to this old monk. The student said, I do not know what is transmitted. The master said, Every one of them all
<lb n="0362b06" ed="J"/>belongs to birth and death. The monk said, You must not bury the patriarchs. The master said, Transmit what?</p>
<lb n="0362b07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b0701">A monk asked, What is it like when both ordinary and holy are exhausted? The master said, May you become a great worthy. This old monk is one who obstructs Buddhas
<lb n="0362b08" ed="J"/>and patriarchs.</p>
<lb n="0362b09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b0901">A monk asked, I heard of Zhaozhou from afar, but after arriving why do I not see him? The master said, It is this old monk's fault.</p>
<lb n="0362b10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b1001">A monk asked, The bright moon is in the sky. I do not know how things are in the room. The master said, Since leaving home, this old monk has never
<lb n="0362b11" ed="J"/>made a livelihood. The student said, Then the master does not act for the present age? The master said, One's own illness
<lb n="0362b12" ed="J"/>cannot be cured, how could one cure all illnesses? The student said, What is the student to do with no support? The master said, If you rely,
<lb n="0362b13" ed="J"/>you step on the ground. If you do not rely, then east or west as you please.</p>
<lb n="0362b14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b1401">A monk asked, What is it like when mind is in mind and mind cannot measure it? The master said, Measure whom? The student said, Measure myself. The master<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0362b1401" n="0362b1401"/><anchor xml:id="beg0362b1401" n="0362b1401"/><anchor xml:id="end0362b1401"/>
<lb n="0362b15" ed="J"/>said, There are not two.</p>
<lb n="0362b16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b1601">A monk asked, What is it like when no boundary or mark is seen? The master pointed to the clean bottle and said, What is this? The student said, A clean bottle.
<lb n="0362b17" ed="J"/>The master said, Excellent not seeing boundary marks.</p>
<lb n="0362b18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b1801">A monk asked, What is returning to the root? The master said, The moment you intend it, you miss.</p>
<lb n="0362b19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b1901">A monk asked, Without leaving words and phrases, how can one attain solitary liberation? The master said, Leaving words and phrases is solitary liberation. The student said:
<lb n="0362b20" ed="J"/>Just now no one told me to come here. The master said, Then what brought you here? The student said, Why does the master
<lb n="0362b21" ed="J"/>not pick it out? The master said, I picked it out long ago.</p>
<lb n="0362b22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b2201">A monk asked, Not mind and not identical with wisdom, please give one phrase, master. The master said, This old monk falls behind you.</p>
<lb n="0362b23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b2301">A monk asked, What is the ultimate? The master said, The ultimate. The student said, Which one is the ultimate? The master said, This old
<lb n="0362b24" ed="J"/>monk is the ultimate; you do not understand how to ask this question. The student said, It is not that I do not ask. The master said, The ultimate
<lb n="0362b25" ed="J"/>is in what place?</p>
<lb n="0362b26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b2601">A monk asked, What is it like when not hanging even an inch of thread? The master said, Not hanging what? The student said, Not hanging an inch of thread.
<lb n="0362b27" ed="J"/>The master said, Excellent not hanging an inch of thread.</p>
<lb n="0362b28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b2801">A monk asked, What about a person like one saving his head from fire? The master said, Just study. The student said, Where? The master said:
<lb n="0362b29" ed="J"/>Do not occupy another's rank.</p>
<lb n="0362b30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362b3001">A monk asked, In the empty kalpa, who is the master? The master said, This old monk sits right there. The student said, What
<pb n="0362c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0362c"/>
<lb n="0362c01" ed="J"/>dharma do you preach? The master said, I preach what you asked.</p>
<lb n="0362c02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362c0201">A monk asked, It is said of old, empty clarity illumines itself. What is self-illumination? The master said, It is not called another's illumination.
<lb n="0362c03" ed="J"/>The student said, What about where illumination does not reach? The master said, Your words have fallen.</p>
<lb n="0362c04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362c0401">A monk asked, What is the target, the exact point? The master said, When not a single thought has arisen.</p>
<lb n="0362c05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362c0501">A monk asked, What is the Dharma King? The master said, The great king of the province is. The monk said, Is the master not? The master said:
<lb n="0362c06" ed="J"/>Are you planning rebellion? Altogether you do not recognize even one king.</p>
<lb n="0362c07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362c0701">A monk asked, What is Buddha-mind? The master said, You are mind, I am Buddha; whether you serve or not, see for yourself. The student
<lb n="0362c08" ed="J"/>said, The master is certainly there, but can one still serve or not? The master said, You teach me and let me see.</p>
<lb n="0362c09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362c0901">A monk asked, Among the three bodies, which is the original body? The master said, Not one may be lacking.</p>
<lb n="0362c10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362c1001">A monk asked, I do not know who is patriarch in this land. The master said, Since Bodhidharma came here, all are so. The student said:
<lb n="0362c11" ed="J"/>Which patriarchal generation is the master? The master said, I do not fall into rank. The student said, Where is it? The master
<lb n="0362c12" ed="J"/>said, In your ears.</p>
<lb n="0362c13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362c1301">A monk asked, Not abandoning the root and not chasing branches, what is the right path? The master said, Fine monk, child of leaving home. The student
<lb n="0362c14" ed="J"/>said, This student has never left home. The master said, Take refuge in Buddha, take refuge in Dharma. The student said, I do not know whether
<lb n="0362c15" ed="J"/>there is even a home to leave or not. The master said, You must directly leave home. The student said, Where should one place
<lb n="0362c16" ed="J"/>it? The master said, For now, sit at home.</p>
<lb n="0362c17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362c1701">A monk asked, A clear-eyed person sees everything, but does he still see form or not? The master said, Strike it away. The student said, How
<lb n="0362c18" ed="J"/>can one strike it? The master said, Do not use force. The student said, If one does not use force, how can one strike it? The master said, If you use
<lb n="0362c19" ed="J"/>force, you go astray.</p>
<lb n="0362c20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362c2001">A monk asked, The great meaning of patriarchs and Buddhas, for what kind of person is it? The master said, Only for people of the present time. The student said, What is to be done
<lb n="0362c21" ed="J"/>if one cannot manage it? The master said, Whose fault is that? The student said, How should one undertake it? The master said, Nowadays no one
<lb n="0362c22" ed="J"/>can undertake it. The monk said, Then there is no support to rely on? The master said, Yet you cannot do without this old monk.</p>
<lb n="0362c23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362c2301">A monk asked, What about one who has finished the matter? The master said, Precisely great cultivation. The student said, I do not know whether the master still
<lb n="0362c24" ed="J"/>cultivates or not. The master said, Putting on clothes and eating food. The student said, Putting on clothes and eating food are ordinary things, I do not know whether that is
<lb n="0362c25" ed="J"/>cultivation or not. The master said, You tell me first, what do I do every day?</p>
<lb n="0362c26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362c2601">Vice Minister Cui asked, Does a great good spiritual friend also enter hell or not? The master said, This old monk is the last to
<lb n="0362c27" ed="J"/>enter. Cui said, If he is a great good spiritual friend, why enter hell? The master said, If this old monk
<lb n="0362c28" ed="J"/>did not enter, how could I get to see you, Vice Minister?</p>
<lb n="0362c29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0362c2901">A monk asked, What if there is a difference of a hair's breadth? The master said, Heaven and earth are far apart. The monk said, What if there is no difference of a hair's breadth?
<lb n="0362c30" ed="J"/>The master said, Heaven and earth are far apart.</p>
<pb n="0363a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0363a"/>
<lb n="0363a01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a0101">A monk asked, What are eyes that do not sleep? The master said, Ordinary eyes, fleshly eyes. He also said, Though one has not yet attained heavenly
<lb n="0363a02" ed="J"/>eyes, the power of the fleshly eyes is like this. The student said, What are sleeping eyes? The master said, Buddha-eye and Dharma-eye
<lb n="0363a03" ed="J"/>are sleeping eyes.</p>
<lb n="0363a04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a0401">A monk asked, At Dayu Ridge one caught up in time, so why could it not be lifted? The master picked up his robe and said:
<lb n="0363a05" ed="J"/>Where did you get this from? The monk said, I am not asking about this. The master said, Then in that case it cannot be lifted.</p>
<lb n="0363a06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a0601">A monk asked, If not joined and not dispersed, how does one distinguish? The master said, You have one, I have one. The monk said, This
<lb n="0363a07" ed="J"/>one is joining, what is dispersing? The master said, You are just joining.</p>
<lb n="0363a08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a0801">A monk asked, What is the road that does not miss? The master said, Knowing mind and seeing nature is the road that does not miss.</p>
<lb n="0363a09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a0901">A monk asked, If a bright pearl is in the palm, does it shine or not? The master said, Shining is certainly not absent, but what do you call the pearl?</p>
<lb n="0363a10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a1001">A monk asked, What is it like when the numinous sprout has no root? The master said, Where have you come from? The monk said, From Taiyuan.
<lb n="0363a11" ed="J"/>The master said, Excellent rootless.</p>
<lb n="0363a12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a1201">A monk asked, What if a student intends to become a Buddha? The master said, That is terribly strenuous. The monk said, If there is no effort,
<lb n="0363a13" ed="J"/>then what? The master said, Then go ahead and become Buddha.</p>
<lb n="0363a14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a1401">A monk asked, This student is dull and sunk in rising and falling; how can he get out? The master just sat there. The monk said, I truly
<lb n="0363a15" ed="J"/>am asking the master. The master said, Where are you making one rise and one sink?</p>
<lb n="0363a16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a1601">A monk asked, Neither in the ordinary nor in the holy, how can one avoid the road of two ends? The master said, Remove the two ends<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0363a1601" n="0363a1601"/><anchor xml:id="beg0363a1601" n="0363a1601"/><anchor xml:id="end0363a1601"/>
<lb n="0363a17" ed="J"/>and come answer me. The monk did not understand. The master said, Not understanding, from where does it arise? Here, it arises from this old
<lb n="0363a18" ed="J"/>monk. When you are in the marketplace, from where does it arise? The monk said, Why is the master not fixed? The master
<lb n="0363a19" ed="J"/>said, I teach you, why not say, Today the wind is fine.</p>
<lb n="0363a20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a2001">A monk asked, What is a great icchantika person? The master said, If this old monk answers you, will you believe it? The monk said, The
<lb n="0363a21" ed="J"/>master's word is weighty, how would I dare not believe? The master said, It is hard to find an icchantika person.</p>
<lb n="0363a22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a2201">A monk asked, A greatly shameless person, where can he be placed? The master said, He cannot be placed here. The monk said:
<lb n="0363a23" ed="J"/>If he suddenly sticks his head out, what then? The master said, Take him away.</p>
<lb n="0363a24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a2401">A monk asked, What is it like when function does not appear? The master said, Function is certainly not absent, but who is appearance?</p>
<lb n="0363a25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a2501">A monk asked, In the empty kalpa, is there still anyone cultivating or not? The master said, What do you call an empty kalpa? The monk said:
<lb n="0363a26" ed="J"/>Not a single thing is. The master said, Only this is called cultivation. What do you call an empty kalpa?</p>
<lb n="0363a27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a2701">A monk asked, What is leaving home? The master said, Do not tread on high reputation; do not seek foul ruin.</p>
<lb n="0363a28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363a2801">A monk asked, Without pointing to a single dharma, what is the master's dharma? The master said, This old monk does not speak Maoshan dharma.
<lb n="0363a29" ed="J"/>The monk said, Since you do not speak Maoshan dharma, what is the master's dharma? The master said, I told you I do not speak
<lb n="0363a30" ed="J"/>Maoshan dharma. The monk said, Is this then it or not? The master said, This old monk has never taken this
<pb n="0363b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0363b"/>
<lb n="0363b01" ed="J"/>and shown it to people.</p>
<lb n="0363b02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363b0201">A monk asked, What is the single path of liberation right before one's eyes? The master said, No two and also no three. The monk said, Right before my eyes
<lb n="0363b03" ed="J"/>there is a path; is the student permitted to advance or not? The master said, If so, then a thousand miles, ten thousand miles.</p>
<lb n="0363b04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363b0401">A monk asked, What is the matter beyond Vairocana? The master said, This old monk is under your feet. The monk said, master
<lb n="0363b05" ed="J"/>why are you under the student's feet? The master said, You originally do not know there is a matter beyond.</p>
<lb n="0363b06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363b0601">A monk asked, What is fitting the head? The master said, It is you not fitting the head. The monk said, What is not fitting the head?
<lb n="0363b07" ed="J"/>The master said, Pick it out in the previous phrase.</p>
<lb n="0363b08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363b0801">A monk asked, What is the master's exact meaning? The master said, Stop, stop, no need to speak. My Dharma is subtle and hard to conceive.</p>
<lb n="0363b09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363b0901">A monk asked, What is it like when clear and limpid, without a speck? The master said, Falling into a pit, dropping into a ditch. The monk said, What fault is there? The master
<lb n="0363b10" ed="J"/>said, Why do you wrong such a person?</p>
<lb n="0363b11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363b1101">A monk asked, I do not know, when one leaves home and vows to seek unsurpassed bodhi, what then? The master said, Before leaving home, one is driven by
<lb n="0363b12" ed="J"/>bodhi; after leaving home, one can make bodhi serve.</p>
<lb n="0363b13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363b1301">A scholar, seeing the master's staff in his hand, said, Buddha does not take away sentient beings' wishes, is that so? The master
<lb n="0363b14" ed="J"/>said, Yes. The scholar said, Then may I ask the master for the staff in your hand? The master said:
<lb n="0363b15" ed="J"/>A gentleman does not take what another favors. The scholar said, I am no gentleman. The master said, This old monk
<lb n="0363b16" ed="J"/>is no Buddha either.</p>
<lb n="0363b17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363b1701">The master was out and saw an old woman planting rice. He said, If you suddenly met a fierce tiger, what would you do? The old woman said, No
<lb n="0363b18" ed="J"/>single dharma can match the mind. The master said, Drop it. The old woman said, Tu. The master said, Hard to have one like this around.</p>
<lb n="0363b19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363b1901">A scholar took leave, saying, I have troubled the master here for a long time and have nothing with which to repay
<lb n="0363b20" ed="J"/>the master. Another day I will come back as a donkey to repay the master. The master said, Then how is this old monk to
<lb n="0363b21" ed="J"/>get a saddle?</p>
<lb n="0363b22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363b2201">The master went to Daowu's place. As soon as he entered the monks' hall, Daowu said, A single arrow from Nanquan has come. The master said, Watch the
<lb n="0363b23" ed="J"/>arrow. Daowu said, It has passed. The master said, It hit.</p>
<lb n="0363b24" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0363b25" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0363b26" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0363b27" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0363b28" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0363b29" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0363b30" ed="J"/><cb:juan n="1" fun="close"><cb:jhead>Recorded Sayings of Master Zhaozhou, Upper Scroll<note place="inline">End.</note></cb:jhead></cb:juan>
<milestone n="2" unit="juan"/>
<pb n="0363c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0363c"/>
<lb n="0363c01" ed="J"/><cb:juan n="2" fun="open"><cb:mulu n="2" type="卷"></cb:mulu><cb:jhead>Recorded Sayings of Master Zhaozhou, Middle Scroll</cb:jhead></cb:juan>
<lb n="0363c02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363c0201">The master ascended the hall and addressed the assembly, A golden Buddha does not pass through the furnace, a wooden Buddha does not pass through fire, a clay Buddha does not pass through water,
<lb n="0363c03" ed="J"/>the true Buddha sits within. Bodhi, nirvana, suchness, Buddha-nature, all are clothes clinging to the body, and also
<lb n="0363c04" ed="J"/>are called afflictions. If one does not ask, there are no afflictions. In the ground of ultimate reality, where can anything be set? If one mind does not
<lb n="0363c05" ed="J"/>arise, the ten thousand dharmas are without fault. Just investigate the principle and sit for twenty or thirty years. If you do not understand, cut off this old
<lb n="0363c06" ed="J"/>monk's head and take it. Dreams, illusions, empty flowers are vainly grasped. If mind is not different, the ten thousand dharmas are also thus. Since<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0363c0601" n="0363c0601"/><anchor xml:id="beg0363c0601" n="0363c0601"/><anchor xml:id="end0363c0601"/>
<lb n="0363c07" ed="J"/>it is not obtained from outside, what further binds you? Like a sheep, why blindly pick up things and stuff them in your mouth?
<lb n="0363c08" ed="J"/>What are you doing? This old monk once heard Master Yaoshan say, If someone asks, just tell him to shut the dog's mouth. This old
<lb n="0363c09" ed="J"/>monk also says, Shut the dog's mouth. Taking me is filth; not taking me is purity. It is just like a hunting dog
<lb n="0363c10" ed="J"/>that only wants to get something to eat. Where can Buddhadharma be placed? A thousand people, ten thousand people, all
<lb n="0363c11" ed="J"/>are fellows seeking Buddha; not one seeker of the Way can be found. If you would be a disciple of the Empty King, do not let
<lb n="0363c12" ed="J"/>the sickness of mind, the hardest to cure, remain. Before there was a world, this nature was already there. When the world perishes, this nature does not
<lb n="0363c13" ed="J"/>perish. From the moment you have seen this old monk once, you are no longer someone else, but simply the host himself. This one
<lb n="0363c14" ed="J"/>why seek outside again? At such a time, do not turn your head and change your face, or you will lose it.</p>
<lb n="0363c15" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363c1501">A monk asked, When the hundred bones all crumble and scatter, yet one thing remains ever numinous, what then? The master said, This morning again the wind
<lb n="0363c16" ed="J"/>has risen.</p>
<lb n="0363c17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363c1701">A monk asked, I will not ask about the Three Vehicles and the twelve divisions of teaching. What is the Patriarch's meaning in coming from the West? The master said:
<lb n="0363c18" ed="J"/>The water buffalo has calved, go and look well. The monk said, I do not understand this meaning. The master said, I also
<lb n="0363c19" ed="J"/>do not know.</p>
<lb n="0363c20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363c2001">A monk asked, What is it like when the myriad nations come to court? The master said, Meeting people, you cannot call out.</p>
<lb n="0363c21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363c2101">A monk asked, Throughout the twelve hours, how does one wash out and sift? The master said, The Naih River is muddy, the western stream runs swift. The monk said:
<lb n="0363c22" ed="J"/>Can one still see Manjusri or not? The master said, You muddle-eyed fellow, where have you been coming and going?</p>
<lb n="0363c23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363c2301">Asked, What is the place of practice? The master said, You come from the place of practice, you go to the place of practice; in your whole body
<lb n="0363c24" ed="J"/>it is the place of practice. What place is not?</p>
<lb n="0363c25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363c2501">Asked, What is it like before the sprout has emerged? The master said, Smell it and your skull splits. He said, What about when one does not smell it,
<lb n="0363c26" ed="J"/>then what? The master said, There is no such idle time.</p>
<lb n="0363c27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363c2701">Asked, What is counting and measure? The master said, One, two, three, four, five. He said, What about the matter not bound by counting and measure,
<lb n="0363c28" ed="J"/>then what? The master said, One, two, three, four, five.</p>
<lb n="0363c29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0363c2901">Asked, In what world is there no day and night? The master said, Right now, is it day or night? He said, I am not asking
<lb n="0363c30" ed="J"/>about right now. The master said, What can you do about this old monk?</p>
<pb n="0364a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0364a"/>
<lb n="0364a01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a0101">Asked, Kashyapa's upper robe, not treading the Caoxi road, who gets to wear it? The master said, Empty space
<lb n="0364a02" ed="J"/>does not appear in the world; practitioners all do not know.</p>
<lb n="0364a03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a0301">Asked, What is mingled yet not mixed? The master said, This old monk eats vegetables and keeps the long fast. He said, Can one still attain tran-
<lb n="0364a04" ed="J"/>scendence or not? The master said, Break the fast.</p>
<lb n="0364a05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a0501">Asked, What are the words of the ancients? The master said, Listen carefully, listen carefully.</p>
<lb n="0364a06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a0601">Asked, What is the student's proper business? The master said, If it is thus, what are you dissatisfied with?</p>
<lb n="0364a07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a0701">Asked, The ten thousand dharmas return to one; where does the one return? The master said, In Qingzhou I made a cloth robe,
<lb n="0364a08" ed="J"/>it weighed seven jin.</p>
<lb n="0364a09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a0901">Asked, What is a home-leaver? The master said, He does not bow to the Son of Heaven, and his parents bow back to him.</p>
<lb n="0364a10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a1001">Asked, What is the matter face to face? The master said, You are a face to face fellow.</p>
<lb n="0364a11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a1101">Asked, Who is the person beyond Buddha? The master said, The one right there leading the plow ox is.</p>
<lb n="0364a12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a1201">Asked, What is urgency? The master said, This old monk speaks like this; what do you make of it? He said, I do not understand. The master
<lb n="0364a13" ed="J"/>said, I tell you: in haste, put on your boots and stand on water; ride a horse to Chang'an, and the tips of your boots are still not
<lb n="0364a14" ed="J"/>wet.</p>
<lb n="0364a15" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a1501">Asked, When the four mountains close in, what then? The master said, No road that is Zhaozhou.</p>
<lb n="0364a16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a1601">Asked, When the ancient hall has no king, what then? The master coughed once. He said, Then is this the minister addressing the throne
<lb n="0364a17" ed="J"/>below? The master said, The thief's body is already exposed.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0364a1701" n="0364a1701"/><anchor xml:id="beg0364a1701" n="0364a1701"/><anchor xml:id="end0364a1701"/></p>
<lb n="0364a18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a1801">Asked, How old are you, Master? The master said, A string of prayer beads cannot count it out.</p>
<lb n="0364a19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a1901">Asked, Whose Dharma heir are you, Master? The master said, Congshen.</p>
<lb n="0364a20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a2001">Asked, If someone elsewhere suddenly asks, What Dharma does Zhaozhou teach? how should one reply? The master said, Salt
<lb n="0364a21" ed="J"/>is expensive, rice is cheap.</p>
<lb n="0364a22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a2201">Asked, What is Buddha? The master said, Are you Buddha?</p>
<lb n="0364a23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a2301">Asked, What is leaving home? The master said, How could you get to see this old monk?</p>
<lb n="0364a24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a2401">Asked, What about where buddhas and patriarchs are unbroken? The master said, No leakage.</p>
<lb n="0364a25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a2501">Asked, Original source, please instruct me. The master said, The original source has no illness. He said, What about the place of realization? The master said,
<lb n="0364a26" ed="J"/>The realized person knows. He said, At such a time, then what? The master said, Give it a name for me.</p>
<lb n="0364a27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a2701">Asked, When it is pure one without mixture, what then? The master said, A very fine question indeed.</p>
<lb n="0364a28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a2801">Asked, Does a person of nonaction and stillness fall into dead emptiness or not? The master said, Falls into dead emptiness.
<lb n="0364a29" ed="J"/>He said, Ultimately, how is it? The master said, Become a donkey, become a horse.</p>
<lb n="0364a30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364a3001">Asked, What is the Patriarch's meaning in coming from the West? The master said, The bed leg is it. He said, Is that it or not?
<pb n="0364b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0364b"/>
<lb n="0364b01" ed="J"/>The master said, If it is, then take it off and carry it away.</p>
<lb n="0364b02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b0201">Asked, When it is clear and spotless, what then? The master said, Here, this old monk does not employ hired laborers.</p>
<lb n="0364b03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b0301">Asked, When even a phoenix cannot fly there, what then? The master said, From where did it arise?</p>
<lb n="0364b04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b0401">Asked, In the ground of ultimate reality, when not a single mote is accepted, what then? The master said, Everything is altogether in there.</p>
<lb n="0364b05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b0501">Asked, What is the one phrase? The master answered, Yes. The monk asked again. The master said, I do not suffer from deafness.</p>
<lb n="0364b06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b0601">Asked, Does a newborn child already possess the six consciousnesses or not? The master said, Hitting a ball on swift flowing water.</p>
<lb n="0364b07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b0701">Asked, When everything arrives, what then? The master said, It is still a hundred paces short of this old monk.</p>
<lb n="0364b08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b0801">Asked, What is the master's family style? The master said, This old monk left home from childhood, and shook off the ragged means of living
<lb n="0364b09" ed="J"/>completely.</p>
<lb n="0364b10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b1001">Asked, Please speak apart from the four propositions. The master said, This old monk is always right in there.</p>
<lb n="0364b11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b1101">Asked, Why does Bianque, the king of physicians, have illness? The master said, Bianque, king of physicians, does not leave the bed and pillow.
<lb n="0364b12" ed="J"/>He also said, One drop of sweet dew moistens the great thousand worlds universally.</p>
<lb n="0364b13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b1301">Asked, What is the white ox in the open ground? The master said, That beast.</p>
<lb n="0364b14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b1401">Asked, What is the mark of a great person? The master said, Look at it sideways. He said, That is still approaching from below the steps,<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0364b1401" n="0364b1401"/><anchor xml:id="beg0364b1401" n="0364b1401"/><anchor xml:id="end0364b1401"/>
<lb n="0364b15" ed="J"/>is it not? The master said, This old monk has no time to go chasing that idle fellow.</p>
<lb n="0364b16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b1601">Asked, The moment a thought arises, one falls among humans and gods; if there is utterly no thought, one falls among kin and attendants what then?
<lb n="0364b17" ed="J"/>The master said, Not only this old monk, even an adept could not answer you.</p>
<lb n="0364b18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b1801">Asked, Whenever there is action, it all falls into dregs; please answer without acting. The master scolded the nun, saying, Bring
<lb n="0364b19" ed="J"/>water here and add it to the boiling cauldron.</p>
<lb n="0364b20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b2001">Asked, What is prajna paramita? The master said, Maha prajna paramita.</p>
<lb n="0364b21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b2101">Asked, What is the lion that bites people? The master said, I take refuge in Buddha, I take refuge in Dharma, I take refuge in Sangha do not
<lb n="0364b22" ed="J"/>bite this old monk.</p>
<lb n="0364b23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b2301">Asked, Leaving aside words and phrases, please speak, Master. The master coughed.</p>
<lb n="0364b24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b2401">Asked, How can one avoid slandering the ancients and not betray their kindness? The master said, How do you do it, Reverend?</p>
<lb n="0364b25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b2501">Asked, What is the one phrase? The master said, What are you saying?</p>
<lb n="0364b26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b2601">Asked, What is the one phrase? The master said, Two phrases.</p>
<lb n="0364b27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b2701">Asked, What about saying only the Buddha alone is a good spiritual friend? The master said, Demon talk.</p>
<lb n="0364b28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b2801">Asked, What is bodhi? The master said, This one is icchantika.</p>
<lb n="0364b29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b2901">Asked, What is the mark of a great person? The master said, A fine descendant indeed.</p>
<lb n="0364b30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364b3001">Asked, When it is silent and without support, what then? The master said, This old monk is behind your back.</p>
<pb n="0364c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0364c"/>
<lb n="0364c01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c0101">Asked, What is the monastery? The master said, What else is there? He said, Who is the person in the monastery,
<lb n="0364c02" ed="J"/>then? The master said, This old monk and you, Reverend.</p>
<lb n="0364c03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c0301">Asked, When two dragons fight over a jewel, who gets it? The master said, This old monk just watches.</p>
<lb n="0364c04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c0401">Asked, Who is the person beyond cause and effect? The master said, If not for your asking, Reverend, this old monk truly would not
<lb n="0364c05" ed="J"/>know.</p>
<lb n="0364c06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c0601">Asked, The many blind men feel the elephant and each speaks differently how is the true elephant? The master said, Without falsity, it is just
<lb n="0364c07" ed="J"/>not known.</p>
<lb n="0364c08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c0801">Asked, What is the first phrase? The master coughed. He said, Is that it or not? The master said, This old monk coughs
<lb n="0364c09" ed="J"/>and may not?</p>
<lb n="0364c10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c1001">Asked, Does the great ocean receive all streams or not? The master said, The great ocean says it does not know. He said, Why
<lb n="0364c11" ed="J"/>does it not know? The master said, It never says, I receive all streams.</p>
<lb n="0364c12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c1201">Asked, What is Vairocana? The master said, Vairocana, Vairocana.</p>
<lb n="0364c13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c1301">Asked, Do the buddhas have a teacher or not? The master said, They do. He said, Who is the teacher of the buddhas? The master said,
<lb n="0364c14" ed="J"/>Amitabha Buddha, Amitabha Buddha.</p>
<lb n="0364c15" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c1501">Asked, Who is the student's teacher? The master said, Clouds have the force of leaving the mountain; water has no sound of plunging into the ravine. He said,
<lb n="0364c16" ed="J"/>I am not asking about that. The master said, It is just that you do not recognize your teacher.</p>
<lb n="0364c17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c1701">Asked, Everywhere they all speak from the mouth; how do you show people, Master? The master struck the brazier with his heel
<lb n="0364c18" ed="J"/>to show him. He said, Is that it or not? The master said, You have just recognized this old monk's heel.</p>
<lb n="0364c19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c1901">Asked, When one does not walk the great way, what then? The master said, A fellow who peddles contraband salt. He said, And when one does walk the great way,
<lb n="0364c20" ed="J"/>what then? The master said, Bring me your official permit.</p>
<lb n="0364c21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c2101">Asked, What is the original body? The master said, Ever since he recognized this old monk, this fellow
<lb n="0364c22" ed="J"/>has not been different. He said, Then am I separated from you by a lifetime, Master? The master said, Not only this life; for a thou-
<lb n="0364c23" ed="J"/>sand lives, ten thousand lives, you still would not know this old monk.</p>
<lb n="0364c24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c2401">Asked, What is the Patriarch's meaning in coming from the West? The master said, How long has the gourd been hanging on the east wall
<lb n="0364c25" ed="J"/>there?</p>
<lb n="0364c26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c2601">Asked, When square and round do not fit, what then? The master said, Not square, not round. He said, At such a time, then what?
<lb n="0364c27" ed="J"/>The master said, It is square, it is round.</p>
<lb n="0364c28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c2801">Asked, When practitioners meet, what then? The master said, Present lacquerware.</p>
<lb n="0364c29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0364c2901">Asked, Why can truth not be contemplated? The master said, Truth is not nonexistent, but contemplation cannot get it. He said, In the end
<lb n="0364c30" ed="J"/>what is it? The master said, Lost the truth.</p>
<pb n="0365a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0365a"/>
<lb n="0365a01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a0101">Asked, When going does not reach and asking does not reach, what then? The master said, Reaching and not reaching a practitioner
<lb n="0365a02" ed="J"/>sees as snot and spit. He said, What is the matter within that? The master spat on the ground.</p>
<lb n="0365a03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a0301">Asked, What is the Patriarch's meaning in coming from the West? The master said, If you do not call it the Patriarch's meaning, still
<lb n="0365a04" ed="J"/>it is not yet there. He said, What about the original? The master said, Four eyes facing each other; there is no second master.</p>
<lb n="0365a05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a0501">Asked, Without possessing form and bearing, can one still understand or not? The master said, Right now, do you understand or not?</p>
<lb n="0365a06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a0601">Asked, What is a person of great shamelessness? The master said, All are endowed with the inconceivable.</p>
<lb n="0365a07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a0701">Asked, I intend to go south and study a bit of Buddhadharma how about it? The master said, When you go south,
<lb n="0365a08" ed="J"/>if you see a place with Buddha, hurry past it; where there is no Buddha, do not stay. He said, Then the student
<lb n="0365a09" ed="J"/>has no support? The master said, Willow fluff, willow fluff.</p>
<lb n="0365a10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a1001">Asked, What is the urgent point? The master said, One question, one answer.</p>
<lb n="0365a11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a1101">Asked, Without relying on three inches, does it still depend on the present time or not? The master said, I speak following you; how do you
<lb n="0365a12" ed="J"/>understand it?</p>
<lb n="0365a13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a1301">Asked, What is the master's family style? The master said, In the vast universe, people are without number. He said, I ask the mas-
<lb n="0365a14" ed="J"/>ter not to answer with words. The master said, Should this old monk be like that?</p>
<lb n="0365a15" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a1501">Asked, When two dragons fight over a jewel, who gets it? The master said, The loser loses nothing; the winner has no use for it.</p>
<lb n="0365a16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a1601">Asked, What is the mark of a great person? The master said, What is it?</p>
<lb n="0365a17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a1701">A layman offered a kasaya and asked, Wearing such a robe, would one not betray the ancients? The master
<lb n="0365a18" ed="J"/>threw down his whisk and said, Is this ancient or is this present?</p>
<lb n="0365a19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a1901">Asked, What is the conduct of a shramana? The master said, Extend the hands, not the feet.</p>
<lb n="0365a20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a2001">Asked, Before Niutou met the Fourth Patriarch, what was it like? The master said, Full of firewood, full of water. He said, After meeting him,
<lb n="0365a21" ed="J"/>what then? The master said, Full of firewood, full of water.</p>
<lb n="0365a22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a2201">Asked, What is the student's own self? The master said, Have you eaten your gruel yet? He said, I have eaten gruel. The master<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0365a2201" n="0365a2201"/><anchor xml:id="beg0365a2201" n="0365a2201"/><anchor xml:id="end0365a2201"/>
<lb n="0365a23" ed="J"/>said, Go wash your bowl.</p>
<lb n="0365a24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a2401">Asked, What is Vairocana? The master said, Has the white camel come yet? He said, It has come. The master said, Lead it<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0365a2401" n="0365a2401"/><anchor xml:id="beg0365a2401" n="0365a2401"/><anchor xml:id="end0365a2401"/>
<lb n="0365a25" ed="J"/>away and feed it grass.</p>
<lb n="0365a26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a2601">Asked, What is teacherless wisdom? The master said, This old monk has never taught you, Reverend.</p>
<lb n="0365a27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a2701">Asked, What is the intimate phrase? The master said, The words have fallen.</p>
<lb n="0365a28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a2801">Asked, Without borrowing the mouth, is discussion still permitted or not? The master said, Exactly at this time. He said, Then please discuss it, Master.
<lb n="0365a29" ed="J"/>The master said, This old monk has never come out.</p>
<lb n="0365a30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365a3001">Asked, For what purpose did the Second Patriarch cut off his arm? The master said, Powdering bones and shattering the body. He said, To make offering to what
<pb n="0365b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0365b"/>
<lb n="0365b01" ed="J"/>person? The master said, An offering to the one who comes.</p>
<lb n="0365b02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b0201">Asked, Why does the Bodhisattva of boundless body not see the Tathagata's crown mark? The master said, You are the rev-
<lb n="0365b03" ed="J"/>erend.</p>
<lb n="0365b04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b0401">Asked, By day there is sunlight, by night there is firelight what is divine light? The master said, Sunlight, firelight.</p>
<lb n="0365b05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b0501">Asked, What is the right place to ask? The master said, Wrong. He said, What is the place of not asking? The master said, In the previous
<lb n="0365b06" ed="J"/>phrase, distinguish it.</p>
<lb n="0365b07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b0701">Asked, What is the mark of a great person? The master touched his face with his hand, folded his hands, and composed his expression.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0365b0701" n="0365b0701"/><anchor xml:id="beg0365b0701" n="0365b0701"/><anchor xml:id="end0365b0701"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0365b0702" n="0365b0702"/><anchor xml:id="beg0365b0702" n="0365b0702"/><anchor xml:id="end0365b0702"/></p>
<lb n="0365b08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b0801">Asked, What is nonaction? The master said, This is action.</p>
<lb n="0365b09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b0901">Asked, What is the Patriarch's meaning in coming from the West? The master said, The ox got lost from the pen.</p>
<lb n="0365b10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b1001">Asked, I have come from afar; please instruct me, Master. The master said, The moment you enter the gate, it would be fitting to spit in your face.</p>
<lb n="0365b11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b1101">Asked, What is the straight and direct road? The master said, Has the boatman from Huainan arrived yet? He said, This student
<lb n="0365b12" ed="J"/>does not understand. The master said, For now, be glad you have arrived.</p>
<lb n="0365b13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b1301">Asked, Does the cypress tree have buddha nature or not? The master said, It does. He said, When will it become Buddha? The master said,
<lb n="0365b14" ed="J"/>When empty space falls to the ground. He said, When will empty space fall to the ground? The master said, When the cypress tree becomes Buddha.</p>
<lb n="0365b15" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b1501">Asked, What is the meaning of coming from the West? The master said, Why did you curse this old monk in the courtyard? He said, This stu-
<lb n="0365b16" ed="J"/>dent has done no wrong. The master said, This old monk cannot go curse you in the courtyard.</p>
<lb n="0365b17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b1701">Asked, What is the meaning of coming from the West? The master said, Hair grows on wooden teeth.</p>
<lb n="0365b18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b1801">Asked, When a poor son comes, what do you give him? The master said, Not poor. He said, What can be done, if he seeks out the Master?
<lb n="0365b19" ed="J"/>The master said, Just keep to poverty.</p>
<lb n="0365b20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b2001">Asked, Why does the Bodhisattva of boundless body not see the Tathagata's crown mark? The master said, As if through gauze
<lb n="0365b21" ed="J"/>silk.</p>
<lb n="0365b22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b2201">Asked, Who gets to drink the sweet dew of the devas? The master said, Thank you for bringing it.</p>
<lb n="0365b23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b2301">A monk asked, "What about one who has gone beyond heaven and earth?" The master said, "When there is such a person, report it to me."</p>
<lb n="0365b24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b2401">Asked, "What is the monastery?" The master said, "The three gates and the Buddha hall."</p>
<lb n="0365b25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b2501">Asked, "What is the unborn and undying?" The master said, "Originally it is unborn; now too it has no extinction."</p>
<lb n="0365b26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b2601">Asked, "Who is the lord of Zhaozhou?" The master said, "The great king is."</p>
<lb n="0365b27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b2701">Asked, "At a critical moment, please speak, Master." The master said, "Pissing is a small matter; it must be that this old monk himself goes, only then"
<lb n="0365b28" ed="J"/>can it be done."</p>
<lb n="0365b29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365b2901">Asked, "What is the sixteen-foot golden body?" The master said, "Tuck the collar under the armpit." The monk said, "I do not understand." The master
<lb n="0365b30" ed="J"/>said, "If you do not understand, ask someone to cut it."</p>
<pb n="0365c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0365c"/>
<lb n="0365c01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c0101">Asked, "What when a student has doubts?" The master said, "Big convenience, small convenience." The student said, "A big doubt." The master said,<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0365c0101" n="0365c0101"/><anchor xml:id="beg0365c0101" n="0365c0101"/><anchor xml:id="end0365c0101"/>
<lb n="0365c02" ed="J"/>"For a big convenience, the northeast corner; for a small convenience, behind the monks' hall."</p>
<lb n="0365c03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c0301">Asked, "Who is the person above Buddha?" The master got down from the Chan couch, looked him up and down, and said, "This fellow
<lb n="0365c04" ed="J"/>is so tall and big; cut him into three stakes and it would do. Why ask about above and below?"</p>
<lb n="0365c05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c0501">A nun asked, "What is the most secret meaning?" The master pinched her with his hand. She said, "master still has this thing!"
<lb n="0365c06" ed="J"/>The master said, "It is you who have this thing."</p>
<lb n="0365c07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c0701">The master addressed the assembly, saying, "Thirty years ago, in the south, at the side of the brazier, this old monk had a saying about no host and
<lb n="0365c08" ed="J"/>no guest. Right up to now, no one has brought it up."</p>
<lb n="0365c09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c0901">Asked, "The king supports you so generously, Master; with what do you repay him?" The master said, "Reciting Buddha." He said,
<lb n="0365c10" ed="J"/>"Even a poor fellow can recite Buddha." The master said, "Call the attendant and give him one coin."</p>
<lb n="0365c11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c1101">Asked, "What is the master's family style?" The master said, "Though the screen is broken, its frame still remains."</p>
<lb n="0365c12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c1201">Asked, "What is the meaning of non-moving?" The master said, "Tell me, that wild duck flying from east to
<lb n="0365c13" ed="J"/>west, did it move or not?"</p>
<lb n="0365c14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c1401">Asked, "What is the meaning of coming from the West?" The master said, "Where did you get this news from?"</p>
<lb n="0365c15" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c1501">Asked, "What is a person in the dust?" The master said, "Give some tea-and-salt money."</p>
<lb n="0365c16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c1601">Asked, "The Tripitaka Master Great-Ear searched for the National Teacher a third time and did not see him. Where, then, was the National Teacher
<lb n="0365c17" ed="J"/>?" The master said, "Inside the Tripitaka Master's nostrils."</p>
<lb n="0365c18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c1801">Asked, "What about when a blind turtle meets the hole in a floating log?" The master said, "That is no accidental matter."</p>
<lb n="0365c19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c1901">Asked, "What if one dwells long in cliffs and valleys?" The master said, "Why not hide away?"</p>
<lb n="0365c20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c2001">Asked, "What is the great meaning of the Buddha Dharma?" The master said, "Bow." As the monk was about to continue speaking, the master called
<lb n="0365c21" ed="J"/>the novice Wenyuan. Wenyuan came, and the master shouted, "Where have you just come from?"</p>
<lb n="0365c22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c2201">Asked, "What is one's own original intention?" The master said, "This old monk has no need of an ox-cleaver."</p>
<lb n="0365c23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c2301">Asked, "For long I have heard of Zhaozhou's stone bridge, but on arriving I see only a log bridge." The master said, "Venerable, you only see
<lb n="0365c24" ed="J"/>the log bridge and do not see Zhaozhou's stone bridge?" He said, "What is Zhaozhou's stone bridge?" The master said, "Cross
<lb n="0365c25" ed="J"/>over, come across."</p>
<lb n="0365c26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c2601">Another monk asked, "For long I have heard of Zhaozhou's stone bridge, but on arriving I see only a log bridge." The master said, "You only
<lb n="0365c27" ed="J"/>see the log bridge and do not see Zhaozhou's stone bridge?" He said, "What is the stone bridge?" The master said, "It carries donkeys
<lb n="0365c28" ed="J"/>and carries horses."</p>
<lb n="0365c29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0365c2901">Asked, "Master, what is your surname?" The master said, "Changzhou has it." He said, "How many years of the cycle are you?" The master said, "Suzhou
<lb n="0365c30" ed="J"/>has it."</p>
<pb n="0366a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0366a"/>
<lb n="0366a01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a0101">The master ascended the hall and said, "As soon as there is right and wrong, the mind is lost in confusion. Is there still any part for answering words?" There was
<lb n="0366a02" ed="J"/>a monk who came out and struck the attendant once, saying, "Why do you not answer the master?" The master then returned to the abbot's quarters. Later
<lb n="0366a03" ed="J"/>the attendant asked for instruction, "Did that monk just now understand or not?" The master said, "The one sitting sees the one standing; the one standing
<lb n="0366a04" ed="J"/>sees the one sitting."</p>
<lb n="0366a05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a0501">Asked, "What is the Way?" The master said, "The one outside the wall." He said, "I am not asking about that." The master said, "What Way are you asking
<lb n="0366a06" ed="J"/>about?" He said, "The Great Way." The master said, "The Great Way leads to Chang'an."</p>
<lb n="0366a07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a0701">Asked, "What about sweeping away dust and seeing Buddha?" The master said, "Sweeping away dust is not absent, but seeing Buddha cannot be attained."</p>
<lb n="0366a08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a0801">Asked, "What is the body without illness?" The master said, "The four elements and the five skandhas."</p>
<lb n="0366a09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a0901">Asked, "What is an icchantika?" The master said, "Why not ask about bodhi?" He said, "What is bodhi?" The master
<lb n="0366a10" ed="J"/>said, "Just this is the icchantika."</p>
<lb n="0366a11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a1101">Sometimes the master curled his fingers and said, "This old monk calls it a fist. What do you all call it?" A monk said,
<lb n="0366a12" ed="J"/>"How can the master present an object to people?" The master said, "I do not present objects to people. If I were to present an object
<lb n="0366a13" ed="J"/>to you, Venerable, I would bury you." He said, "What about this then?" The master at once said farewell.</p>
<lb n="0366a14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a1401">Asked, "One question and one answer always fall into heavenly demons and outsiders; but if one remains silent, one also falls into his trap and net.
<lb n="0366a15" ed="J"/>What is Zhaozhou's family style?" The master said, "You do not know how to ask." He said, "Please answer, Master." The master
<lb n="0366a16" ed="J"/>said, "According to your case, you deserve twenty blows."</p>
<lb n="0366a17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a1701">The master addressed the assembly, saying, "As soon as there is right and wrong, the mind is lost in confusion. Is there still any part for answering words?" There was
<lb n="0366a18" ed="J"/>a monk who came out, slapped the novice once, and then left. The master returned to the abbot's quarters. The next day he asked
<lb n="0366a19" ed="J"/>the attendant, "Where is that monk from yesterday?" The attendant said, "He left right then." The master
<lb n="0366a20" ed="J"/>said, "For thirty years I played at riding horses, and got thrown by a donkey."</p>
<lb n="0366a21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a2101">Asked, "If someone comes in such a way, does the master receive him or not?" The master said, "I receive him." He said, "If someone does not come in such a way,
<lb n="0366a22" ed="J"/>does the master receive him or not?" The master said, "I receive him." He said, "One who comes in such a way is received by the master; one who does not come in such a way,
<lb n="0366a23" ed="J"/>how does the master receive him?" The master said, "Stop, stop, no need to speak. My Dharma is subtle and hard to conceive."</p>
<lb n="0366a24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a2401">The King of Zhen Prefecture asked, "Reverend Master, at your age, how many teeth remain?" The master said, "Only one tooth."
<lb n="0366a25" ed="J"/>The king said, "How can you eat things?" The master said, "Though only one, every bite catches."</p>
<lb n="0366a26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a2601">Asked, "What is the student's jewel?" The master said, "Ask loudly." The monk bowed. The master said, "You do not know how to ask.
<lb n="0366a27" ed="J"/>Why not say, 'I do not ask about high or low; what is the student's jewel?' Why not ask like that?" The monk
<lb n="0366a28" ed="J"/>then asked again. The master said, "I should have let that fellow go."</p>
<lb n="0366a29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a2901">Asked, "When the two sides are silent and still, how does the master expound?" The master said, "This year there are no storms."</p>
<lb n="0366a30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366a3001">Asked, "With the whole assembly gathered like clouds, what should be discussed?" The master said, "Today we drag timbers and raise the monks' hall." He said,
<pb n="0366b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0366b"/>
<lb n="0366b01" ed="J"/>"Could it be that just this is receiving students?" The master said, "This old monk does not know backgammon, nor
<lb n="0366b02" ed="J"/>does he know long rows."</p>
<lb n="0366b03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b0301">Asked, "What is the true human body?" The master said, "Spring, summer, autumn, winter." He said, "Then the student
<lb n="0366b04" ed="J"/>finds it hard to understand?" The master said, "You asked me about the true human body."</p>
<lb n="0366b05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b0501">Asked, "What is the great meaning of the Buddha Dharma?" The master said, "What is your name?" He said, "So-and-so." The master said, "In the Hanyuan Hall,
<lb n="0366b06" ed="J"/>in the Golden Valley Garden."</p>
<lb n="0366b07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b0701">Asked, "Who is the teacher of the seven Buddhas?" The master said, "When wanting to sleep, sleep; when wanting to rise, rise."</p>
<lb n="0366b08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b0801">Asked, "The Way is not outside things, and outside things is not the Way. What is the Way outside things?" The master struck him. He said, "master,
<lb n="0366b09" ed="J"/>do not hit me. Later on you may hit the wrong person." The master said, "Dragons and snakes are easy to distinguish, but patch-robed monks<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0366b0901" n="0366b0901"/><anchor xml:id="beg0366b0901" n="0366b0901"/><anchor xml:id="end0366b0901"/>
<lb n="0366b10" ed="J"/>are hard to fool."</p>
<lb n="0366b11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b1101">When the master saw the king enter the monastery, he did not rise, but slapped his own knee with his hand and said, "Do you understand?" The king said, "I do not
<lb n="0366b12" ed="J"/>understand." The master said, "I left home young and now am old; when I see people, I lack the strength to get down from the Chan couch."<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0366b1201" n="0366b1201"/><anchor xml:id="beg0366b1201" n="0366b1201"/><anchor xml:id="end0366b1201"/></p>
<lb n="0366b13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b1301">Asked, "What is honest speech?" The master said, "Your mother is ugly."</p>
<lb n="0366b14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b1401">Asked, "What about one who from the past until now does not forget?" The master said, "Do not bind the mind to what cannot be attained; always think on
<lb n="0366b15" ed="J"/>and recollect all Buddhas of the ten directions."</p>
<lb n="0366b16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b1601">Asked, "What is honest speech?" The master said, "Eat an iron staff."</p>
<lb n="0366b17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b1701">Asked, "What is the matter above Buddha?" The master clapped his hands and laughed loudly.</p>
<lb n="0366b18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b1801">Asked, "One lamp lights hundreds and thousands of lamps; from where does the first lamp issue?" The master kicked out
<lb n="0366b19" ed="J"/>one sandal, and then said, "A real adept would not ask like that."</p>
<lb n="0366b20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b2001">Asked, "Returning to the root one gets the point, but following illumination one loses the source. What then?" The master said, "This old monk does not answer that question."
<lb n="0366b21" ed="J"/>He said, "Please answer, Master." The master said, "Should it be like this?"</p>
<lb n="0366b22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b2201">Asked, "What is the place of no thinking?" The master said, "Speak quickly, speak quickly."</p>
<lb n="0366b23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b2301">Asked, "Ascending Tusita at night and descending Jambudvipa by day, why does the mani jewel not appear therein?" The master said,
<lb n="0366b24" ed="J"/>"What are you saying?" The monk asked again. The master said, "Vipashin Buddha set his mind on this early, and right up to now has not
<lb n="0366b25" ed="J"/>attained the marvel."</p>
<lb n="0366b26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b2601">Asked, "What about the place beyond thought?" The master said, "Speak at once, speak at once."</p>
<lb n="0366b27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b2701">Asked, "What is the jewel in the robe?" The master said, "What fault is there with this question?" He said, "This is the question;
<lb n="0366b28" ed="J"/>what is the jewel?" The master said, "If so, then even the robe is lost."</p>
<lb n="0366b29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b2901">Asked, "What when for ten thousand miles there is no inn?" The master said, "Lodge in the Chan monastery."</p>
<lb n="0366b30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366b3001">Asked, "Does a dog still have Buddha-nature or not?" The master said, "In front of every house gate the road leads to Chang'an."</p>
<pb n="0366c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0366c"/>
<lb n="0366c01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c0101">Asked, "If presented face to face, does that fully express the great meaning or not?" The master said, "Lower your voice." He said, "What about where it cannot be taken in
<lb n="0366c02" ed="J"/>?" The master said, "I tell you, lower your voice."</p>
<lb n="0366c03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c0301">Asked, "What is the phrase right before us?" The master said, "This old monk is not as good as you."</p>
<lb n="0366c04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c0401">Asked, "Who is the one that comes forth?" The master said, "Buddhas and bodhisattvas."</p>
<lb n="0366c05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c0501">Asked, "What about before the numinous grass has sprouted?" The master said, "If you smell it, your skull splits." He said, "What if one does not smell it?"
<lb n="0366c06" ed="J"/>The master said, "Like a dead man standing." He said, "Is the student still allowed to harmonize?" The master said, "When people come, do not
<lb n="0366c07" ed="J"/>tell them."</p>
<lb n="0366c08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c0801">Asked, "Are the patriarchs' meaning and the teachings' meaning the same or different?" The master said, "Just left home and not yet ordained, and already asking people everywhere."<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0366c0801" n="0366c0801"/><anchor xml:id="beg0366c0801" n="0366c0801"/><anchor xml:id="end0366c0801"/></p>
<lb n="0366c09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c0901">Asked, "What is the holy?" The master said, "Not ordinary." He said, "What is ordinary?" The master said, "Not holy." He said, "When not
<lb n="0366c10" ed="J"/>ordinary and not holy, then what?" The master said, "A fine Chan monk."</p>
<lb n="0366c11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c1101">Asked, "When two mirrors face each other, which is brightest?" The master said, "Your eyelids, Venerable, cover Mount Sumeru."</p>
<lb n="0366c12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c1201">Asked, "I have only recently entered the monasteries; I beg the master for instruction." The master said, "Blue heaven, blue heaven."</p>
<lb n="0366c13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c1301">Asked, "What when the earlier phrase is gone and the later phrase is hard to make clear?" The master said, "The moment you name it, it will not do." He said,<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0366c1301" n="0366c1301"/><anchor xml:id="beg0366c1301" n="0366c1301"/><anchor xml:id="end0366c1301"/>
<lb n="0366c14" ed="J"/>"Please distinguish it, Master." The master said, "Ask, ask."</p>
<lb n="0366c15" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c1501">Asked, "What when it is steep and hard to climb?" The master said, "This old monk does not go to the summit of high peaks."</p>
<lb n="0366c16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c1601">Asked, "Who is the one not companion to the ten thousand dharmas?" The master said, "Not a person."</p>
<lb n="0366c17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c1701">Asked, "Please, Master, a phrase of the middle way in the school vehicle." The master said, "Today I have no money for the official."</p>
<lb n="0366c18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c1801">Asked, "I will not ask differently; please, Master, do not answer differently." The master said, "Strange."</p>
<lb n="0366c19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c1901">Asked, "Outside the teachings of the three vehicles, how do you receive people?" The master said, "Since this world came to be, the sun and moon have never
<lb n="0366c20" ed="J"/>changed."</p>
<lb n="0366c21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c2101">Asked, "When the three places do not connect, how does one leave consciousness?" The master said, "Consciousness is outside the matter."</p>
<lb n="0366c22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c2201">Asked, "When all capacities gather together, what is the matter within?" The master said, "My eyes are originally straight; I do not speak
<lb n="0366c23" ed="J"/>of the matter within."</p>
<lb n="0366c24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c2401">Asked, "Who is the one who does not stop on pure ground?" The master said, "You are not yet among those people." He said, "Then
<lb n="0366c25" ed="J"/>who is among them?" The master said, "Stop."</p>
<lb n="0366c26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c2601">Asked, "What is the source of the ten thousand dharmas?" The master said, "Beams, rafters, and pillars." He said, "The student does not understand." The master
<lb n="0366c27" ed="J"/>said, "Brackets and joined hands, and still you do not understand."</p>
<lb n="0366c28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c2801">Asked, "What when not a single thing is brought along?" The master said, "Put it down."</p>
<lb n="0366c29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0366c2901">Asked, "If on the road one meets a realized person, and one does not respond with speech or silence, with what should one respond?" The master said, "A person
<lb n="0366c30" ed="J"/>comes from Chenzhou and does not get a letter from Xuzhou."</p>
<pb n="0367a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0367a"/>
<lb n="0367a01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a0101">Asked, "Opening the mouth is conditioned action; what is unconditioned?" The master pointed with his hand and said, "This is
<lb n="0367a02" ed="J"/>unconditioned." He said, "This is conditioned; what is unconditioned?" The master said, "Unconditioned." He said, "This
<lb n="0367a03" ed="J"/>is conditioned." The master said, "It is conditioned."</p>
<lb n="0367a04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a0401">The master addressed the assembly, saying, "The single word Buddha, I do not like to hear."</p>
<lb n="0367a05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a0501">Asked, "Does the master still teach people or not?" The master said, "Buddha, Buddha."</p>
<lb n="0367a06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a0601">Asked, "When the present moment is exhausted, what is the exact place?" The master said, "Exhaust the present moment, and do not ask about that
<lb n="0367a07" ed="J"/>one." He said, "What is the exact?" The master said, "I tell you, do not ask." He said, "How can it be seen?" The master said,
<lb n="0367a08" ed="J"/>"Great has no outside; small has no inside."</p>
<lb n="0367a09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a0901">Asked, "What when one is beyond the four propositions and cuts off the hundred negations?" The master said, "This old monk does not recognize death." He said, "This
<lb n="0367a10" ed="J"/>is the master's own matter." The master said, "Exactly so." He said, "Please give instruction, master." The master said, "Beyond
<lb n="0367a11" ed="J"/>the four propositions and the hundred negations cut off, with what would I instruct you?"</p>
<lb n="0367a12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a1201">Asked, "What is the master's family style?" The master said, "Inside, not one thing; outside, nothing sought."</p>
<lb n="0367a13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a1301">Asked, "What is returning to the root and attaining the point?" The master said, "If I answer you, it misses."</p>
<lb n="0367a14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a1401">Asked, "What is the mind of doubt?" The master said, "If I answer you, it also misses."</p>
<lb n="0367a15" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a1501">Asked, "Does one who has left home still become worldly or not?" The master said, "One who leaves home is at once a seat-master. Leave or not leave,
<lb n="0367a16" ed="J"/>this old monk does not manage it." He said, "Why do you not manage it?" The master said, "Thus, that itself is leaving home."</p>
<lb n="0367a17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a1701">Asked, "What about a disciple without a teacher?" The master said, "The undefiled wisdom-nature is originally complete." He also said,
<lb n="0367a18" ed="J"/>"This is a disciple without a teacher."</p>
<lb n="0367a19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a1901">Asked, "What when no boundary marks are seen?" The master said, "Why is it thus?"</p>
<lb n="0367a20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a2001">Asked, "What when clear yet not pure, muddled yet not turbid?" The master said, "Not pure, not turbid." He said, "What
<lb n="0367a21" ed="J"/>is that?" The master said, "Rather pitiful." He said, "What is mastery in all directions?" The master said, "Leave aside the Vajra
<lb n="0367a22" ed="J"/>Chan."</p>
<lb n="0367a23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a2301">A monk asked, What is the jewel in the bag? The master said, What is there to dislike? The monk said, When its use is inexhaustible, how is it? The master
<lb n="0367a24" ed="J"/>said, Is your own one still weighty or not? He also said, When used it is heavy; when not used it is light.</p>
<lb n="0367a25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a2501">A monk asked, What is the Patriarch's true meaning? The master coughed up phlegm and spat. The monk said, What about the matter within that? The master again
<lb n="0367a26" ed="J"/>spat on the ground.</p>
<lb n="0367a27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a2701">A monk asked, What is the conduct of a śramaṇa? The master said, Conduct free from conduct.</p>
<lb n="0367a28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a2801">A monk asked, Please point out the place of true rest. The master said, If I point it out, it is not rest.</p>
<lb n="0367a29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a2901">A monk asked, How is it when there is no question? The master said, It goes against ordinary speech.</p>
<lb n="0367a30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367a3001">A monk asked, How is it when the four mountains press in? The master said, There are no tracks of escape.</p>
<pb n="0367b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0367b"/>
<lb n="0367b01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b0101">A monk asked, When one gets here and cannot speak, then what? The master said, It cannot be spoken. The monk said, How should one speak? The master
<lb n="0367b02" ed="J"/>said, Speak from the place where it cannot be spoken.</p>
<lb n="0367b03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b0301">A monk asked, As long as there are words and phrases, none go beyond the summit. What is the matter outside the summit? The master called the novice Wen-
<lb n="0367b04" ed="J"/>yuan. Wenyuan answered, Yes? The master said, It is already late in the day.</p>
<lb n="0367b05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b0501">A monk asked, What is Vairocana Buddha? The master said, Do not speak foully.</p>
<lb n="0367b06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b0601">A monk asked, The supreme Way is not difficult, it only dislikes choosing and selecting. How can one avoid choosing and selecting? The master said, Above heaven and
<lb n="0367b07" ed="J"/>below heaven, I alone am honored. The monk said, That is still choosing and selecting. The master said, Storehouse slave, where is
<lb n="0367b08" ed="J"/>the choosing and selecting?</p>
<lb n="0367b09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b0901">A monk asked, Who is a person outside the three realms? The master said, What can you do about this old monk being within the three realms?</p>
<lb n="0367b10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b1001">A monk asked, What about one who knows there is and yet is not in being? The master said, If you ask further, you are deliberately questioning this old monk.</p>
<lb n="0367b11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b1101">The master addressed the assembly, Head south and go to the monasteries; do not stay here. A monk then asked, Reverend,
<lb n="0367b12" ed="J"/>what sort of place is here? The master said, My here is a firewood grove.</p>
<lb n="0367b13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b1301">A monk asked, What is Vairocana Buddha? The master said, By nature, one is a disciple.</p>
<lb n="0367b14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b1401">A monk asked, How is it when one returns to the root and gets the meaning? The master said, Too hasty. The monk said, I do not understand. The master said, Not
<lb n="0367b15" ed="J"/>understanding starts from where?</p>
<lb n="0367b16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b1601">Minister Liu entered the monastery and saw the master sweeping the ground. He asked, Great good teacher, why are you sweeping away dust?
<lb n="0367b17" ed="J"/>The master said, It comes from outside.</p>
<lb n="0367b18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b1801">A monk asked, How is it when a sharp sword leaves the scabbard? The master said, Dark. The monk said, As I ask directly, how can it be made clear?
<lb n="0367b19" ed="J"/>The master said, I have no such idle time. The monk said, What if I fold my hands before others? The master said, Sooner or later
<lb n="0367b20" ed="J"/>I will see you folding your hands. The monk said, How about when one is not folding hands? The master said, Who is the one not folding hands?</p>
<lb n="0367b21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b2101">A monk asked, Where is the śramaṇa's place of power? The master said, Where are you not effective?</p>
<lb n="0367b22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b2201">A monk asked, Where does the master instruct students? The master said, Right before me there are no students. The monk said, Then
<lb n="0367b23" ed="J"/>that means you do not appear in the world. The master then said, Take care.</p>
<lb n="0367b24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b2401">A monk asked, Are the Patriarch's meaning and the teachings' meaning the same or different? The master made a fist and placed it on his head. The monk said, Reverend, you still have this
<lb n="0367b25" ed="J"/>thing there? The master took off his hat and said, Tell me, what does this old monk have?</p>
<lb n="0367b26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b2601">A monk asked, How is it when the mind neither stops nor abides? The master said, It is a living thing. Right here, this very one is being
<lb n="0367b27" ed="J"/>driven by mind-consciousness. The monk said, How can one avoid being driven by mind-consciousness? The master lowered his head.</p>
<lb n="0367b28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b2801">A monk asked, From where does the Way arise? The master said, This arises, but the Way does not belong to arising and ceasing. The monk said, Could it be
<lb n="0367b29" ed="J"/>natural or not? The master said, This is natural; the Way is not like that.</p>
<lb n="0367b30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367b3001">A monk asked, Are the Patriarch's meaning and the teachings' meaning the same or different? The master said, If you understand the Patriarch's meaning, then you understand the teachings' meaning.</p>
<pb n="0367c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0367c"/>
<lb n="0367c01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c0101">A monk asked, What is moving among other kinds? The master said, Om lin, om lin.<g ref="#CB03514"/><g ref="#CB03514"/></p>
<lb n="0367c02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c0201">A monk asked, How is it when the height is steep and hard to climb? The master said, This old monk lives on the peak itself. The monk said, What about Cao-
<lb n="0367c03" ed="J"/>xi by the roadside? The master said, Caoxi is bad. The monk said, Why does no one get there nowadays? The master said,
<lb n="0367c04" ed="J"/>It is because it is steep.</p>
<lb n="0367c05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c0501">A monk asked, What is the jeweled moon in the empty sky? The master said, It stops up this old monk's ears.</p>
<lb n="0367c06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c0601">A monk asked, What if there is the slightest deviation? The master said, Crude. The monk said, What about responding to the occasion? The master said, Bent.</p>
<lb n="0367c07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c0701">A monk asked, What is the conduct of a śramaṇa? The master stretched out his hand and brushed his robe.</p>
<lb n="0367c08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c0801">A monk asked, How is it where the life of Patriarchs and Buddhas does not cease? The master said, No one knows.</p>
<lb n="0367c09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c0901">A monk asked, What is expedient function called? The master said, It is called expedient function.</p>
<lb n="0367c10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c1001">A monk asked, This student has recently entered the monastery and does not understand. I beg the master for instruction. The master said, Before entering the monastery, even more
<lb n="0367c11" ed="J"/>you did not understand.</p>
<lb n="0367c12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c1201">A monk asked, What did the ancient worthies of old use to instruct people? The master said, If not for your question, this old monk would not even know
<lb n="0367c13" ed="J"/>there were ancient worthies. The monk said, Please instruct me. The master said, This old monk is not an ancient worthy.</p>
<lb n="0367c14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c1401">A monk asked, Before the Buddha-flower has opened, how does one discern the true and real? The master said, It is true, it is real. The monk said, On whose
<lb n="0367c15" ed="J"/>account is this matter? The master said, This old monk has a share; you, reverend, have a share.</p>
<lb n="0367c16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c1601">A monk asked, What is Buddha? The master said, What sort of person are you?</p>
<lb n="0367c17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c1701">A monk asked, How is it on the straight road? The master said, The straight road.</p>
<lb n="0367c18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c1801">A monk asked, What is the mystery within mystery, unbroken mystery? The master said, Your asking me is unbroken mystery.</p>
<lb n="0367c19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c1901">A monk asked, Before the flower of awakening has opened, how does one discern the real? The master said, It has already opened. The monk said, I still do not know<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0367c1901" n="0367c1901"/><anchor xml:id="beg0367c1901" n="0367c1901"/><anchor xml:id="end0367c1901"/>
<lb n="0367c20" ed="J"/>whether it is true or real. The master said, True is real, real is true.</p>
<lb n="0367c21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c2101">A monk asked, Is there anyone who does not repay the four kinds of grace and the three virtues? The master said, Yes. The monk said, Who is that? The master
<lb n="0367c22" ed="J"/>said, A fellow who betrays grace and fails virtue.</p>
<lb n="0367c23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c2301">A monk asked, When a poor son comes, what thing do you give him? The master said, Nothing is lacking.</p>
<lb n="0367c24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c2401">A monk asked, Who is the true host of Zhaozhou? The master said, This old monk is Congshen.</p>
<lb n="0367c25" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c2501">An old woman asked, I am in a body burdened by the five obstructions; how can I be freed from them? The master said, May all people
<lb n="0367c26" ed="J"/>be reborn in heaven; may you, old woman, sink forever in the bitter sea.</p>
<lb n="0367c27" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c2701">A monk asked, How is it when the bright moon is in the sky? The master said, You are still a fellow below the steps. The monk said, Please receive me up the
<lb n="0367c28" ed="J"/>steps. The master said, When the moon has set, come see me.</p>
<lb n="0367c29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0367c2901">At times the master addressed the assembly, When this old monk first arrived at Yaoshan, I got one phrase, and right up to now
<lb n="0367c30" ed="J"/>I have been stuffed full, snoring with fullness.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="juan"/>
<pb n="0368a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0368a"/>
<lb n="0368a01" ed="J"/><cb:juan n="3" fun="open"><cb:mulu n="3" type="卷"></cb:mulu><cb:jhead>Recorded Sayings of Reverend Zhaozhou, Lower Scroll, together with encounters, examinations, discriminations, verses, and hymns</cb:jhead></cb:juan>
<lb n="0368a02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368a0201">Once while the master was seated in meditation in his room, the steward reported, Great King has come to pay respects. The king
<lb n="0368a03" ed="J"/>bowed, and an attendant asked, When the ruler comes, why did you not rise? The master said, You do not understand.
<lb n="0368a04" ed="J"/>Here with this old monk, when lower-grade people come, I go out to the main gate to receive them; when middle-grade people come, I get down from the meditation platform to receive them;
<lb n="0368a05" ed="J"/>when upper-grade people come, I receive them on the meditation platform. One cannot call the Great King middle-grade or lower-grade,
<lb n="0368a06" ed="J"/>for fear of slighting him. The king was delighted and repeatedly invited him inside for offerings.</p>
<lb n="0368a07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368a0701">The master asked Lay Official Zhou, Have you ever dreamed of Linji? The official raised his fist. The master
<lb n="0368a08" ed="J"/>said, On that side did you see him? The official said, On this side I saw him. The master said, Where did you see Linji? The official had no
<lb n="0368a09" ed="J"/>reply. The master asked, Where does Official Zhou come from? He said, Neither coming nor going. The master said, I am not an old
<lb n="0368a10" ed="J"/>crow, flying here and there.</p>
<lb n="0368a11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368a1101">The master addressed the assembly, As soon as there is right and wrong, the mind is lost in confusion. Is there still any share in answering? Later
<lb n="0368a12" ed="J"/>a monk cited this to Luopu, and Luopu clicked his teeth; he also cited it to Yunju, and Yunju said, Why bother?<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0368a1201" n="0368a1201"/><anchor xml:id="beg0368a1201" n="0368a1201"/><anchor xml:id="end0368a1201"/>
<lb n="0368a13" ed="J"/>The monk cited it to the master. The master said, In the south many people lose body and life. The monk said, Please, master,
<lb n="0368a14" ed="J"/>give an example. As soon as the master raised it, the monk pointed to a monk beside him and said, This monk here, after eating his meal, what
<lb n="0368a15" ed="J"/>talk is he making?</p>
<lb n="0368a16" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368a1601">Once while the master was reading the Diamond Sutra, a monk asked, All Buddhas and the Buddhas' unsurpassed bodhi
<lb n="0368a17" ed="J"/>come forth from this sutra. What is this sutra? The master said, Diamond Prajñā Pāramitā
<lb n="0368a18" ed="J"/>Sutra, Thus have I heard: at one time the Buddha was in Śrāvastī. The monk said, No. The master said, I myself
<lb n="0368a19" ed="J"/>may not read the sutra either?</p>
<lb n="0368a20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368a2001">When a monk was taking leave, the master said, When you go out, if someone suddenly asks, Have you seen Zhaozhou or not?
<lb n="0368a21" ed="J"/>how will you reply? The monk said, I can only say I have. The master said, This old monk is a donkey; how will you
<lb n="0368a22" ed="J"/>say you saw me? The monk had no reply.</p>
<lb n="0368a23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368a2301">The master asked a newly arrived monk, Where do you come from? He said, From the south. The master said, Do you know there is a Zhaozhou
<lb n="0368a24" ed="J"/>barrier? He said, One must know the Zhaozhou barrier. The master shouted, You peddler of smuggled salt! Then he said, Brother,
<lb n="0368a25" ed="J"/>the Zhaozhou barrier is hard to pass. The monk said, What is the Zhaozhou barrier? The master said, The stone bridge is.</p>
<lb n="0368a26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368a2601">A monk came from Xuefeng. The master said, Reverend, do not stay here. This old monk's place is only
<lb n="0368a27" ed="J"/>a place to avoid trouble. The Buddha-Dharma is entirely in the south. The monk said, How can the Buddha-Dharma have north and south? The master said, Even if
<lb n="0368a28" ed="J"/>you come from Yunju or Xuefeng, you are still just a plank-carrying fellow. The monk said, I do not yet know how things are over there.
<lb n="0368a29" ed="J"/>The master said, Why did you wet the bed last night? The monk said, After realization, how is it? The master said,
<lb n="0368a30" ed="J"/>Still shit.</p>
<pb n="0368b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0368b"/>
<lb n="0368b01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368b0101">He addressed the assembly, Here I have lions coming out of the cave, and also lions staying in the cave; it is only hard
<lb n="0368b02" ed="J"/>to get a lion cub. At that time a monk snapped his fingers in reply. The master said, What is that? He said, A lion cub.
<lb n="0368b03" ed="J"/>The master said, For me to call it a lion cub is already a fault, and you go on trampling further.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0368b0301" n="0368b0301"/><anchor xml:id="beg0368b0301" n="0368b0301"/><anchor xml:id="end0368b0301"/></p>
<lb n="0368b04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368b0401">He asked a newly arrived monk, From what place did you depart? He said, From Xuefeng. The master said, What sayings does Xuefeng
<lb n="0368b05" ed="J"/>use to instruct people? He said, The master often says, The whole world in the ten directions is the śramaṇa's one eye. You
<lb n="0368b06" ed="J"/>people, where will you shit? The master said, If you return, send him a shovel.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0368b0601" n="0368b0601"/><anchor xml:id="beg0368b0601" n="0368b0601"/><anchor xml:id="end0368b0601"/></p>
<lb n="0368b07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368b0701">While the master was distributing clothes to the assembly, a monk asked, master, after giving everything away, what will you
<lb n="0368b08" ed="J"/>use? The master called, Fellow from Huzhou. The monk answered, Yes. The master said, Use what!</p>
<lb n="0368b09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368b0901">The master addressed the assembly, Before the world existed, this nature already existed; when the world is destroyed, this nature is not destroyed.
<lb n="0368b10" ed="J"/>A monk asked, What is this nature? The master said, The five skandhas and four great elements. The monk said, Those still perish; what then is
<lb n="0368b11" ed="J"/>this nature? The master said, The four great elements and five skandhas.</p>
<lb n="0368b12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368b1201">A scriptural lecturer from Dingzhou arrived. The master asked, What discipline do you study? He said, Sutras, vinaya, and treatises; I lecture without even listening first.
<lb n="0368b13" ed="J"/>The master raised his hand and showed it to him, Can you lecture on this? The lecturer was bewildered and did not know. The master said, Even if
<lb n="0368b14" ed="J"/>you can lecture without listening, you are still only a fellow who lectures on sutras and treatises. If it is Buddha-Dharma, it is not yet
<lb n="0368b15" ed="J"/>there. He said, Then is not your present speech itself Buddha-Dharma? The master said, Even if you can ask
<lb n="0368b16" ed="J"/>and answer, it all belongs to sutras and treatises; Buddha-Dharma is not there. He had no reply.</p>
<lb n="0368b17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368b1701">The master asked an attendant, Where do you come from? He said, From the north hall. The master said, How is that hall
<lb n="0368b18" ed="J"/>compared with this hall? The attendant had no reply. A monk was standing nearby; the master told him to answer in the attendant's place, and the monk answered for him,
<lb n="0368b19" ed="J"/>saying, I came from that hall. The master laughed at him. The master then told Wenyuan to answer for him, and Wenyuan said, The attendant
<lb n="0368b20" ed="J"/>is still fine; he does not take the master's words.</p>
<lb n="0368b21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368b2101">The master asked a lecturer, What do you study? He said, I lecture on the Vimalakīrti Sutra. The master said, The Vimalakīrti Sutra says, Step by step
<lb n="0368b22" ed="J"/>is the site of awakening. Where is the lecturer? No reply. The master told Quanyi to answer in the lecturer's place. Quan-
<lb n="0368b23" ed="J"/>yi said, From this one question alone, can you recognize the site of awakening? The master said, Your body is in the site of awakening, your mind
<lb n="0368b24" ed="J"/>is where? Speak quickly! He said, master is not seeking the student's mind. The master said, I am. He said,
<lb n="0368b25" ed="J"/>This one question and one answer, what are they? The master said, This old monk is not in the mental factors; the Dharma passes beyond<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0368b2501" n="0368b2501"/><anchor xml:id="beg0368b2501" n="0368b2501"/><anchor xml:id="end0368b2501"/>
<lb n="0368b26" ed="J"/>eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind, and is known and understood. He said, Since it is not among the mind's reckonings, why does master
<lb n="0368b27" ed="J"/>seek it? The master said, Because for your sake I cannot say it. He said, If the Dharma passes beyond eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind and is not
<lb n="0368b28" ed="J"/>understood, how can you say it cannot be said? The master said, Eat my phlegm and spittle.</p>
<lb n="0368b29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368b2901">The master asked a monk, Have you ever read the Lotus Sutra? He said, I have. The master said, In the sutra it says, Wearing rag robes
<lb n="0368b30" ed="J"/>in a secluded place, falsely called araṇya, one deceives and deludes worldly people. How do you understand this? The monk was about to
<pb n="0368c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0368c"/>
<lb n="0368c01" ed="J"/>bow. The master said, Are you wearing rag robes? He said, I am wearing them. The master said, Do not deceive me. He said, How<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0368c0101" n="0368c0101"/><anchor xml:id="beg0368c0101" n="0368c0101"/><anchor xml:id="end0368c0101"/>
<lb n="0368c02" ed="J"/>can I avoid being deluded? The master said, Make your own living; do not take this old monk's words.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0368c0201" n="0368c0201"/><anchor xml:id="beg0368c0201" n="0368c0201"/><anchor xml:id="end0368c0201"/></p>
<lb n="0368c03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368c0301">The master asked a lecturer, What do you study? He said, I lecture on the Vimalakīrti Sutra. The master said, Which one is Vimalakīrti's
<lb n="0368c04" ed="J"/>grandfather? He said, I am. The master said, Then why are you passing on words for children and grandchildren? He had no reply.</p>
<lb n="0368c05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368c0501">One day the master ascended the hall. As soon as a monk came forward to bow, the master put his palms together and said, Take care. On another day a monk
<lb n="0368c06" ed="J"/>bowed. The master said, Ask well. He said, What is Chan? The master said, Today the sky is cloudy; I will not answer
<lb n="0368c07" ed="J"/>questions.</p>
<lb n="0368c08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368c0801">He asked a newly arrived monk, From what direction do you come? He said, I come from no direction. The master then turned his back. The monk took his sitting cloth
<lb n="0368c09" ed="J"/>and turned along with the master. The master said, Fine indeed, no direction.</p>
<lb n="0368c10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368c1001">He asked a newly arrived monk, Where do you come from? He said, From the south. The master said, After meeting from three thousand li away, do not
<lb n="0368c11" ed="J"/>play games. He said, I have not. The master said, Pluck willow blossoms, pluck willow blossoms.</p>
<lb n="0368c12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368c1201">Fenggan arrived below Mount Wutai and saw an old man. Fenggan said, Could you be Mañjuśrī or not? The old
<lb n="0368c13" ed="J"/>man said, There cannot be two Mañjuśrīs. Fenggan then bowed, and the old man disappeared. A monk cited this
<lb n="0368c14" ed="J"/>to the master. The master said, Fenggan had only one eye. The master then ordered Wenyuan to play the old man, and I
<lb n="0368c15" ed="J"/>will play Fenggan. The master said, Could you be Mañjuśrī or not? There could not be two Mañjuśrīs. The master said, Man-
<lb n="0368c16" ed="J"/>juśrī, Mañjuśrī.</p>
<lb n="0368c17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368c1701">The master asked two newly arrived monks, Reverend, have you been here before? One said, I have not been here. The master said, Go drink tea.
<lb n="0368c18" ed="J"/>He then asked the other one, Have you been here before? He said, I have. The master said, Go drink tea. The prior
<lb n="0368c19" ed="J"/>of the monastery asked, master, telling one who has not been here to go drink tea is one thing; but one who has been here, why
<lb n="0368c20" ed="J"/>do you also tell him to go drink tea? The master said, Prior. The prior answered, Yes. The master said, Go drink tea.</p>
<lb n="0368c21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368c2101">The master went to Yunju. Yunju said, You are old indeed; why not find a place to stay? The master said, What
<lb n="0368c22" ed="J"/>place can one stay in? Yunju said, Ahead there is the foundation of an old temple. The master said, Then, master,
<lb n="0368c23" ed="J"/>find a place to stay yourself." The master again went to Zhuyu. Zhuyu said, "So old already, why not find a place to stay
<lb n="0368c24" ed="J"/>and go there?" The master said, "What place can one stay in?" Zhuyu said, "So old already, and you do not even know a place to
<lb n="0368c25" ed="J"/>stay!" The master said, "For thirty years I handled horses and rode them; today I was kicked down by a donkey." The master again went to Zhuyu's
<lb n="0368c26" ed="J"/>abbot's room and looked all around. Zhuyu said, "Why take a fall on level ground?" The master said, "Only because
<lb n="0368c27" ed="J"/>my mind is coarse."</p>
<lb n="0368c28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0368c2801">One day the master took his staff up into Zhuyu's dharma hall, pacing east and west. Zhuyu said, "What are you
<lb n="0368c29" ed="J"/>doing?" The master said, "Testing the water." Zhuyu said, "There is not a single drop here at my place, so what water are you testing?" The master then
<lb n="0368c30" ed="J"/>leaned his staff against the wall and went down.</p><p xml:id="pJ24p0368c3008" cb:place="inline">On the road to Mount Tai there was an old woman who liked to question monks. A monk asked:
<pb n="0369a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0369a"/>
<lb n="0369a01" ed="J"/>"Which way does the road to Mount Tai go?" She said, "Go straight on!" As soon as the monk started off, the old woman said, "There goes another one like that
<lb n="0369a02" ed="J"/>too!" After hearing of this, the master went and asked, "Which way does the road to Mount Tai go?" She said, "Go straight on!"
<lb n="0369a03" ed="J"/>As soon as the master started off, the old woman said, "There goes another one like that too!" The master returned and told the assembly, saying, "Today that old woman
<lb n="0369a04" ed="J"/>was seen through by this old monk."</p>
<lb n="0369a05" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369a0501">Seeing a monk come, the master picked up a burning ember and showed it to him, saying, "Do you understand?" The monk said, "I do not." The master said, "You must not
<lb n="0369a06" ed="J"/>call it fire; this old monk has said enough." The master again picked up the ember and said, "Do you understand?" He said, "I do not." The master then
<lb n="0369a07" ed="J"/>said, "From here in Shu Prefecture there is the monk of Mount Touzi. Go pay respects and ask him. If the conditions accord,
<lb n="0369a08" ed="J"/>you need not come back; if they do not accord, then come back." The monk then went, and upon arriving at Master Touzi's place,
<lb n="0369a09" ed="J"/>Touzi asked, "Where have you just come from?" He said, "I left Zhaozhou and came especially to pay respects to you, Master!"
<lb n="0369a10" ed="J"/>Touzi said, "What words did old Zhaozhou speak?" The monk then fully recounted the previous exchange. Touzi then
<lb n="0369a11" ed="J"/>got down from the meditation seat, walked three or five steps, sat back down, and said, "Do you understand?" The monk said, "I do not!" Touzi said, "Go back and
<lb n="0369a12" ed="J"/>tell Zhaozhou." The monk returned and told the master. The master said, "Do you understand yet?" He said, "Not yet."
<lb n="0369a13" ed="J"/>The master said, "That is not much different either."<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0369a1301" n="0369a1301"/><anchor xml:id="beg0369a1301" n="0369a1301"/><anchor xml:id="end0369a1301"/></p>
<lb n="0369a14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369a1401">Dongshan asked a monk, "Where do you come from?" He said, "From mending shoes." Dongshan said, "By your own understanding, or relying on another?" He said, "Relying on another."
<lb n="0369a15" ed="J"/>Dongshan said, "Did he also point to you, Venerable?" There was no reply. The master spoke on his behalf, saying, "If he approves, then it is not contrary."
<lb n="0369a16" ed="J"/>Puhua was eating raw greens. Linji saw him and said, "Puhua is very much like a donkey." Puhua then
<lb n="0369a17" ed="J"/>brayed like a donkey. Linji let it go and left. Puhua said, "That brat Linji has only one eye."
<lb n="0369a18" ed="J"/>The master spoke on his behalf, saying, "Just give him his proper fodder."</p>
<lb n="0369a19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369a1901">Baoshou asked Hu Dingjiao, "Are you not Hu Dingjiao?" He said, "I would not dare." Bao said, "Can you nail
<lb n="0369a20" ed="J"/>empty space?" He said, "Please first break open empty space!" Baoshou then struck him and said, "Later there will be a talkative master
<lb n="0369a21" ed="J"/>who will explain it to you." Later Hu Dingjiao recounted this to the master. The master said, "Why were you
<lb n="0369a22" ed="J"/>struck by him?" He said, "I do not know where my fault was!" The master said, "You cannot even manage this one seam,<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0369a2201" n="0369a2201"/><anchor xml:id="beg0369a2201" n="0369a2201"/><anchor xml:id="end0369a2201"/>
<lb n="0369a23" ed="J"/>and you still tell him to break it open!" Dingjiao then understood. The master spoke on his behalf, saying, "First nail up this one seam."
<lb n="0369a24" ed="J"/>The master asked a newly arrived monk, "Where have you come from?" He said, "From Xuefeng." The master said, "What sayings does Xuefeng
<lb n="0369a25" ed="J"/>use to instruct people?" He said, "Xuefeng often says, 'The whole world in the ten directions is the monk's
<lb n="0369a26" ed="J"/>single eye. You people, where will you shit?' " The master said, "When you return, send Venerable Xuefeng a<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0369a2601" n="0369a2601"/><anchor xml:id="beg0369a2601" n="0369a2601"/><anchor xml:id="end0369a2601"/>
<lb n="0369a27" ed="J"/>shovel for me."</p>
<lb n="0369a28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369a2801">While traveling on the road, the master met an old woman who asked, "Where does the master live?" The master said, "Zhaozhou
<lb n="0369a29" ed="J"/>East Courtyard west." The master later raised this to a monk, saying, "Tell me, which west character is used there?" One monk said, "The west of east-west."
<lb n="0369a30" ed="J"/>Another monk said, "The west of dwelling and lodging." The master said, "You two could both serve as magistrates of the salt and iron office."</p>
<pb n="0369b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0369b"/>
<lb n="0369b01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369b0101">The master was strolling in the garden with a vice minister. They saw a rabbit run past, and the minister asked, "Master, you are a great spiritual teacher;
<lb n="0369b02" ed="J"/>why did the rabbit run when it saw you?" The master said, "This old monk likes to kill."</p>
<lb n="0369b03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369b0301">The master saw a monk sweeping the ground and asked, "Sweeping like this, can it ever become clean?" He said, "The more I sweep,
<lb n="0369b04" ed="J"/>the more there is." The master said, "Is there not one who brushes away dust?" He said, "Who is the one who brushes away dust?" The master said, "Do you understand?"
<lb n="0369b05" ed="J"/>He said, "I do not." The master said, "Go ask Yunju." The monk then went and asked Yunju, "Who
<lb n="0369b06" ed="J"/>is the one who brushes away dust?" Yunju said, "That blind fellow."</p>
<lb n="0369b07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369b0701">The master asked a monk, "How long have you been here?" He said, "Seven or eight years." The master said, "Have you ever seen this old
<lb n="0369b08" ed="J"/>monk?" He said, "Yes." The master said, "If I were a donkey, how would you see me?" He said, "I would see in the dharma realm."
<lb n="0369b09" ed="J"/>The master said, "I thought you had this move; all those meals you ate were wasted!" The monk said,
<lb n="0369b10" ed="J"/>"Please speak, Master." The master said, "Why did you not say, 'See in the fodder'?"</p>
<lb n="0369b11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369b1101">The master asked the cook, "Today are we eating raw vegetables or cooked vegetables?" The cook lifted a stalk of greens. The master said,
<lb n="0369b12" ed="J"/>"Those who know gratitude are few; those who betray gratitude are many."</p>
<lb n="0369b13" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369b1301">A lay practitioner came to the monastery to burn incense. The master asked a monk, "He is over there burning incense and bowing, while I
<lb n="0369b14" ed="J"/>am here talking with you. At just such a time, where is life?" The monk said, "Master,
<lb n="0369b15" ed="J"/>what is it?" The master said, "In that case it is over there." He said, "In that case, that is already prior." The master<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0369b1501" n="0369b1501"/><anchor xml:id="beg0369b1501" n="0369b1501"/><anchor xml:id="end0369b1501"/>
<lb n="0369b16" ed="J"/>laughed at him.</p>
<lb n="0369b17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369b1701">The master and his junior attendant Wenyuan debated doctrine; neither could claim victory. Whoever claimed victory had to lose a pancake. The master said,
<lb n="0369b18" ed="J"/>"I have a donkey!" Yuan said, "I am the donkey's rump." The master said, "I am donkey dung." Yuan said, "I
<lb n="0369b19" ed="J"/>am a worm in the dung." The master said, "What are you doing in there?" Yuan said, "I am spending the summer there."
<lb n="0369b20" ed="J"/>The master said, "Bring the pancake here."</p>
<lb n="0369b21" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369b2101">As the master was returning from going inside, he saw a banner pole missing one section. A monk asked, "One section of the banner pole
<lb n="0369b22" ed="J"/>is gone; did it go up to heaven or into the earth?" The master said, "It neither went to heaven nor entered the earth." He asked,
<lb n="0369b23" ed="J"/>"Then where did it go?" The master said, "It fell off."</p>
<lb n="0369b24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369b2401">While the master was seated, a monk came out and bowed. The master said, "Take care." As the monk was about to ask a question, the master said, "Again
<lb n="0369b25" ed="J"/>it is so."</p>
<lb n="0369b26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369b2601">While standing under the eaves, the master heard swallows chattering and said, "These swallows mutter on and on, enticing people into
<lb n="0369b27" ed="J"/>talk." A monk asked, "I wonder, is it pleasant or not?" The master said, "Vaguely like a tune, just enough to listen to,
<lb n="0369b28" ed="J"/>and then the wind blows it into another melody."</p>
<lb n="0369b29" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369b2901">A monk took leave to depart. The master said, "Where are you going?" He said, "To Min." The master said, "There are many soldiers in Min;
<lb n="0369b30" ed="J"/>you must avoid them." He said, "Where should I avoid them to?" The master said, "Just right."</p>
<pb n="0369c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0369c"/>
<lb n="0369c01" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369c0101">A monk came for an interview and saw the master sitting with his patched robe covering his head, so he withdrew. The master said, "Venerable,
<lb n="0369c02" ed="J"/>do not say this old monk did not respond."</p>
<lb n="0369c03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369c0301">The master asked a monk, "Where do you come from?" He said, "From the south." The master said, "Who was your companion?"
<lb n="0369c04" ed="J"/>He said, "A water buffalo." The master said, "What a fine monk you are, but why keep company with a beast?" He said, "Because there is no difference."
<lb n="0369c05" ed="J"/>The master said, "A fine beast indeed." He said, "How could I agree?" The master said, "If you do not agree, then give me back my companion
<lb n="0369c06" ed="J"/>first."</p>
<lb n="0369c07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369c0701">The master asked a monk, "Is there a patriarch in the hall or not?" He said, "There is." The master said, "Call him to come wash
<lb n="0369c08" ed="J"/>this old monk's feet."</p>
<lb n="0369c09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369c0901">In the hall there were two monks, each pushing the other away and refusing to be first seat. The steward reported this to the master. The master said,
<lb n="0369c10" ed="J"/>"Make them both second seat." He asked, "Then who should be first seat?" The master said, "Set out the incense." He said,
<lb n="0369c11" ed="J"/>"The incense has already been set out." The master said, "The incense of precepts, the incense of concentration."</p>
<lb n="0369c12" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369c1201">The master asked a monk, "Where have you come from?" He said, "From the capital." The master said, "Did you pass through Tong Pass?"
<lb n="0369c13" ed="J"/>He said, "I did not pass through it." The master said, "Today I have caught a smuggler of illicit salt."</p>
<lb n="0369c14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369c1401">While seeing off a deceased monk, the master said, "It is only one dead man, yet countless people escort him." He also said, "So many
<lb n="0369c15" ed="J"/>dead men escort one living man." At that time a monk asked, "Is it the mind that lives, or the body that lives?" The master said,
<lb n="0369c16" ed="J"/>"Body and mind both do not live." He said, "Then what is this?" The master said, "A dead fellow."</p>
<lb n="0369c17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369c1701">A monk saw a cat and asked, "I call it a cat; what does the master call it,
<lb n="0369c18" ed="J"/>I wonder?" The master said, "It is you who call it a cat."</p>
<lb n="0369c19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369c1901">When the king of Zhenzhou came to visit the master, the attendant came to report, saying, "The king has come." The master said, "May the king
<lb n="0369c20" ed="J"/>have ten thousand blessings." The attendant said, "He is not here yet; he has only reached below the gate." The master said, "And yet you say the king has
<lb n="0369c21" ed="J"/>come."</p>
<lb n="0369c22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369c2201">From atop the east privy he called for Wenyuan, and Wenyuan answered. The master said, "Up on the east privy, I cannot speak
<lb n="0369c23" ed="J"/>Buddhist teaching with you."</p>
<lb n="0369c24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369c2401">While passing through the hall, he called the attendant, and the attendant answered. The master said, "What fine hall-merit."
<lb n="0369c25" ed="J"/>The attendant had no reply.</p>
<lb n="0369c26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369c2601">When the master went to Linji's place, he had just begun washing his feet when Linji asked, "What is the meaning of the Patriarch's coming from the West?"
<lb n="0369c27" ed="J"/>The master said, "I am right in the middle of washing my feet." Linji came closer and leaned over to listen. The master said, "If you understand, then understand.
<lb n="0369c28" ed="J"/>If you do not, do not peck at it any further, what are you doing?" Linji flicked his sleeves and left. The master said, "After thirty years of pilgrimage,
<lb n="0369c29" ed="J"/>today I have put a mistaken note under someone's foot."</p>
<lb n="0369c30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0369c3001">When the master reached Guoqing Monastery on Tiantai and saw Hanshan and Shide, he said, "Long have I heard of Hanshan and Shide;
<pb n="0370a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0370a"/>
<lb n="0370a01" ed="J"/>coming here, I see only two water buffaloes." Hanshan and Shide then acted out buffalo fighting. The master said,
<lb n="0370a02" ed="J"/>"Hey, hey!" Hanshan and Shide gnashed their teeth and glared at each other. The master returned to the hall. The two came into the hall and asked
<lb n="0370a03" ed="J"/>the master, "How about that earlier exchange?" The master just laughed loudly.</p>
<lb n="0370a04" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370a0401">One day the two asked the master, "Where have you been?" The master said, "To bow to the five hundred arhats." The two
<lb n="0370a05" ed="J"/>said, "Five hundred water buffaloes, and where are the arhats?" The master said, "Why did they become five hundred
<lb n="0370a06" ed="J"/>water buffaloes?" Hanshan said, "Blue heaven, blue heaven!" The master laughed loudly.</p>
<lb n="0370a07" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370a0701">While on pilgrimage, the master met two hermitage masters. One was acting as a horn-haired page boy. The master greeted them, but the two
<lb n="0370a08" ed="J"/>paid no attention at all. The next morning, the horn-haired boy brought a pot of rice, set it on the ground, and divided it into three
<lb n="0370a09" ed="J"/>portions. The hermitage master pulled his mat forward and sat. The boy also pulled his mat forward and sat facing him,
<lb n="0370a10" ed="J"/>still not inviting the master. The master then also pulled his mat forward and sat. The boy looked at the master, and the hermitage
<lb n="0370a11" ed="J"/>master said, "Do not say you rose early; there are travelers by night as well." The master said, "Why not have this traveler
<lb n="0370a12" ed="J"/>instructed?" The hermitage master said, "He is someone's son." The master said, "I should have let it pass." The boy then stood up,
<lb n="0370a13" ed="J"/>looked at the hermitage master, and said, "Why so much talk?" From then on the boy entered the mountains and was not seen again.</p>
<lb n="0370a14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370a1401">While the master was reading a sutra, the novice Wenyuan came in. The master glanced at him from the side over the sutra. The novice
<lb n="0370a15" ed="J"/>then went out. The master followed and seized him, saying, "Speak quickly! Speak quickly!" Wenyuan said, "Amitabha!
<lb n="0370a16" ed="J"/>Amitabha!" The master then returned to the abbot's quarters.</p>
<lb n="0370a17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370a1701">When a novice boy came for interview, the master said to the attendant, "Tell him to go." The attendant told the boy,
<lb n="0370a18" ed="J"/>"The master says to go." The master said, "The novice boy gets in through the gate; the attendant stays outside the gate."</p>
<lb n="0370a19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370a1901">While traveling, the master came to the monastery of a senior master. As soon as he entered and they saw each other, he said, "Is there? Is there?"
<lb n="0370a20" ed="J"/>The senior master raised his fist. The master said, "The water is shallow; the boat is hard to moor." He then went out. He went to another monastery,
<lb n="0370a21" ed="J"/>saw the senior master, and said, "Is there? Is there?" The senior master raised his fist. The master said, "Able to let go and able to seize,
<lb n="0370a22" ed="J"/>able to take and able to gather." He bowed and went out.</p>
<lb n="0370a23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370a2301">One day the master held up a string of beads and asked a Silla elder, "Do they also have this over there?" He said,
<lb n="0370a24" ed="J"/>"They do." The master said, "How is it compared with this?" He said, "It is not like this." The master said, "Since they have it, why is it not
<lb n="0370a25" ed="J"/>like this?" There was no reply. The master answered for him, saying, "Have you not heard: Silla and Great Tang."</p>
<lb n="0370a26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370a2601">He asked a newly arrived monk, "Where do you come from?" He said, "From the south!" The master raised a finger and said, "Do you understand?" He said, "I do not."
<lb n="0370a27" ed="J"/>The master said, "Ten thousand blessings in movement and stillness. You do not understand?"</p>
<lb n="0370a28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370a2801">While on pilgrimage, the master asked Daci, "What is prajna's substance?" Daci said, "What is prajna's
<lb n="0370a29" ed="J"/>substance?" The master laughed loudly and left. The next day Daci saw the master sweeping and asked, "What is prajna's
<lb n="0370a30" ed="J"/>substance?" The master put down the broom, laughed loudly, and went away. Daci then returned to his
<pb n="0370b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0370b"/>
<lb n="0370b01" ed="J"/>quarters.</p>
<lb n="0370b02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370b0201">The master came to Baizhang. Baizhang asked, "Where do you come from?" He said, "From Nanquan." Baizhang said, "What
<lb n="0370b03" ed="J"/>sayings does Nanquan use to instruct people?" The master said, "Sometimes he says, 'Even one who has not attained must still stand steeply
<lb n="0370b04" ed="J"/>forth.' " Baizhang shouted at him. The master's expression turned startled. Baizhang said, "Excellent, steep indeed." The master then danced
<lb n="0370b05" ed="J"/>and went out.</p>
<lb n="0370b06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370b0601">The master came to Touzi's place and sat facing him at the meal. Touzi gave him a steamed cake to eat. The master said, "I will not eat."
<lb n="0370b07" ed="J"/>Before long, griddle cakes were served, and Touzi had a novice pass one to the master. The master received the cake and then bowed to the novice
<lb n="0370b08" ed="J"/>three times. Touzi remained silent.</p>
<lb n="0370b09" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370b0901">A monk painted the master's portrait and presented it to him. The master said, "If it looks like this old monk, then beat me to death; if it does not look like me,
<lb n="0370b10" ed="J"/>then burn it."</p>
<lb n="0370b11" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370b1101">As the master was walking with Wenyuan, he pointed with his hand to a patch of ground and said, "This would be a fine place to set up a
<lb n="0370b12" ed="J"/>patrol post." Wenyuan went and stood there, saying, "Bring your official pass!" The master then gave him
<lb n="0370b13" ed="J"/>a slap. Yuan said, "The pass was clearly in order."</p>
<lb n="0370b14" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370b1401">The master asked a newly arrived monk, "Where have you just come from?" He said, "Mount Tai." The master said, "Did you see Manjusri there or not?" The monk
<lb n="0370b15" ed="J"/>spread out his hands. The master said, "Many can spread out their hands, but who has seen Manjusri?" He said, "Just guarding the breath in a murderous hurry." The master
<lb n="0370b16" ed="J"/>He said, If one does not see the geese in the clouds, how would one know the cold of the desert frontier.</p>
<lb n="0370b17" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370b1701">A monk asked, I have come from far away to throw myself on the Master; I ask the Master to receive me. The Master said, Under Sun Bin, why drill a tortoise shell?
<lb n="0370b18" ed="J"/>The monk flicked his sleeves and went out. The Master said, I had taken him for a worthy one, but he has broken both his legs.</p>
<lb n="0370b19" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370b1901">The Master and the head monk were looking at the stone bridge. He then asked the head monk, Who built this? He said, Li Ying built it.
<lb n="0370b20" ed="J"/>The Master said, When he built it, where did he set his hand to begin? There was no reply. The Master said, You ordinarily speak of the stone bridge, but when asked
<lb n="0370b21" ed="J"/>about the place where the work began, you do not even know.</p>
<lb n="0370b22" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370b2201">The head monk of the Silla Monastery invited the Master for a meal. When the Master reached the gate, he asked, What monastery is this? He said, Silla
<lb n="0370b23" ed="J"/>Monastery. The Master said, Between you and me lies an ocean.</p>
<lb n="0370b24" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370b2401">The Master asked a monk, Where do you come from? He said, From Yunju. The Master said, What saying does Yunju have? He said:
<lb n="0370b25" ed="J"/>A monk asked, What is it like when the spirit ram hangs its horns? Yunju said, Six sixes are thirty-six. The Master said, Yun
<lb n="0370b26" ed="J"/>ju, elder brother teacher, is still around. The monk then asked, I do not yet know Your Reverence's meaning. The Master said, Nine nines
<lb n="0370b27" ed="J"/>are eighty-one.</p>
<lb n="0370b28" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370b2801">One evening an old woman came into the monastery. The Master said, What are you doing? The old woman said, Seeking lodging. The Master said:
<lb n="0370b29" ed="J"/>What kind of place is this here? The old woman laughed heartily and left.</p>
<lb n="0370b30" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370b3001">The Master went out and met an old woman carrying a basket. The Master then asked, Where are you
<pb n="0370c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0370c"/>
<lb n="0370c01" ed="J"/>going? She said, Going to steal Zhaozhou's bamboo shoots. The Master said, If you suddenly met Zhaozhou, then what? The old woman stepped close
<lb n="0370c02" ed="J"/>and slapped him once.</p>
<lb n="0370c03" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370c0301">The Master saw the monastery head bringing uncooked rice; when the crows saw him, they all flew off. The Master said, When the crows saw
<lb n="0370c04" ed="J"/>you, why did they fly away? The head monk said, They fear me. The Master said, What kind of talk is that?
<lb n="0370c05" ed="J"/>The Master answered in his place: Because I have a mind to kill.</p>
<lb n="0370c06" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370c0601">The Master asked a monk, Where do you come from? He said, From Jiangxi. The Master said, Where is Zhaozhou located?
<lb n="0370c07" ed="J"/>The monk had no reply.</p>
<lb n="0370c08" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370c0801">The Master was passing by the hall and saw a monk bowing. The Master struck him once with a staff and said, Bowing is also a good
<lb n="0370c09" ed="J"/>thing. The Master said, A good thing is not as good as no thing.</p>
<lb n="0370c10" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370c1001">When the Master visited Tong Pass, the guard at Tong Pass asked him, Do you know there is a Tong Pass or not? The Master said, I know
<lb n="0370c11" ed="J"/>there is a Tong Pass. He said, Those with official papers may pass; those without official papers may not pass. The Master said:
<lb n="0370c12" ed="J"/>If the imperial carriage were suddenly to arrive, what then? The guard said, It too must be inspected before passing. He said, You want to rebel.
<lb n="0370c13" ed="J"/>The Master came to Baoshou. When Baoshou saw him coming, he turned his back and sat facing away. The Master then spread out his sitting cloth.
<lb n="0370c14" ed="J"/>Baoshou stood up, and the Master immediately went out.</p>
<lb n="0370c15" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370c1501">When the Master was with Nanquan, Nanquan led a water buffalo into the monks' hall and made a circuit around the hall.
<lb n="0370c16" ed="J"/>The head monk then slapped the buffalo's back three times, and Nanquan stopped and left. Later the Master placed a bundle of grass
<lb n="0370c17" ed="J"/>before the head monk, and the head monk had no reply.</p>
<lb n="0370c18" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370c1801">A scholar saw the Master and praised him, saying, Reverend, you are an ancient Buddha. The Master said, Scholar, you are
<lb n="0370c19" ed="J"/>a new Tathagata.</p>
<lb n="0370c20" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370c2001">A monk asked, What is nirvana? The Master said, My hearing is poor. The monk asked again. The Master said, I am not
<lb n="0370c21" ed="J"/>bothered by deaf ears. Then he had a verse: Broad and easy is the Great Way, nirvana's gate is right before your face; just sit, thinking without
<lb n="0370c22" ed="J"/>limit, and next year spring will be spring again.</p>
<lb n="0370c23" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370c2301">A monk asked, Are the two roads of life and death the same or different? The Master then had a verse: A wayfarer asks of life and death,
<lb n="0370c24" ed="J"/>how can life and death be discussed? In Shuanglin, one pond of water; a bright moon shines over heaven and earth. To call that understanding upon the words,
<lb n="0370c25" ed="J"/>this is to toy with spirit and soul. If you wish to grasp life and death, it is like a madman speaking dream-spring.</p>
<lb n="0370c26" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0370c2601">A monk asked, When the Buddhas face trouble, they hide their bodies in flames; when the Reverend faces trouble, where
<lb n="0370c27" ed="J"/>do you hide your body? The Master then had a verse: He says the Buddha has trouble; I say he has disaster. Just watch how I avoid
<lb n="0370c28" ed="J"/>trouble, where is there any following along? Being and nonbeing are not the point, going and coming are not going and coming. For your sake I speak of the difficult
<lb n="0370c29" ed="J"/>Dharma, but face to face, have you recognized it yet?</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0370c30" ed="J"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Verses</cb:mulu><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Song of the Twelve Hours</cb:mulu><head>Song of the Twelve Hours</head>
<pb n="0371a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0371a"/>
<lb n="0371a01" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371a0101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">At cockcrow, the Chou hour, sorrow comes when I get up and still look shabby. No skirt, no short jacket at all, only the form of a kasaya
<lb n="0371a02" ed="J"/>barely remains. The loincloth has no waist, the trousers no opening, and on my head are three or five pecks of bluish ash. Looking north, I meant to practice
<lb n="0371a03" ed="J"/>and benefit people, but who knew I would end up in such a wretched state.</l></lg>
<lb n="0371a04" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371a0401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">At dawn, the Yin hour, this ruined monastery in a desolate village is hard to speak of. For the morning gruel there is not a grain of rice, only facing empty
<lb n="0371a05" ed="J"/>windows and dust in the cracks. Only sparrows chatter, no one draws near; sitting alone, I often hear falling leaves. Who says that leaving home
<lb n="0371a06" ed="J"/>cuts off love and hate? Thinking on it, without noticing, tears soak my cloth.</l></lg>
<lb n="0371a07" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371a0701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">At sunrise, the Mao hour, purity itself turns into vexation. Conditioned merit is covered by dusty curtains, and endless fields
<lb n="0371a08" ed="J"/>have never been swept. Much furrowing of brows, little to the heart's liking; unbearable are that black and yellow old ones from the east village. Offerings and support
<lb n="0371a09" ed="J"/>they never bring, yet they let their donkeys eat the grass before my hall.</l></lg>
<lb n="0371a10" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371a1001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">At mealtime, the Chen hour, I vainly look to the neighboring houses for cooking smoke. I parted from steamed buns years ago; today I can only<g ref="#CB05283"/>
<lb n="0371a11" ed="J"/>think and swallow saliva. Little recitation, frequent sighing; among a hundred households there is not one good person. Those who come only
<lb n="0371a12" ed="J"/>say they want tea to drink, and if they get no tea they gulp and go off angry.</l></lg>
<lb n="0371a13" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371a1301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">By midmorning, the Si hour, who knew shaving the head would come to this? For no reason I was invited to be a village monk, humiliated and hungry,
<lb n="0371a14" ed="J"/>wretched, almost to death. Hu Zhangsan and Black Li Si never produce the least bit of respect. They just now suddenly
<lb n="0371a15" ed="J"/>come to the gate only to ask to borrow tea and borrow paper.</l></lg>
<lb n="0371a16" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371a1601" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">At noon, the Wu hour, tea and meals come around with no fixed measure. I leave the south house and go to the north house, and once I get to the north
<lb n="0371a17" ed="J"/>house they make excuses. Bitter sandy salt, barley vinegar, sorghum rice with pickled lettuce. They only call this an offering
<lb n="0371a18" ed="J"/>not to be taken lightly, and say a monk's resolve on the Way must be firm.</l></lg>
<lb n="0371a19" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371a1901" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">In the afternoon, the Wei hour, this time I do not trample the ground of passing time. I once heard one full meal makes one forget a hundred hungers; today this old
<lb n="0371a20" ed="J"/>monk's body itself proves it. I practice no meditation, discuss no doctrine, spread out a torn mat and sleep in the sun. I reckon that even in
<lb n="0371a21" ed="J"/>Tusita Heaven above, there is nothing like this sun baking my back.</l></lg>
<lb n="0371a22" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371a2201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">In the late afternoon, the Shen hour, there are also people who burn incense and bow. Five old women, three with goiters, and one pair of faces
<lb n="0371a23" ed="J"/>black and rough. Sesame tea is truly a treasure. Vajra, no need to strain so hard. I only wish that next year,
<lb n="0371a24" ed="J"/>when silkworms and wheat are ripe, little Rahula will give me a coin.</l></lg>
<lb n="0371a25" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371a2501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">At sunset, the You hour, apart from desolation what is there to keep? Of lofty wandering monks, surely none are entrusted here; temple-roaming novices<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0371a2501" n="0371a2501"/><anchor xml:id="beg0371a2501" n="0371a2501"/><anchor xml:id="end0371a2501"/>
<lb n="0371a26" ed="J"/>are always around. Extraordinary words never reach the mouth, and in vain I continue as a descendant of Shakyamuni. One staff,
<lb n="0371a27" ed="J"/>rough and thorny, serves not only for climbing mountains but also for beating dogs.</l></lg>
<lb n="0371a28" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371a2801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">At dusk, the Xu hour, I sit alone in an empty dark room. I never encounter lamp-light bright as sunlight; before my eyes there is only
<lb n="0371a29" ed="J"/>Jinzhou lacquer-blackness. I hear no bell, the days pass in vain; only the mice I hear chattering and squeaking. By what means could I still
<lb n="0371a30" ed="J"/>have the mood to think of reciting a paramita?</l></lg>
<pb n="0371b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0371b"/>
<lb n="0371b01" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371b0101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">In the night watch, the Hai hour, who loves the bright moon before the gate? Here I worry only that when I lie down, there is no clothing
<lb n="0371b02" ed="J"/>to use for a cover. Liu the steward, Zhao of the five precepts, what strange goodness they speak with their mouths. Let you mountain monks
<lb n="0371b03" ed="J"/>have your bags utterly empty; if asked about it, all because you simply do not understand.</l></lg>
<lb n="0371b04" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371b0401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">At midnight, the Zi hour, when have mind and circumstances ever paused even briefly? I think of all the home-leavers under heaven; among abbots like me,
<lb n="0371b05" ed="J"/>how many can there be? An earthen couch-bed, broken reed mat, an old elm-wood pillow, and no blanket at all. Before the honored image I do not burn<g ref="#CB15831"/>
<lb n="0371b06" ed="J"/>benzoin incense; in the ashes there is only the smell of cow dung.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0371b07" ed="J"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Seeing a pagoda being built, he had a verse</cb:mulu><head>Seeing a pagoda being built, he had a verse</head>
<lb n="0371b08" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371b0801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Originally complete and perfect, what need is there to pile up stones? Names, distant and carved, are far removed from me. If someone asks,
<lb n="0371b09" ed="J"/>I will never point it out or depict it.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0371b10" ed="J"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Seeing that the understandings of various places went by different roads, he made a reproving verse</cb:mulu><head>Seeing that the understandings of various places went by different roads, he made a reproving verse</head>
<lb n="0371b11" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371b1101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">South of Zhaozhou, north of the stone bridge, in Guanyin Monastery there is Maitreya. The Patriarch left behind a single sandal,
<lb n="0371b12" ed="J"/>and to this very day it cannot be found.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0371b13" ed="J"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Because of the fish drum, he had a verse</cb:mulu><head>Because of the fish drum, he had a verse</head>
<lb n="0371b14" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371b1401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The four great elements are indeed nature's work; if it has sound, what is most precious is the emptiness inside. Do not wonder that I do not speak with ordinary people
<lb n="0371b15" ed="J"/>about it, only because the pitch and mode are not the same.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0371b16" ed="J"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Because of a lotus, he had a verse</cb:mulu><head>Because of a lotus, he had a verse</head>
<lb n="0371b17" ed="J"/><lg xml:id="lgJ24p0371b1701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">A wondrous root and shoot, fresh with snow; no one knows in what age it left the Western Heaven. The depth or shallowness of the muddy mire people do not
<lb n="0371b18" ed="J"/>know; only when it rises from the water do they know it is a white lotus.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0371b19" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0371b20" ed="J"/><cb:juan n="2" fun="close"><cb:jhead>Recorded Sayings of Reverend Zhaozhou, Lower Scroll<note place="inline">End.</note></cb:jhead></cb:juan></cb:div>
<lb n="0371b21" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0371b22" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0371b23" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0371b24" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0371b25" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0371b26" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0371b27" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0371b28" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0371b29" ed="J"/>
<lb n="0371b30" ed="J"/>
<pb n="0371c" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0371c"/>
<lb n="0371c01" ed="J"/><cb:div type="xu"><cb:mulu level="1" type="序">Biographical Record of Chan Master Zhenji of Zhaozhou</cb:mulu><head>Biographical Record of Chan Master Zhenji of Zhaozhou</head>
<lb n="0371c02" ed="J"/><p xml:id="pJ24p0371c0201">The Master was a disciple in Nanquan's lineage. His secular surname was Hao, originally from Hao Village in Caozhou; his personal name was Cong
<lb n="0371c03" ed="J"/>shen. A pagoda inscription in Zhenfu says: Did the Master reach seven hundred jiazi cycles? When King Wu was in decline, he withdrew to avoid
<lb n="0371c04" ed="J"/>the times in remote mountains, eating roots and wearing grass, yet the deportment of a monk did not change. At first the Master traveled with his original teacher and came to Nan
<lb n="0371c05" ed="J"/>quan. His original teacher first completed the formal greetings; only then did the Master make his greeting. Nanquan was lying in the abbot's room,
<lb n="0371c06" ed="J"/>and when he saw the Master come to visit, he asked, From where have you lately come? The Master said, Ruixiang Monastery. Nanquan said, Did you
<lb n="0371c07" ed="J"/>see the auspicious image? The Master said, The auspicious image I did not see, but I did see a reclining Tathagata. Nanquan then got up
<lb n="0371c08" ed="J"/>and asked, Are you a novice with a master, or a novice without a master? The Master replied, A novice with a master. Nanquan said:
<lb n="0371c09" ed="J"/>Which one is your master? The Master said, Though it is early spring and still cold, I respectfully wish Your Reverence's honored body peace and ten thousand
<lb n="0371c10" ed="J"/>blessings. Nanquan then called the steward and said, Arrange another place for this novice. After the Master received full ordination, he heard that his ordination
<lb n="0371c11" ed="J"/>teacher was west of Caozhou, residing at Huguo Monastery, so he returned there to pay respects. After he arrived, his original teacher ordered
<lb n="0371c12" ed="J"/>the Hao family, saying: Your son has returned from wandering among teachers. His relatives were overjoyed beyond measure and only<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0371c1201" n="0371c1201"/><anchor xml:id="beg0371c1201" n="0371c1201"/><anchor xml:id="end0371c1201"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0371c1202" n="0371c1202"/><anchor xml:id="beg0371c1202" n="0371c1202"/><anchor xml:id="end0371c1202"/>
<lb n="0371c13" ed="J"/>waited for the next day, all planning to come see him. When the Master heard this, he said: The dusty net of worldly affection has no end.
<lb n="0371c14" ed="J"/>I have already left home; I do not wish to meet them again. That very night he packed up and went on ahead. Afterward he himself carried<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0371c1401" n="0371c1401"/><anchor xml:id="beg0371c1401" n="0371c1401"/><anchor xml:id="end0371c1401"/>
<lb n="0371c15" ed="J"/>his bottle and staff and traveled everywhere. He often said of himself: If a seven-year-old child surpasses me, I will ask
<lb n="0371c16" ed="J"/>him; if a hundred-year-old old man is not equal to me, I will teach him. Not until he was eighty did he settle at Zhao
<lb n="0371c17" ed="J"/>zhou, at Guanyin Monastery east of the city, ten li from the stone bridge. Thereafter his abbacy was austere and spare, his resolve was to emulate the ancients.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0371c1701" n="0371c1701"/><anchor xml:id="beg0371c1701" n="0371c1701"/><anchor xml:id="end0371c1701"/>
<lb n="0371c18" ed="J"/>In the monks' hall there were no front or rear platforms; meals were arranged only as needed. One leg of his rope bed was broken, so he used a burnt piece of firewood
<lb n="0371c19" ed="J"/>and tied it on with rope. Whenever someone made a new one for him, the Master would not permit it. For more than forty years as abbot,
<lb n="0371c20" ed="J"/>he never once sent a single letter to solicit his patrons. Then a monk from the south came and quoted a question to Xuefeng:
<lb n="0371c21" ed="J"/>What is it like when an ancient ravine has a cold spring? Xuefeng said, Stare with wide eyes and you cannot see the bottom. The student said, For one who drinks it, how
<lb n="0371c22" ed="J"/>is it? Xuefeng said, It does not enter through the mouth. When the Master heard this, he said: If not through the mouth, then it enters through the nostrils.
<lb n="0371c23" ed="J"/>That monk then asked the Master, What is it like when an ancient ravine has a cold spring? The Master said, Bitter. The student said, For one who drinks it, how
<lb n="0371c24" ed="J"/>is it? The Master said, Dead. When Xuefeng heard the Master's words, he praised him, saying: Ancient Buddha, ancient Buddha. Because of this, Xuefeng
<lb n="0371c25" ed="J"/>afterward no longer answered such questions. Later, when the King of Yan in Hebei led troops to take Zhenfu, once they reached the border
<lb n="0371c26" ed="J"/>a reader of omens reported: In Zhaozhou there dwells a sage; if you fight, you will surely not win. Yan
<lb n="0371c27" ed="J"/>and Zhao, the two kings, thereupon spread a banquet and both ceased hostilities. Then they asked: In Zhao's golden land, what superior man
<lb n="0371c28" ed="J"/>is there? Someone said: There is a great master who lectures on the Avatamsaka Sutra, lofty and solitary in conduct. In years of great drought, all command him
<lb n="0371c29" ed="J"/>to go to Mount Tai to pray. Before the master returns, sweet rain pours down. They said: I fear this is not yet the very best. Someone
<lb n="0371c30" ed="J"/>said: One hundred twenty li from here is Zhaozhou Guanyin Monastery. There is a Chan master there, advanced in years and seniority,
<pb n="0372a" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0372a"/>
<lb n="0372a01" ed="J"/>with clear Dharma eye. All said: This one may fit the omen. The two kings halted their carriages and went to see him. Once they arrived
<lb n="0372a02" ed="J"/>in the monastery, the Master sat upright and did not rise. The King of Yan then asked: Which is more honored, the king of men or the Dharma King?
<lb n="0372a03" ed="J"/>The Master said: If among kings of men, the king of men is honored; if among Dharma kings, the Dharma King is honored. Yan
<lb n="0372a04" ed="J"/>King assented. After a while the Master asked: Which one is the great king of Zhenfu? The King of Zhao
<lb n="0372a05" ed="J"/>responded: Your disciple. The Master said: This old monk idly remains in the mountains and rivers and has not been able<note place="inline">Because Zhaozhou was affiliated with the prefectural government, this was done to express due respect.</note>
<lb n="0372a06" ed="J"/>to come face you. After a moment, attendants asked the Master to teach Dharma for the great king. The Master said: The great king has many attendants,
<lb n="0372a07" ed="J"/>how can they let this old monk speak Dharma? So they ordered the attendants to withdraw. At the Master's side there was a novice, Wen
<lb n="0372a08" ed="J"/>yuan, who said loudly: Inform the great king, these are not the attendants in question. The great king then asked: What
<lb n="0372a09" ed="J"/>attendants are those? He replied: The great king has many taboo names, so the Reverend does not dare speak Dharma. The King of Yan then
<lb n="0372a10" ed="J"/>said: I ask the Chan master to set aside the taboos and teach Dharma. The Master said: From this I know that the great king's relatives in former kalpas were all
<lb n="0372a11" ed="J"/>enemies. Our Buddha, the World-Honored One, when his name is spoken once, sins are extinguished and blessings arise. But your royal ancestors, as soon as someone
<lb n="0372a12" ed="J"/>touches upon their names, anger arises. The Master's compassion did not tire; he taught Dharma for a long time. The two kings
<lb n="0372a13" ed="J"/>bowed their heads and praised him, honoring him without end. The next day, when they were about to return, the King of Yan sent a vanguard envoy, who heard that the Master
<lb n="0372a14" ed="J"/>did not rise, and at dawn entered the monastery to accuse the Master of arrogance toward the lords. When the Master heard this, he came out to greet him. The vanguard
<lb n="0372a15" ed="J"/>then asked: Yesterday, when the two kings came, you did not rise; today, when you see me come, why
<lb n="0372a16" ed="J"/>did you rise to greet me? The Master said: When the commander becomes equal to a great king, this old monk also will not rise to greet him. The vanguard, hearing
<lb n="0372a17" ed="J"/>the Master's words, bowed again and again and left. Soon after, the King of Zhao sent messengers to invite the Master for offerings. When he arrived
<lb n="0372a18" ed="J"/>at the city gate, the whole city in formal array received him and escorted him inside. As soon as the Master descended from the jeweled carriage, the king bowed and invited
<lb n="0372a19" ed="J"/>the Master up to the hall, where he sat in the proper seat. After a while, the Master struck his forehead with his hand and said: Those standing below the steps, what
<lb n="0372a20" ed="J"/>officials are they? The attendants said: They are honored elders of the various monasteries, along with great masters and senior worthies. The Master said: Each of them
<lb n="0372a21" ed="J"/>is a teaching host in his own place. If they remain below the steps, this old monk will also rise. The king then ordered them up into the hall. That day
<lb n="0372a22" ed="J"/>as the feast was about to end, the monastic officials lined up, and from top to bottom each person was to ask one question. One person asked about Buddha
<lb n="0372a23" ed="J"/>Dharma. As soon as the Master saw him, he asked: What are you doing? He said: Asking about Buddha Dharma. The Master said: Here you have already seated<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0372a2301" n="0372a2301"/><anchor xml:id="beg0372a2301" n="0372a2301"/><anchor xml:id="end0372a2301"/>
<lb n="0372a24" ed="J"/>this old monk aside; where then are you asking what Dharma? Two honored ones do not teach side by side. The king then ordered<note place="inline">This is a word used in the wording.</note>
<lb n="0372a25" ed="J"/>it stopped. At that time the queen and the king were both standing in attendance at his sides. The queen said: I ask the Chan master to, for
<lb n="0372a26" ed="J"/>The great king receives the prediction with a touch on the crown. The Master rubbed the great king's crown with his hand and said, May Your Majesty and this old monk
<lb n="0372a27" ed="J"/>have the same span of years. At that time, when arrangements were made to receive the Master, he was temporarily lodged in a nearby monastery, and in due time a site was chosen to build a Chan monastery.
<lb n="0372a28" ed="J"/>When the Master heard of it, he had someone tell the king, If a single blade of grass is disturbed, this old monk will return to Zhaozhou.
<lb n="0372a29" ed="J"/>At that time, Commander Dou vowed to donate an orchard, worth fifteen thousand strings of cash, to be named Zhenji
<lb n="0372a30" ed="J"/>Chan Monastery, also called the Dou Family Garden. After the Master entered the monastery, the assembly gathered like clouds from the sea. At that time the Prince of Zhao
<pb n="0372b" ed="J" xml:id="J24.B137.0372b"/>
<lb n="0372b01" ed="J"/>offered reverential support, and the Prince of Yan sent from Youzhou ceremonial robes bestowed by decree. The prefectural authorities prepared full honors to receive him. The Master
<lb n="0372b02" ed="J"/>firmly declined and would not accept them. Attendants carried the chest before the Master and said, For the sake of the Chan Master's Buddha Dharma, the great king
<lb n="0372b03" ed="J"/>earnestly asks the Master to wear these robes. The Master said, It is precisely for the sake of the Buddha Dharma that this old monk does not wear these
<lb n="0372b04" ed="J"/>robes. The attendants said, At least do it for the great king's sake. The Master said, What concern is it of worldly officials! Then he personally
<lb n="0372b05" ed="J"/>took the robe and draped it on himself. They bowed and offered congratulations again and again, and the Master merely acknowledged them. The Master stayed in Zhaozhou<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0372b0501" n="0372b0501"/><anchor xml:id="beg0372b0501" n="0372b0501"/><anchor xml:id="end0372b0501"/>
<lb n="0372b06" ed="J"/>for two years. When he was about to leave the world, he told his disciples, After I pass away, cremate me, and do not
<lb n="0372b07" ed="J"/>wash and sort the relics. The disciples of a lineage master are not like the superficial customs of the world. Besides, the body is an illusion, so what relics could there be
<lb n="0372b08" ed="J"/>to produce? This must not be done. He ordered a young attendant monk to send one whisk to the Prince of Zhao, with the message: This<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0372b0801" n="0372b0801"/><anchor xml:id="beg0372b0801" n="0372b0801"/><anchor xml:id="end0372b0801"/>
<lb n="0372b09" ed="J"/>is what this old monk could not use up in a lifetime. On the tenth day of the eleventh month in the year of wuzi, the Master sat upright
<lb n="0372b10" ed="J"/>and died. At that time, at the Dou Family Garden, there were tens of thousands of monks and laypeople with carts and horses, and their cries of grief shook
<lb n="0372b11" ed="J"/>the plains and fields. The Prince of Zhao carried out all the funeral rites, weeping with sorrow and lamentation, no different from when the golden coffin was concealed
<lb n="0372b12" ed="J"/>in splendor at Kusinagara. All raised a lofty wild-goose stupa and specially erected a grand stele, bestowing the posthumous title Zhenji<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0372b1201" n="0372b1201"/><anchor xml:id="beg0372b1201" n="0372b1201"/><anchor xml:id="end0372b1201"/>
<lb n="0372b13" ed="J"/>Chan Master, and Guangzu Stupa. On the thirteenth day of the first summer month in the eleventh year of Baoda of the Later Tang,
<lb n="0372b14" ed="J"/>a student consulted Chan Master Huitong of the Eastern Monastery in the Eastern Capital about the causes and course of the former man's teaching activity in Zhaozhou.
<lb n="0372b15" ed="J"/>He bowed and withdrew, then took up the brush and recorded it. It is fully factual.</p></cb:div>
</body>
<back>
<cb:div type="apparatus">
<head>Collated notes.</head>
<p>
<app from="#beg0357a1601" to="#end0357a1601"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">Asked, and</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">and asked</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0357b0801" to="#end0357b0801"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">rotten</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">decayed</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0358c1301" to="#end0358c1301"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0359a1301" to="#end0359a1301"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">forked</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">to govern</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0359a2001" to="#end0359a2001"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">self</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0359c2201" to="#end0359c2201"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">only<note type="cf1">T51n2077_p0653a24</note></lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">both</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0359c2301" to="#end0359c2301"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">self</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0359c2901" to="#end0359c2901"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">between</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">asked</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0360a0101" to="#end0360a0101"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0360a2201" to="#end0360a2201"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">self</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0361a0501" to="#end0361a0501"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">one</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">　</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0361a1601" to="#end0361a1601"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">mutual</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">tusk</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0361a1602" to="#end0361a1602"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">mutual</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">tusk</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0361a1701" to="#end0361a1701"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">self</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0361b0501" to="#end0361b0501"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">yet</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">Xi</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0361b1501" to="#end0361b1501"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">self</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0361b2401" to="#end0361b2401"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">monk</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig"><unclear></unclear></rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0362b1401" to="#end0362b1401"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">self</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0363a1601" to="#end0363a1601"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">yet</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">Xi</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0363c0601" to="#end0363c0601"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">seize</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">urgent</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0364a1701" to="#end0364a1701"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0364b1401" to="#end0364b1401"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">eye<note type="cf1">C077n1710_p0709b24</note></lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">ear</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0365a2201" to="#end0365a2201"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">self</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0365a2401" to="#end0365a2401"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">white</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">　</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0365b0701" to="#end0365b0701"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">forked</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">to govern</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0365b0702" to="#end0365b0702"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">gather in</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">gather in</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0365c0101" to="#end0365c0101"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">great<note type="cf1">X68n1315_p0085a08</note></lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">not</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0366b0901" to="#end0366b0901"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0366b1201" to="#end0366b1201"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0366c0801" to="#end0366c0801"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">arrive<note type="cf1">X68n1315_p0086a11</note></lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">then</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0366c1301" to="#end0366c1301"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0367c1901" to="#end0367c1901"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0368a1201" to="#end0368a1201"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">like</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">companion</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0368b0301" to="#end0368b0301"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">early<note type="cf1">C077n1710_p0713b10</note></lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">is</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0368b0601" to="#end0368b0601"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">diarrhea</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">ah</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0368b2501" to="#end0368b2501"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">replied,<note type="cf1">X68n1315_p0088a01</note></lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">understand</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0368c0101" to="#end0368c0101"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">confusion</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">or</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0368c0201" to="#end0368c0201"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">confusion</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">or</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0369a1301" to="#end0369a1301"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">compare<note type="cf1">C077n1710_p0714b08</note></lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">teaching</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0369a2201" to="#end0369a2201"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">still<note type="cf1">T47n1996_p0680c23</note></lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">above</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0369a2601" to="#end0369a2601"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">diarrhea</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">ah</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0369b1501" to="#end0369b1501"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0371a2501" to="#end0371a2501"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">yet</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">Xi</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0371c1201" to="#end0371c1201"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0371c1202" to="#end0371c1202"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0371c1401" to="#end0371c1401"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0371c1701" to="#end0371c1701"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0372a2301" to="#end0372a2301"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">the sixth earthly branch</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0372b0501" to="#end0372b0501"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">already</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">yi (variant form)</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0372b0801" to="#end0372b0801"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">to order; to command<note type="cf1">X68n1315_p0077a04</note></lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">now; today</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0372b1201" to="#end0372b1201"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">posthumous title</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">posthumous title (variant form)</rdg></app>
</p>
</cb:div>
<cb:div type="add-notes">
<head>newly added textual notes</head>
<p>
<note n="0357a1601" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0357a1601">"asked, then" (CB); "and asked" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0357b0801" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0357b0801">"decayed" (CB); "to plaster/daub" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0358c1301" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0358c1301">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0359a1301" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0359a1301">"fork; cross" (CB); "again/also; to govern" (Jiaxing, variant)</note>
<note n="0359a2001" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0359a2001">"self" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0359c2201" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0359c2201">"only; but" (CB); "all; together" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0359c2301" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0359c2301">"self" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0359c2901" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0359c2901">"interval; between" (CB); "to ask" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0360a0101" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0360a0101">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0360a2201" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0360a2201">"self" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0361a0501" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0361a0501">"one" (CB); omitted (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0361a1601" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0361a1601">"mutual" (CB); "tooth" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0361a1602" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0361a1602">"mutual" (CB); "tooth" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0361a1701" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0361a1701">"self" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0361b0501" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0361b0501">"yet; but; to retreat" (CB); "xi" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0361b1501" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0361b1501">"self" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0361b2401" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0361b2401">"monk" (CB); absent in Jiaxing (blank)<unclear></unclear></note>
<note n="0362b1401" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0362b1401">"self" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0363a1601" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0363a1601">"yet; but; to retreat" (CB); "xi" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0363c0601" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0363c0601">"to seize" (CB); "to urge; hurried" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0364a1701" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0364a1701">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0364b1401" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0364b1401">"eye" (CB); "ear" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0365a2201" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0365a2201">"self" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0365a2401" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0365a2401">"white" (CB); omitted (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0365b0701" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0365b0701">"fork; cross" (CB); "again/also; to govern" (Jiaxing, variant)</note>
<note n="0365b0702" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0365b0702">"to gather; to restrain" (CB); "to gather; to restrain" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0365c0101" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0365c0101">"great" (CB); "not" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0366b0901" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0366b0901">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0366b1201" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0366b1201">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0366c0801" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0366c0801">"to arrive" (CB); "then; thus" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0366c1301" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0366c1301">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0367c1901" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0367c1901">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0368a1201" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0368a1201">"similar; like" (CB); "companion" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0368b0301" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0368b0301">"early" (CB); "is; to be" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0368b0601" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0368b0601">"to defecate" (CB); "a" (Jiaxing, phonetic/particle)</note>
<note n="0368b2501" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0368b2501">"to answer" (CB); "to understand; meeting" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0368c0101" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0368c0101">"confused; doubt" (CB); "or; perhaps" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0368c0201" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0368c0201">"confused; doubt" (CB); "or; perhaps" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0369a1301" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0369a1301">"to compare; rather" (CB); "to teach" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0369a2201" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0369a2201">"still; yet" (CB); "above; up" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0369a2601" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0369a2601">"to defecate" (CB); "a" (Jiaxing, phonetic/particle)</note>
<note n="0369b1501" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0369b1501">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0371a2501" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0371a2501">"yet; but; to retreat" (CB); "xi" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0371c1201" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0371c1201">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0371c1202" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0371c1202">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0371c1401" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0371c1401">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0371c1701" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0371c1701">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0372a2301" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0372a2301">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0372b0501" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0372b0501">"already" (CB); "si" (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
<note n="0372b0801" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0372b0801">"to order; to command" (CB); "now; today" (Jiaxing)</note>
<note n="0372b1201" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0372b1201">posthumous title (CB); posthumous title (Jiaxing, variant form)</note>
</p>
</cb:div>
</back></text></TEI>