<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cbeta-org/xml-p5/master/schema/cbeta-p5.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cb="http://www.cbeta.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="J27nB196">
<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
			<title level="s">Jiaxing Canon (Shinwenfeng Edition)</title>
			<title level="s" xml:lang="zh-Hant">嘉興大藏經（新文豐版）</title>
			<title level="m" xml:lang="zh-Hant">鴛湖用禪師語錄</title>
			<title>Jiaxing Canon (Shinwenfeng Edition), Electronic version, No. B196 鴛湖用禪師語錄</title>
			<title xml:lang="zh-Hant">嘉興大藏經（新文豐版）數位版, No. B196 鴛湖用禪師語錄</title>
			<author>清 妙用說　悟進．悟元等編</author>
			<respStmt>
				<resp>Electronic Version by</resp>
				<name>CBETA</name>
			</respStmt>
		</titleStmt>
		<editionStmt>
			<edition>XML TEI P5</edition>
			<respStmt xml:id="resp1"><resp>corrections</resp><name>CBETA</name></respStmt>
			<respStmt xml:id="resp2"><resp>corrections</resp><name>CBETA.maha</name></respStmt>
		</editionStmt>
		<extent>2卷</extent>
		<publicationStmt>
			<idno type="CBETA">
				<idno type="canon">J</idno>.<idno type="vol">27</idno>.<idno type="no">B196</idno>
			</idno>
			<distributor>
				<name>財團法人佛教電子佛典基金會 (CBETA)</name>
				<address>
					<addrLine><email>service@cbeta.org</email></addrLine>
				</address>
			</distributor>
			<availability>
				<p>Available for non-commercial use when distributed with this header intact.</p>
			</availability>
			<date>2025-01-30 02:11:07 +0800</date>
		</publicationStmt>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>嘉興大藏經（新文豐版）</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	</fileDesc>
	<encodingDesc>
		<projectDesc>
			<p xml:lang="en" cb:type="ly">Input by CBETA(first version), Input by CBETA(second version), Part of text as provided by LINDEN, Punctuated text as provided by Mr. Chen Bo-Xun</p>
			<p xml:lang="zh-Hant" cb:type="ly">CBETA 人工輸入（版本一），CBETA 人工輸入（版本二），LINDEN 大德提供部份經文，陳伯勳大德提供新式標點</p>
		</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl>
			<punctuation resp="#resp1"><p>新式標點</p></punctuation>
		</editorialDecl>
		<tagsDecl>
			<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
				<tagUsage gi="rdg">
					<listWit>
						<witness xml:id="wit.cbeta">【CB】</witness>
						<witness xml:id="wit.orig">【嘉興】</witness>
					</listWit>
				</tagUsage>
			</namespace>
		</tagsDecl>
		<charDecl>
			<char xml:id="CB00576">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB00576</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[寧*頁]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping type="unicode">U+29573</mapping>
				<mapping cb:dec="983616" type="PUA">U+F0240</mapping>
			</char>
			<char xml:id="CB01323">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB01323</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[車*度]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping type="unicode">U+2834F</mapping>
				<mapping cb:dec="984363" type="PUA">U+F052B</mapping>
			</char>
			<char xml:id="CB05286">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB05286</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[飢-几+殳]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping type="unicode">U+4B26</mapping>
				<mapping cb:dec="988326" type="PUA">U+F14A6</mapping>
			</char>
			<char xml:id="CB05958">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB05958</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[木*屈]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping type="unicode">U+3B7E</mapping>
				<mapping cb:dec="988998" type="PUA">U+F1746</mapping>
			</char>
			<char xml:id="CB15341">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB15341</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[土*(天/韭)]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping type="unicode">U+21481</mapping>
				<mapping cb:dec="998381" type="PUA">U+F3BED</mapping>
			</char>
			<char xml:id="CB16270">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB16270</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[虫*晏]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping cb:dec="999310" type="PUA">U+F3F8E</mapping>
			</char>
		</charDecl>
	</encodingDesc>
	<profileDesc>
		<langUsage>
			<language ident="en">English</language>
			<language ident="zh-Hant">Chinese (Traditional)</language>
		</langUsage>
	</profileDesc>
	<revisionDesc>
		<change when="2013-05-20">
			<name>CW</name><name>Ray Chou 周邦信</name>P4 to P5 conversion by p4top5a.py, intended for publication
		</change>
		<change when="2008-08-29T12:13:20">
			Zhou Bang-Xin (ed.) Created initial TEI XML version with BASICX.BAT
		</change>
	</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><body>
<milestone n="1" unit="juan" />
<pb n="0375a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0375a" />
<lb n="0375a01" ed="J" />
<note type="community" resp="theksepyro">translated blocks 1-27, 29-35, 37-40, 42-1453</note>
<cb:div type="xu"><cb:mulu level="1" type="序">Preface</cb:mulu><head>Preface</head>
<lb n="0375a02" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0375a0201"><figure><graphic url="../figures/J/J27p0375_01.gif"></graphic></figure></p>
<lb n="0375a03" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375a04" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375a05" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375a06" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375a07" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375a08" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375a09" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375a10" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375a11" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375a12" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375a13" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375a14" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375a15" ed="J" />
<pb n="0375b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0375b" />
<lb n="0375b01" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0375b0101"><figure><graphic url="../figures/J/J27p0375_02.gif"></graphic></figure></p>
<lb n="0375b02" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b03" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b04" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b05" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b06" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b07" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b08" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b09" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b10" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b11" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b12" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b13" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b14" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375b15" ed="J" />
<pb n="0375c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0375c" />
<lb n="0375c01" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0375c0101"><figure><graphic url="../figures/J/J27p0375_03.gif"></graphic></figure></p></cb:div>
<lb n="0375c02" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375c03" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375c04" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375c05" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375c06" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375c07" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375c08" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375c09" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375c10" ed="J" />
<lb n="0375c11" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="xu"><cb:mulu level="1" type="序">Preface to the Recorded Sayings of Chan Master Yuanhu</cb:mulu><head>Preface to the Recorded Sayings of Chan Master Yuanhu</head>
<lb n="0375c12" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0375c1201">I have heard that the ultimate Way is without words and wondrous awakening is not transmitted; then what have the successive patriarchs transmitted in Chan?
<lb n="0375c13" ed="J" />If it is said to be without words, then what are the sayings and the seventeen hundred cases of the Three Vehicles speaking about? Yet in transmission
<lb n="0375c14" ed="J" />there is indeed that which cannot be transmitted, and in words there is also that which words do not fully express. I have often observed that our
<lb n="0375c15" ed="J" />great master Yuanhu possessed the legacy of Longshan Huangniu, and with Chan Master Shiyu was a fellow practitioner
<lb n="0375c16" ed="J" />like brothers. Master Shi received the Dharma from Yunmen, while our master was the direct heir of Nanming; they frequently exchanged letters and verses,
<lb n="0375c17" ed="J" />calling each other intimate friends. In the spring of the gengchen year, our prefecture invited the master to reside at Puming, and Master Shi came from Xuefeng
<lb n="0375c18" ed="J" />and together with the assembly earnestly requested our master to open the hall and commence the retreat, but the master, in humility, firmly declined on account of illness.
<lb n="0375c19" ed="J" />I therefore entreated him, saying, “You are the Dharma eye of a thousand sages, containing the unsurpassed subtle meaning; why begrudge your broad and long
<lb n="0375c20" ed="J" />tongue, and not offer guidance to people of the three capacities?” The master said, “There are indeed things one may cease and things one may not
<pb n="0376a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0376a" />
<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0375c2001" n="0375c2001" /><anchor xml:id="beg0375c2001" n="0375c2001" /><anchor xml:id="end0375c2001" />
<lb n="0376a01" ed="J" />cease. Fortunately my friend Tianhua is here; why should this old monk add superfluous words?” His courteous refusals were exceedingly modest;<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0376a0101" n="0376a0101" /><anchor xml:id="beg0376a0101" n="0376a0101" /><anchor xml:id="end0376a0101" />
<lb n="0376a02" ed="J" />after declining in this way three times, he had no choice but to ascend the hall. The fourfold assembly gathered like clouds, all at once listening to his Dharma teaching,<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0376a0201" n="0376a0201" /><anchor xml:id="beg0376a0201" n="0376a0201" /><anchor xml:id="end0376a0201" />
<lb n="0376a03" ed="J" />like the resounding of great bells and chimes, shattering the world’s dull dream, suddenly causing people to awaken and rise up with clarity,
<lb n="0376a04" ed="J" />and none failed to be convinced of our master’s transcendence of sense faculties and objects, his wondrous transformations without limit. Thus, our master’s every
<lb n="0376a05" ed="J" />strike and shout was nothing but a golden needle to awaken the world; his brief words and short verses were like the sound of a poison drum, heard far and near,
<lb n="0376a06" ed="J" />all who heard were struck. Those not yet struck, if they carefully read this record, each word is a true explanation, each saying a subtle truth, as if
<lb n="0376a07" ed="J" />receiving teaching face to face. Indeed, disciples recorded these notes into volumes; this too shows our master’s swift and skillful functioning of wisdom,
<lb n="0376a08" ed="J" />widely awakening the world. Though it is said the ultimate Way is without words and wondrous awakening is not transmitted, if one spiritually understands this record, then
<lb n="0376a09" ed="J" />words ultimately return to wordlessness, and that which is not transmitted is entirely received. Ah, how ultimate this is!</p>
<lb n="0376a10" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0376a1001" style="margin-left:6em">Respectfully composed by the disciple Zhu Qiaoxiu of Zhicheng</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0376a11" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Table of Contents of the Recorded Sayings of Chan Master Yong of Yuanhu at Puming</cb:mulu><head>Table of Contents of the Recorded Sayings of Chan Master Yong of Yuanhu at Puming</head>
<lb n="0376a12" ed="J" />
<list rend="no-marker"><item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a1201">Preface</item>
<lb n="0376a13" ed="J" />
<item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a1301">Volume One
<lb n="0376a14" ed="J" />
<list rend="no-marker"><item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a1401">Ascend the Dharma seat</item>
<lb n="0376a15" ed="J" />
<item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a1501">Informal instruction</item>
<lb n="0376a16" ed="J" />
<item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a1601">Encounters and conditions</item>
<lb n="0376a17" ed="J" />
<item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a1701">Commentary and verse on old cases</item>
<lb n="0376a18" ed="J" />
<item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a1801">Image praise</item>
<lb n="0376a19" ed="J" />
<item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a1901">Dharma words</item></list></item>
<lb n="0376a20" ed="J" />
<item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a2001">Volume Two
<lb n="0376a21" ed="J" />
<list rend="no-marker"><item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a2101">Correspondence</item>
<lb n="0376a22" ed="J" />
<item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a2201">Verses</item>
<lb n="0376a23" ed="J" />
<item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a2301">Miscellaneous writings</item></list></item>
<lb n="0376a24" ed="J" />
<item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a2401">Appendix
<lb n="0376a25" ed="J" />
<list rend="no-marker"><item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a2501">Biographical account</item>
<lb n="0376a26" ed="J" />
<item xml:id="itemJ27p0376a2601">Stupa inscription</item></list></item></list></cb:div>
<lb n="0376a27" ed="J" />
<lb n="0376a28" ed="J" />
<lb n="0376a29" ed="J" />
<lb n="0376a30" ed="J" />
<pb n="0376b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0376b" />
<lb n="0376b01" ed="J" />
<cb:juan n="1" fun="open"><cb:mulu n="1" type="卷"></cb:mulu><cb:jhead>Recorded Sayings of Chan Master Yong of Yuanhu, Residing at Puming Chan Monastery in Jianning Prefecture, Fujian, Volume One</cb:jhead></cb:juan>
<lb n="0376b02" ed="J" />
<byline cb:type="editor">Compiled by Dharma heirs, disciples Wujin, Wuyuan, and others</byline>
<lb n="0376b03" ed="J" />
<byline cb:type="other">Reprinted by Dharma descendant Zhenzhi of Tui’an at Changshui</byline>
<lb n="0376b04" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Ascending the Seat</cb:mulu><p xml:id="pJ27p0376b0401">Ascending the seat, the master said: "If we speak of the Buddhadharma, this old monk has no place to open his mouth. Today I happened to see the new mountain
<lb n="0376b05" ed="J" />gate, taking my staff and roaming about in play. Passing through Guozi Ridge, all the way to Huoshao Bridge;
<lb n="0376b06" ed="J" />losing its footing, it fell into a deep stream. Fortunately the old Buddha hall came to the rescue; not only
<lb n="0376b07" ed="J" />did it rescue it, it even rode back on its neck. The new mountain gate cries injustice, and inevitably asks this old monk to judge.
<lb n="0376b08" ed="J" />The new mountain gate deserves thirty blows of the staff, and the old Buddha hall also deserves thirty blows of the staff. Why is that?
<lb n="0376b09" ed="J" />Because a cart is not pushed sideways, and principle is not bent in judgment." He threw down his staff and stepped down from the seat.</p>
<lb n="0376b10" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0376b1001">The Venerable Shiyu, together with Prefect Zhu of Zizhu, invited the master to ascend the seat. The official asked, "When the lotus emerges from the case and the true command is in force,
<lb n="0376b11" ed="J" />what is a fresh phrase?" The master immediately struck him. The official said, "I knew early on that the master had
<lb n="0376b12" ed="J" />such a pivotal device." The master said, "Where did you see it?" The official shouted; the master struck again. As the official hesitated, the master said:
<lb n="0376b13" ed="J" />"Go on, go on!" Then raising the whisk, he said, "Assembly, do you understand? Mind itself is Buddha is still
<lb n="0376b14" ed="J" />confused error; neither mind nor Buddha leaves nothing to pursue. Not mind, not Buddha, not a thing, piercing
<lb n="0376b15" ed="J" />flowers, the butterflies are seen deep within. It cannot be grasped, cannot be abandoned; within the unattainable, it is thus attained; like
<lb n="0376b16" ed="J" />dragonflies lightly touching the water as they gently fly. When Puming expounds in this way, he strikes the itchy spot of Lingfeng. Recall and know
<lb n="0376b17" ed="J" />casting off home and scattering the household, striding broadly in the great expanse, lofty and towering, solitary and दूर, bare and pure, naked and free,
<lb n="0376b18" ed="J" />treading down the crowns of all sages, seizing the vital road of ordinary beings. Even so, at times he holds fast, at times<g ref="#CB00576" />
<lb n="0376b19" ed="J" />he lets go; at times letting go within holding fast, at times holding fast within letting go. Do you also know that in the sandalwood
<lb n="0376b20" ed="J" />forest all is pure sandalwood, and in the lion's den there are nothing but lions? Among you, is there not some keen
<lb n="0376b21" ed="J" />fellow who comes forth and says, "Puming needlessly exposes the hidden depths of Lingfeng"? This mountain monk would only tell him:
<lb n="0376b22" ed="J" />"It is just because we once slept in the same bed that I know well the holes beneath the quilt." He struck the staff and stepped down from the seat.</p>
<lb n="0376b23" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0376b2301">In the winter of the xinsi year, the Venerable Wanru, together with various gentry patrons, sent a monk carrying the robe and whisk of the old man of Yuanhu
<lb n="0376b24" ed="J" />and invited the master to ascend the seat. The master pointed and said, "All you worthy ones! These stagnant goods have come from Jingwei
<lb n="0376b25" ed="J" />Wuqiu Laoren, passed to the ancestor Wuhuan of Chexi, and Wuhuan passed them to Nanming
<lb n="0376b26" ed="J" />our root master, who passed them to this sick monk. This sick monk has long regarded them with a cold eye and cast them aside
<lb n="0376b27" ed="J" />upon a heap of dust; today I take them up again to renew their radiance." Then lifting the Dharma robe, he said, "When raised,<g ref="#CB15341" />
<lb n="0376b28" ed="J" />this ancient robe does not hang by a single thread." Lifting the whisk, he said, "When wielding this old whisk, jackals
<lb n="0376b29" ed="J" />are greatly frightened." Lifting the hand scroll, he said, "Only this thing is of no use, yet it provokes people of the time to add
<lb n="0376b30" ed="J" />extra talk. Last year there was a white-handed thief who, without ever seeing it, stole it away first. Now for the time being
<pb n="0376c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0376c" />
<lb n="0376c01" ed="J" />I store it in a quiet place; if in the future there are again rebellious descendants, they will surely drill shells and strike tiles. All you
<lb n="0376c02" ed="J" />worthy ones, do not stare at it; if you stare, you will go blind."</p>
<lb n="0376c03" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0376c0301">In the spring of the renwu year, the Venerable Wanru Wei entered the mountain to offer a feast and invited the master to ascend the seat. A monk came forward, bowed, and the master
<lb n="0376c04" ed="J" />raised the whisk and said, "Do you understand?" The monk said, "Then it directly accords with the occasion." He raised it again, saying, "The fourfold assembly all know
<lb n="0376c05" ed="J" />kindness." The master immediately struck him. A monk asked, "Setting aside sitting atop a solitary peak, what of the matter of host and guest in mutual interchange?"
<lb n="0376c06" ed="J" />The master struck and said, "Understand this blow." The monk shouted; the master struck again, then said, "I often recall the days we dwelt together;
<lb n="0376c07" ed="J" />counting on my fingers, it has been five or six springs since we parted. What obstruction is there between Min land and Wu mountains? Each time it is raised,
<lb n="0376c08" ed="J" />each time it is new." Then he raised the whisk and said, "In the past the World-Honored One held up a flower and Kashyapa smiled; the World-Honored One
<lb n="0376c09" ed="J" />said, 'I have the treasury of the true Dharma eye, the wondrous mind of nirvana, which I entrust to Mahākāśyapa.' From that time on there has been
<lb n="0376c10" ed="J" />a special transmission outside the teachings, directly pointing to the human mind, seeing one’s nature and becoming Buddha. This old fellow today
<lb n="0376c11" ed="J" />at Puming lets great light shine from the tip of the whisk; say, who can attest to it? Fortunately there is
<lb n="0376c12" ed="J" />the Venerable Ruru, invited from Xinghua, who can bear witness. Assembly! If you see it, then you may
<lb n="0376c13" ed="J" />come forth and withdraw together, walk together and sit together. If you do not know, then you will laugh at Puming’s display as mere proclamation.
<lb n="0376c14" ed="J" />But tell me, where is the place of proclamation?" He threw down the whisk and stepped down from the seat.</p>
<lb n="0376c15" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0376c1501">At the Zhongyuan festival, the xiucai Sumeng and Lianyue, together with the assembly, invited the master to ascend the seat. A monk asked, "What
<lb n="0376c16" ed="J" />is the mind of the ancient Buddha?" The master immediately struck. The monk continued, "What is the mind of a student?" The master said, "If you wish to seize
<lb n="0376c17" ed="J" />a roaming dragon, you must go beyond the lizard." The monk pressed on, "Ultimately, how is it?" The master struck again, then said, "The Dharma body<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0376c1701" n="0376c1701" /><anchor xml:id="beg0376c1701" n="0376c1701" /><anchor xml:id="end0376c1701" /><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0376c1702" n="0376c1702" /><anchor xml:id="beg0376c1702" n="0376c1702" /><anchor xml:id="end0376c1702" />
<lb n="0376c18" ed="J" />flows through the five paths, thus there are distinctions of humans, heavens, and the three lower realms. There is rising and sinking, emerging and
<lb n="0376c19" ed="J" />submerging, high and low, suffering and joy. All of you, if you wish to aid those in the three lower realms, to leave suffering
<lb n="0376c20" ed="J" />and attain happiness, you must have in a single thought a mind that is pure, in a single thought a mind that is luminous, in a single thought a mind that is unhindered. A pure mind
<lb n="0376c21" ed="J" />is the true Buddha, a luminous mind is the true Dharma, an unhindered mind is the true Way. The true Buddha is without form,
<lb n="0376c22" ed="J" />the true Dharma is without characteristics, the true Way is without substance. The three are one and the one is three, yet this is still merely naming.
<lb n="0376c23" ed="J" />You must exhaust your own side and see through it; turning your body in the cold ashes, then you can fully<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0376c2301" n="0376c2301" /><anchor xml:id="beg0376c2301" n="0376c2301" /><anchor xml:id="end0376c2301" />
<lb n="0376c24" ed="J" />take it up with your whole being. At this point, bare and shining, the Buddhas of the three times do not go beyond this,
<lb n="0376c25" ed="J" />nor do the bodhisattvas of the ten directions go beyond this. The twenty-eight patriarchs of the West and the two or three of the East also do not go beyond
<lb n="0376c26" ed="J" />this, nor do the old masters of the world go beyond this. Therefore it is said, "Everywhere is entirely the treasury of light,
<lb n="0376c27" ed="J" />and every place is nothing but the field of liberation." Although it is so, tell me, what is it to uphold it further?
<lb n="0376c28" ed="J" />He then gave a shout, struck the staff, and stepped down from the seat.</p>
<lb n="0376c29" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0376c2901">Huang Chunyuan of Sumeng, recommending Ci, invited the master to ascend the seat. The master said, "The spring wind passes dimly, fine rain and birds
<lb n="0376c30" ed="J" />cry out in sorrow. Appearing and disappearing without trace, why does the bronze man weep?" Taking up the staff, he said, "Assembly, do you see?
<pb n="0377a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0377a" />
<lb n="0377a01" ed="J" />If what you see is taken as existent, and everything is regarded as existing, you bind yourself and submit to judgment, bearing cangue and chains. Or if
<lb n="0377a02" ed="J" />at this point you cast off worldly dust and see through conventions, and take everything as empty, you again fall into a one-sided
<lb n="0377a03" ed="J" />nest of emptiness. Therefore an ancient worthy said, "Abandoning existence and clinging to emptiness is likewise a sickness, like avoiding drowning
<lb n="0377a04" ed="J" />only to leap into fire." If there is a great person who gathers his spirit, exhausts his mind, and presses on to the cliff’s edge,
<lb n="0377a05" ed="J" />letting go, personally accepting it, reviving after utter extinction, unable to deceive even oneself, then at that time the eight characters open wide,
<lb n="0377a06" ed="J" />not only knowing the resting place of Lady Xu, but also together with the Buddhas of the three times and the patriarchs
<lb n="0377a07" ed="J" />realizing and entering the samadhi of playful activity. Even so, when you come under Puming, thirty blows cannot be reduced by even one.
<lb n="0377a08" ed="J" />Not a single blow can be spared." He struck the staff and stepped down from the seat.</p>
<lb n="0377a09" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377a0901">On the master’s birthday he ascended the seat. A monk asked, "Where heaven and earth have no place to rest, and sun and moon never cease their motion, without involving past or present,
<lb n="0377a10" ed="J" />in a single phrase, please the master, instruct us." The master said, "Today is the seventh day of the tenth month." The monk continued, "Lanterns transmit
<lb n="0377a11" ed="J" />the message, the dew pillar sighs, how marvelous!" The master said, "This is not your realm." Another monk stepped forward, and the master immediately struck, saying,
<lb n="0377a12" ed="J" />"By imperial command the flying dragon horse is summoned, and the lame turtle sticks out its head." The monk shouted; the master struck again. Then he said, "Shakyamuni
<lb n="0377a13" ed="J" />the old fellow was born on the eighth day of the fourth month; this sick monk of Puming is born today at the hour of you. Tell me,
<lb n="0377a14" ed="J" />is it the same or is it different? If you say it is the same, then there are myriad distinctions; if you say it is different, then in fact it is one family.
<lb n="0377a15" ed="J" />Worthy ones, clergy and laity, please examine this; if not, then listen to a verse: Gautama long ago already<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0377a1501" n="0377a1501" /><anchor xml:id="beg0377a1501" n="0377a1501" /><anchor xml:id="end0377a1501" />
<lb n="0377a16" ed="J" />came into the world, yet Puming has never come into the world; water at the streambed flows busily, while clouds on the ridge disperse
<lb n="0377a17" ed="J" />at ease and self-content." He then stepped down from the seat.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0377a18" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Informal Instruction</cb:mulu><p xml:id="pJ27p0377a1801">Informal instruction: "From the southeast the north wind blows cold and biting; behind the mountain, the water buffalo stands dull and chilled. This lazy illness has always
<lb n="0377a19" ed="J" />made me reluctant to act, suited only to holding a warm cup of tea. The warm tea cup warms the whole body, yet the breath is cold like ashes.
<lb n="0377a20" ed="J" />All you Chan worthies, since the whole body is warmed, why is it cold like ashes? If you can see this,
<lb n="0377a21" ed="J" />then you may calmly drink tea, eat your meals, and pass the time according to your nature. If not—" He took up the staff and struck it once,
<lb n="0377a22" ed="J" />saying, "The staff speaks on behalf of you all." He struck it again. A monk asked, "Setting aside the reopening of the ancient hall,
<lb n="0377a23" ed="J" />I do not ask about that; what is Puming’s single phrase?" The master immediately shouted. The monk continued, "Then it is like the rising of the dragon
<lb n="0377a24" ed="J" />dancing after the wind, breaking through the blue waves and flowing on." The master said, "Idle words."</p>
<lb n="0377a25" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377a2501">Informal instruction on New Year’s Eve: "The weather is cold at the ninth, the year’s end must be observed; raising cups and taking fruit, all extend their hands,
<lb n="0377a26" ed="J" />drinking tea and water, all moisten their mouths; each is complete as is, all should know this. Assembly, tell me,
<lb n="0377a27" ed="J" />know what? Provisionally it is called Buddha, expediently named wisdom. To understand this wisdom, you must
<lb n="0377a28" ed="J" />go beneath the three beams, before the seven-foot seat, wearing out your trousers and skirts, forgetting food and sleep. Yet this
<lb n="0377a29" ed="J" />wisdom is only within activity and use, not apart from before your very eyes. Therefore Zhaozhou, whenever he saw a monk come for instruction,
<lb n="0377a30" ed="J" />would ask, 'Have you been here before?' The monk would say, 'I have.' Zhaozhou would say, 'Go drink tea.' Or if he said, 'I have not
<pb n="0377b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0377b" />
<lb n="0377b01" ed="J" />been here,' he would also say, 'Go drink tea.' The head monk asked, 'Master, why whether one has been here or not,
<lb n="0377b02" ed="J" />do you tell them all to go drink tea?' Zhaozhou called the attendant, who responded. Zhaozhou said, 'Go drink tea.' That old fellow Zhaozhou
<lb n="0377b03" ed="J" />spoke lightly and swiftly, while the attendant did not discern right and wrong. Here at Puming, we do not concern ourselves with whether one drinks tea
<lb n="0377b04" ed="J" />or eats rice; we only want him to go straight in with a single blade. Tell me, is this the same as the ancients or different? If there is a keen
<lb n="0377b05" ed="J" />patch-robed monk, come forth and speak." The assembly had no reply. The master gave a shout and said, "When the sun and moon come to an end,
<lb n="0377b06" ed="J" />the year is already finished; the fishing boat returns to the quiet reed bank, gathering up line and hook in haste, waiting for spring<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0377b0601" n="0377b0601" /><anchor xml:id="beg0377b0601" n="0377b0601" /><anchor xml:id="end0377b0601" />
<lb n="0377b07" ed="J" />winds before going out again." He took up the staff and rose.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0377b08" ed="J" />
<lb n="0377b09" ed="J" />
<lb n="0377b10" ed="J" />
<lb n="0377b11" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Encounters and Conditions</cb:mulu><head>Encounters and Conditions</head>
<lb n="0377b12" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377b1201">The master cited a verse by Yongming and asked Yunfeng Jun, "A transformed person asks an illusionist; the valley echoes answer the sound of the spring.
<lb n="0377b13" ed="J" />To reach the meaning of our school, a clay ox walks upon the water. What is its intent?" Jun said, "Dreaming eyes see empty
<lb n="0377b14" ed="J" />flowers." The master said, "What about the matter of empty flowers?" Jun said, "Do not listen with the ears." The master again asked, "The ancestor Linji
<lb n="0377b15" ed="J" />has a phrase; how would you speak it?" Jun immediately shouted; the master struck. Jun shouted again,
<lb n="0377b16" ed="J" />and the master struck again. Jun bowed. The master said, "So you are a blind donkey after all." Jun flicked his sleeves and left.</p>
<lb n="0377b17" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377b1701">When Jie’an came for instruction and stepped through the gate, the master said, "What is it?" As An was about to reply, the master gave a thunderous shout,
<lb n="0377b18" ed="J" />and An suddenly attained realization, then covered his ears and left.</p>
<lb n="0377b19" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377b1901">One day the master called to a novice who had just entered the abbot’s quarters and said, "My mind is not at peace; have you attained peace
<lb n="0377b20" ed="J" />or not?" The novice said, "Heaven! Heaven!" The master also said, "Heaven! Heaven!" The novice slapped his knee once
<lb n="0377b21" ed="J" />and then left.</p>
<lb n="0377b22" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377b2201">As soon as Yichu rose from bowing, the master raised his fist and said, "Speak a phrase." Yichu immediately slapped. The master also slapped and said:
<lb n="0377b23" ed="J" />"Tell me, your slap and my slap, what is the meaning?" Yichu said, "Please take care, master."
<lb n="0377b24" ed="J" />The master then stopped; Yichu gave a shout and returned to the attendants’ quarters.</p>
<lb n="0377b25" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377b2501">A monk came for instruction. The master asked, "Where do you come from?" He said, "From Zhejiang." The master said, "What did you see on the way?" The monk hesitated,
<lb n="0377b26" ed="J" />and the master shouted; the monk also shouted. The master struck and said, "Where does that shout land?" The monk bowed
<lb n="0377b27" ed="J" />and said, "Thank you, master, for the instruction." The master struck again.</p>
<lb n="0377b28" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377b2801">Huang Lianxian of Anzhai, upon being appointed to Guangdong, entered the mountain to take leave and asked, "A parting phrase, I beg
<lb n="0377b29" ed="J" />the master to instruct me." The master said, "Three thousand miles away, when meeting people, do not raise it wrongly."</p>
<lb n="0377b30" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377b3001">One day when the master was unwell, Jie’an was attending him. The master called for tea and asked, "Your name is Juexian; what do you call 'before'?"
<pb n="0377c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0377c" />
<lb n="0377c01" ed="J" />Jie’an said, "Fortunately, today I have attained ease." The master said, "What is after awakening?" Jie’an
<lb n="0377c02" ed="J" />said, "Please take care, master." The master said, "Can you distinguish before and after?" Jie’an was silent for a long while; the master then
<lb n="0377c03" ed="J" />shouted. Jie’an said, "I simply go on drinking tea." The master said, "What is the matter of drinking tea?" Jie’an said:
<lb n="0377c04" ed="J" />"Persimmons, dates, and dried tofu are all here." The master said, "Then what about you?" Jie’an said, "I have
<lb n="0377c05" ed="J" />eaten them all in one mouthful." The master said, "What is the taste like?" Jie’an said, "The sweet is naturally sweet, the salty naturally salty."
<lb n="0377c06" ed="J" />The master said, "Not yet, say more." Jie’an said, "I thank you for the tea," then bowed. The master was greatly pleased.</p>
<lb n="0377c07" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377c0701">A monk came for instruction. The master said, "Where have you been staying?" He said, "Last autumn at Ruru Hermitage, and over the new year at Jinsu."
<lb n="0377c08" ed="J" />The master said, "What is the matter with staying east and west?" The monk said, "Yes, yes!" The master said, "No, no!"</p>
<lb n="0377c09" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377c0901">Two monks came for instruction. The master asked, "What have you come here for?" One monk said, "We have come especially to pay respects to the master."
<lb n="0377c10" ed="J" />The master said, "But you happen to meet when this old monk is not here." The monk had no reply. The master said, "Take thirty blows and go out."
<lb n="0377c11" ed="J" />He then said, "What about the second one?" The monk said, "Please the master give instruction." Just then the master happened to cough,
<lb n="0377c12" ed="J" />and said, "You happen to meet this old monk coughing." The monk also had no reply. The master said, "Sit and drink tea."</p>
<lb n="0377c13" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377c1301">One evening, after leaving the hall, the master said, "The summer retreat has passed; if any of you have gained strength, you may as well reveal it.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0377c1301" n="0377c1301" /><anchor xml:id="beg0377c1301" n="0377c1301" /><anchor xml:id="end0377c1301" />
<lb n="0377c14" ed="J" />Show it." A monk said, "Just now I bowed to the master." The master said, "Not yet, say more." The monk said, "The days are long
<lb n="0377c15" ed="J" />and people grow weary." The master said, "That is not your realm." The monk said, "And what about you, master?" The master said, "The days are long
<lb n="0377c16" ed="J" />and people grow weary." The monk then bowed.</p>
<lb n="0377c17" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377c1701">A monk asked, "Mount Sumeru contains a mustard seed, and a mustard seed contains Mount Sumeru—what is the meaning?" The master said, "Just right."</p>
<lb n="0377c18" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377c1801">A monk asked, "I earnestly wish to understand this matter, and feel my effort is intimate and pressing—why is it that I cannot
<lb n="0377c19" ed="J" />break through?" The master said, "Do you understand last night’s case?" He said, "This cannot deceive me."
<lb n="0377c20" ed="J" />The master said, "And yet you say you cannot break through." The monk stood still. The master shouted, "Dead man! Get out!" The monk left,
<lb n="0377c21" ed="J" />and at noon returned holding the silence tablet, presenting it and saying, "I return it to the master." The master seized him and said, "Speak! Speak!" The monk
<lb n="0377c22" ed="J" />shouted. The master said, "Not yet, say more." The monk shouted again. The master said, "After the shout, what then?" He said, "Under the eaves
<lb n="0377c23" ed="J" />the rain drips, drop by drop." The master said, "The dripping rain under the eaves—what is that to you?" The monk shouted again. The master
<lb n="0377c24" ed="J" />said, "Wild shouting," and pushed him out.</p>
<lb n="0377c25" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377c2501">A monk asked, "Within delusion there is awakening, within awakening there is delusion. What is delusion within awakening?" The master said, "Why ask such confused questions?"
<lb n="0377c26" ed="J" />what?</p>
<lb n="0377c27" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0377c2701">A monk from Yuezhu Hermitage came for instruction and asked, "What is it to hide the body where there are no traces, and where there are no traces, not to hide the body?"
<lb n="0377c28" ed="J" />The master said, "Yuezhu Hermitage does not permit you to hide your tracks." The monk said, "What is it that dharmas abide in their dharma positions,
<lb n="0377c29" ed="J" />and that worldly appearances constantly abide?" The master pointed to his seat and said, "This position is yours." The monk
<lb n="0377c30" ed="J" />had no reply; the master struck him.</p>
<pb n="0378a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0378a" />
<lb n="0378a01" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0378a0101">Zhuoya came for instruction. The master said, "Why do you not leave?" He replied, "At just such a time, who is it that goes and who
<lb n="0378a02" ed="J" />remains?" The master was silent for a while, then said, "Do you understand?" He said, "Understanding aside, ultimately who remains?" The master said, "You
<lb n="0378a03" ed="J" />are still indulging in false thinking." He said, "What can be done about this?" The master said, "Where do you see this old
<lb n="0378a04" ed="J" />monk?" He said, "Eye to eye." The master said, "Blind." He said, "Blind, blind!" The master then shouted.</p>
<lb n="0378a05" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0378a0501">One day the master ordered Jie’an Jin and Yichu Yuan to present the final lines of their verses. The two submitted them, and the master, after reading,
<lb n="0378a06" ed="J" />then entrusted them both with a verse, saying, "This stretch along the current has neither beginning nor end; I entrust it to the lion
<lb n="0378a07" ed="J" />cub, whose roar fills the whole earth."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378a08" ed="J" />
<lb n="0378a09" ed="J" />
<lb n="0378a10" ed="J" />
<lb n="0378a11" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Raising Ancient Cases</cb:mulu><head>Raising Ancient Cases</head>
<lb n="0378a12" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0378a1201">He cited: "Chan Master Ruiyan Yan daily called to himself, 'Master!' and then answered himself, and said, 'Be alert!
<lb n="0378a13" ed="J" />Be alert! In the future do not be deceived by others.'" The master said, "In broad daylight under the blue sky, dreaming, and in the dream repeatedly calling
<lb n="0378a14" ed="J" />the master—even if alert and answering, it is still a masterless wandering spirit."</p>
<lb n="0378a15" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0378a1501">He cited: "Chan Master Fazhou Ji of Tianning was asked by Layman Lu of Wutai, 'Before the diagram, was there originally the Changes?'
<lb n="0378a16" ed="J" />Ning said, 'If not, what would you draw?' Lu said, 'After the diagram, how is it?' Ning said, 'Originally there is not a single drawing.'
<lb n="0378a17" ed="J" />Lu said, 'There are clearly sixty-four hexagrams, how can you say there is none?' Ning said, 'Layman, do not cling to words
<lb n="0378a18" ed="J" />so readily.' Lu said, 'Please, master, apart from words, bring forth one line and let me see.' Ning called, 'Wutai!' The layman responded. Ning
<lb n="0378a19" ed="J" />said, 'From where does this line arise?'" The master said, "Before and after the diagram, discussing existence or nonexistence, all are
<lb n="0378a20" ed="J" />unrelated to the Great Changes. Even if there is a call and a response and the lines and images are clear, it is still not the ultimate
<lb n="0378a21" ed="J" />rule for a patch-robed monk. Before the diagram, was there originally the Changes? Why did that old fellow of Tianning not immediately call Wutai, and when
<lb n="0378a22" ed="J" />he responded, then say, 'Was there originally the Changes?' Here Layman Lu surely had another point of entry,
<lb n="0378a23" ed="J" />thus avoiding so much later entanglement."</p>
<lb n="0378a24" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0378a2401">He cited: "At an evening instruction, Chan Master Hengchuan Gong said, 'Shaoshi has no gate—how then can one pass through? In the deep of night
<lb n="0378a25" ed="J" />better to stand patiently and listen as I speak of east and west.'" The master said, "Excellent—no gate at all."</p>
<lb n="0378a26" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0378a2601">He cited: "When the Venerable Guang of Nanming was viewing snow, an attendant monk said, 'The whole mountain is covered with snow.' Nanming said, 'A follower
<lb n="0378a27" ed="J" />of sound and pursuer of form.' The monk said, 'Please, master, speak a phrase apart from sound and form.' Nanming said, 'The whole mountain is
<lb n="0378a28" ed="J" />snow.'" The master said, "This monk pressed against a naked blade and came away alive—indeed skillful. The old man Nanming
<lb n="0378a29" ed="J" />exhausted all his seasoning, yet in the end did not quite satisfy. Here, is there anyone who can speak a phrase apart from sound and form?
<lb n="0378a30" ed="J" />After a long pause he said, "Above all, do not say the whole mountain is snow."</p></cb:div>
<pb n="0378b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0378b" />
<lb n="0378b01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Verses on Ancient Cases</cb:mulu><head>Verses on Ancient Cases</head>
<lb n="0378b02" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b0201" style="margin-left:2em">The World-Honored One at Birth</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b03" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b0301">Knowing the kindness, one repays the kindness—at the moment, how could Yunmen be let go? Later generations should not say empty harshness,
<lb n="0378b04" ed="J" />even now one blow leaves a lasting mark.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b05" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b0501" style="margin-left:2em">The World-Honored One Holding Up a Flower</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b06" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b0601">At the very end it is lifted up and shown to gods and humans; meeting with a smile is no small affinity; the myriad phenomena are all the true
<lb n="0378b07" ed="J" />eye; the udumbara flower blooms fresh in the midst of fire.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b08" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b0801" style="margin-left:2em">A Non-Buddhist Asks the Buddha</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b09" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b0901">The jade flute, pure and mixed, plays a new melody; the felt board lightly tapped keeps the rhythm; yet those seated do not understand
<lb n="0378b10" ed="J" />how to listen, and instead continue another tune that confuses the tones.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b11" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b1101" style="margin-left:2em">Baizhang, attending Mazu, returned from the mountains to the quarters and wept bitterly. A companion asked, "Are you remembering
<lb n="0378b12" ed="J" />your parents?" Baizhang said, "No." "Were you scolded by someone?" "No." "Then why are you crying?"
<lb n="0378b13" ed="J" />Baizhang said, "Go ask the master." The companion went to ask Mazu, who said, "Go ask him."
<lb n="0378b14" ed="J" />The companion returned to the quarters and saw Baizhang laughing loudly, and asked, "Why were you just now
<lb n="0378b15" ed="J" />crying, and now why are you laughing?" Baizhang said, "Just now I cried, now I laugh." The companion was bewildered.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b16" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b1601">One bout of crying, one bout of laughing—before and after both return to the ancient tune; the many are not of Ziqi’s mind,
<lb n="0378b17" ed="J" />following sound and chasing form, it is hard to know the subtle.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b18" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b1801" style="margin-left:2em">Nanquan addressed the assembly, saying, "Not mind, not Buddha, not a thing."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b19" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b1901">Killing without seeing blood—this is Master Wang; where one lets go of body and life is precisely the time to repay kindness.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b20" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b2001" style="margin-left:2em">A monk asked Zhaozhou, "Does a dog have Buddha-nature or not?" Zhaozhou said, "No."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b21" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b2101">The dog thus repays the absence of Buddha-nature; wrapped in cotton, it strikes a protruding stone and enacts the true command; atop Mount Sumeru it strikes the golden
<lb n="0378b22" ed="J" />bell, startling the monkey out of naga concentration.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b23" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b2301" style="margin-left:2em">Zhaozhou asked Nanquan, "Where does one who knows go?" Nanquan said, "In front of the mountain,
<lb n="0378b24" ed="J" />to the lay patron’s house to become a water buffalo." Zhaozhou said, "Thank you for the instruction." Nanquan said:
<lb n="0378b25" ed="J" />"Last night at the third watch, the moon reached the window."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b26" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b2601">Last night at the third watch the moon was deep and still; meeting face to face goes beyond the ordinary stream; green grass everywhere
<lb n="0378b27" ed="J" />is fine, before and behind the mountain one may wander at ease.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b28" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b2801" style="margin-left:2em">Zhaozhou asked Touzi, "When one greatly dies and then lives again, how is it?" Touzi said, "Do not travel at night;
<lb n="0378b29" ed="J" />you must arrive at dawn."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378b30" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378b3001">Turning the hand forms clouds, overturning it makes rain; extending the foot is originally within drawing it back; hanging up sheep and selling dog, old and fitting
<pb n="0378c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0378c" />
<lb n="0378c01" ed="J" />whether there is profit or no profit, one does not leave the marketplace.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c02" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c0201" style="margin-left:2em">A monk asked Shoushan, "What is Buddha?" The mountain said, "The bride rides the donkey while the mother-in-law leads it."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c03" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c0301">The bride rides the donkey while the mother-in-law leads it; the wondrous body is upright and naturally majestic; it is not that Shoushan’s meeting
<lb n="0378c04" ed="J" />after is good karma becoming bad karma.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c05" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c0501" style="margin-left:2em">Linji ascended the seat; a monk came forth, Linji shouted; the monk also shouted and then bowed, and Linji immediately
<lb n="0378c06" ed="J" />struck him. Another monk came; Linji raised the whisk; the monk bowed, and Linji struck him. Another monk
<lb n="0378c07" ed="J" />came; Linji raised the whisk, the monk paid no attention, and Linji also struck him. Another monk came; Linji again raised the whisk,
<lb n="0378c08" ed="J" />and the monk said, "Thank you, Venerable, for the instruction." Linji still struck him.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c09" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c0901">Northern snow drifts and opens Yanmen; level sands in disorder roll up tumbleweed roots; for fame and rank one should not calculate the capture of living
<lb n="0378c10" ed="J" />heads, but directly cut down Loulan to repay the nation’s kindness.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c11" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c1101" style="margin-left:2em">When Xuan Sha saw a newcomer bow, he said, "Bow properly; because of me you are able to bow to me."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c12" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c1201">Because of me you are able to bow to me—la-li la la-li—smash open the stinking skull; the Dharma body is hidden in the northern
<lb n="0378c13" ed="J" />Dipper.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c14" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c1401" style="margin-left:2em">Mingzhao ascended the hall; as soon as the assembly gathered, he said, "The wind is sharp and biting; this is not a place for you to settle your
<lb n="0378c15" ed="J" />body and establish your life. For now return to the warm room to discuss it." Then he went back to the abbot’s quarters. The assembly followed and stood
<lb n="0378c16" ed="J" />there. Mingzhao said, "As soon as you reach the warm room, you are already nodding off." He drove them out with his staff.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c17" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c1701">The biting wind makes words dim and hazy; discussion in the warm room turns out of tune. If you wish to find a place to settle body and life,
<lb n="0378c18" ed="J" />you must sweep away all traces of wild foxes.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c19" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c1901" style="margin-left:2em">Xuan Sha said, "As for this matter, it is like a single stretch of farmland, its four boundaries clearly demarcated and
<lb n="0378c20" ed="J" />deeded and sold to all of you; only the central tree still belongs to this old monk."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c21" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c2101">Bei the ascetic, skilled in clever dealings—where will you find the deed for the sold fields and gardens? In old age he still clings to this withered tree,
<lb n="0378c22" ed="J" />unaware that his whole body is buried in wild grass.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c23" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c2301" style="margin-left:2em">Jianshan said, "There is no dharma apart from the present moment; the meaning is in the present moment. It is not a dharma of the present moment, beyond what the ears
<lb n="0378c24" ed="J" />and eyes can reach."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c25" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c2501">Sounds and forms stand purely arrayed before one; if you try to grasp and observe them, it is entirely irrelevant. For it is all the affair of the official household
<lb n="0378c26" ed="J" />things—do not allow ordinary people to privately probe them.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c27" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c2701" style="margin-left:2em">Dongshan said, "Words do not unfold matters; speech does not match the opportunity. Those who take up words are lost; those who stick to phrases are
<lb n="0378c28" ed="J" />deluded."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0378c29" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0378c2901">The fan-selling old woman covers her face with her hand; the oil-selling girl slicks her hair with water. It is not that their flesh and bones are returned to good condition,
<lb n="0378c30" ed="J" />even if they apply rouge and powder, they still are not charming.</p></cb:div>
<pb n="0379a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0379a" />
<lb n="0379a01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a0101" style="margin-left:2em">Bajiao ascended the hall, picked up his staff and showed it to the assembly, saying, "If you have a staff, I give you a staff;
<lb n="0379a02" ed="J" />if you do not have a staff, I take away your staff." He leaned on his staff,
<lb n="0379a03" ed="J" />and descended the seat.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a04" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a0401">The old Bajiao displays his family style to the fullest; in words and actions there is nothing finer. Benevolence and righteousness indeed arise from poverty,
<lb n="0379a05" ed="J" />while worldly sentiment favors the wealthy households.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a06" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a0601" style="margin-left:2em">A monk asked Yantou, "When the ancient sail is not yet hoisted, how is it?" Yantou said, "A small fish swallows a big fish."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a07" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a0701">A small fish swallows a big fish; Mount Sumeru rushes into the sea; when the ancient sail is not yet hoisted, an iron boat is rocked by a tailwind.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a08" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a0801" style="margin-left:2em">Gushan Breaks the Arrow</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a09" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a0901">Those who prize righteousness often rely on reckless valor; just as they rush into battle, arrows lose their sharpness. Pitiable, the mouse-like trickster seeking scars
<lb n="0379a10" ed="J" />on his hands, still mocking the old frozen pus of village sentiment.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a11" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a1101" style="margin-left:2em">The Old Woman Burns the Hermitage</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a12" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a1201">Peach blossoms red, holding last night’s rain; willows green, wrapped in morning mist. Fragrant spring is the best—how many eyes can truly see through it?</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a13" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a1301" style="margin-left:2em">Because a monk asked Zhaozhou, "Having just entered the monastery, I beg for the master’s instruction." Zhaozhou said, "Have you eaten congee yet?
<lb n="0379a14" ed="J" />The monk said, "I have eaten." Zhaozhou said, "Go wash your bowl." The monk had an awakening.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a15" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a1501">The golden wind brings a bit of chill in gusts; scattered autumn light fills the roadside. Travelers in confusion still cannot return,
<lb n="0379a16" ed="J" />and when meeting others, one must not make mistaken interpretations.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a17" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a1701" style="margin-left:2em">Things Do Not Shift</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a18" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a1801">Bamboo shoots sprout and inevitably become bamboo; fallen flowers cannot be reattached to the branch. I recall as a child riding a bamboo
<lb n="0379a19" ed="J" />horse; now once again it is the time of white hair.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a20" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a2001" style="margin-left:2em">Zhaozhou asked Nanquan, "What is the Way?" Nanquan said, "Ordinary mind is the Way."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a21" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a2101">When angry there is affliction; when joyful there is playful laughter. If you call it ordinary, it is like a falcon flying past Silla.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a22" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a2201" style="margin-left:2em">Fenyang’s Ten Wisdoms Are One Suchness</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a23" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a2301">At sixteen her brows are beautifully refined; in the secluded chamber she vainly grieves, recalling private feelings; she often calls out to Xiaoyu, not without
<lb n="0379a24" ed="J" />reason, only fearing that her lover’s heart is not her heart.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a25" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a2501" style="margin-left:2em">Xuefeng ascended the hall and said, "Venerable ones! At Wangzhou Pavilion I have met you; at Wu
<lb n="0379a26" ed="J" />shi Ridge I have met you; before the monks’ hall I have met you."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a27" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a2701">At Elephant Bone Cliff the words are most intimate; monks’ hall, Wushi, Wangzhou Pavilion—like tiny insects crawling in red flames
<lb n="0379a28" ed="J" />of fire, like a gnat carrying Mount Kunlun on its eyelashes.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379a29" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379a2901" style="margin-left:2em">Jingqing asked Xuan Sha, "I have just entered the monastery community and beg the master to point out a path of entry."
<lb n="0379a30" ed="J" />Xuan Sha said, "Do you still hear the sound of Yanxi Stream?" Jingqing said, "I hear it." Xuan Sha said, "Enter from here."</p></cb:div>
<pb n="0379b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0379b" />
<lb n="0379b01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b0101">Newly entering the monastery, asking for the path of entry—completely immersed and drowned in the sound of Yanxi Stream. Ridiculous Xie San, who has no other
<lb n="0379b02" ed="J" />method, habitually uses public goods for private favors.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b03" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b0301" style="margin-left:2em">Lingyun Sees Peach Blossoms</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b04" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b0401">In spring fragrance, everywhere is abundant beauty; wandering guests are so many their eyes are obscured. If you do not believe the spring lord has any private
<lb n="0379b05" ed="J" />intention, only Lingyun alone was permitted to awaken upon the peach blossoms.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b06" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b0601" style="margin-left:2em">A monk took leave of Zhaozhou. Zhaozhou said, "Where are you going?" He said, "To various places to learn the Buddha Dharma." Zhaozhou raised
<lb n="0379b07" ed="J" />his whisk and said, "Where there is a Buddha, do not stay; where there is no Buddha, pass through quickly; three thousand
<lb n="0379b08" ed="J" />miles away, when meeting people, do not make mistaken claims." The monk said, "In that case I will not go." Zhaozhou said:
<lb n="0379b09" ed="J" />"Pick willow catkins, pick willow catkins."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b10" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b1001">When the mind’s thought and path are utterly cut off, bound up like paper and hemp—how many kinds are there? Even if one has dragon eyes and hawk eyes,
<lb n="0379b11" ed="J" />such a person, when willow catkins fall in disorder, still finds it hard to see clearly.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b12" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b1201" style="margin-left:2em">Minister Lu Gen asked Nanquan, "In my home there is a stone, on which one may sit or
<lb n="0379b13" ed="J" />lie. I intend to carve it into a Buddha—would that be permissible?" He said, "It is permissible." The minister said, "Would it not be impermissible?"
<lb n="0379b14" ed="J" />Nanquan said, "It is not permissible, not permissible."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b15" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b1501">Creation and transformation are endlessly extravagant in intent; where there is no covering, there is again covering. The east wind is gentle and unrestrained, with not much
<lb n="0379b16" ed="J" />power, blowing flowers into bloom and then into falling again.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b17" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b1701" style="margin-left:2em">A monk asked Qianfeng, "The Bhagavats of the ten directions—one road is the gate of nirvana."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b18" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b1801">With a compassionate heart he points and questions the monk—how can this compare to not knowing the arising of right and wrong? The ancient road has always been like a taut string,
<lb n="0379b19" ed="J" />yet instead it makes one walk a rugged and winding path.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b20" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b2001" style="margin-left:2em">Zhaozhou makes use of the twelve hours</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b21" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b2101">boar, dog, rooster, monkey, sheep, horse, snake, dragon, rabbit, tiger, ox, rat—all follow the old monk, until even the plucked and hairless
<lb n="0379b22" ed="J" />birds and rabbits are exhausted; boundless elegance passes through an entire life.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b23" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b2301" style="margin-left:2em">Shushan asked Weishan, "Is it a phrase or no phrase?"</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b24" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b2401">When vines wither and trees fall, where does the phrase return? Ancient Buddhas extend compassion without much deliberation. Fortunately, by the wind blowing the fire
<lb n="0379b25" ed="J" />into strength, suddenly within a smile one sees weapons of war.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b26" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b2601" style="margin-left:2em">Lu Gen asked Nanquan about the story cited regarding Dharma Master Zhao</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b27" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b2701">The minister merely passes along the words of the ancients; like flowers in Wang Lao’s courtyard seen in a dream. If monks and laypeople wish to clarify the true
<lb n="0379b28" ed="J" />meaning, they should quickly take up the subtle details and examine them well.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379b29" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379b2901" style="margin-left:2em">Yunmen picked up his staff and said, "The teachings say: 'Ordinary beings take it as existence; the Two Vehicles analyze
<lb n="0379b30" ed="J" />it as nonexistence; pratyekabuddhas call it illusory existence; bodhisattvas see its very substance as emptiness.'" Then he said, "A patch-robed
<pb n="0379c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0379c" />
<lb n="0379c01" ed="J" />monk, when seeing a staff, should just call it a staff; when walking, just walk; when sitting, just sit; in all cases do not
<lb n="0379c02" ed="J" />move it at all."</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c03" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c0301">In a thousand rivers there is water and a thousand moons; for ten thousand miles of cloudless sky there is a ten thousand mile sky. In past and present mountains and rivers, people themselves
<lb n="0379c04" ed="J" />differ; the patch-robed monk’s staff again proclaims this.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c05" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c0501" style="margin-left:2em">The Old Woman of Mount Tai’s Saying</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c06" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c0601">Busy old woman of Mount Tai pointing out the road—more pitiful still is the scrutinized ascetic Nian. Even if in a dark room one betrays one’s conscience,
<lb n="0379c07" ed="J" />what can one do when the gods and spirits are as swift as lightning?</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c08" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c0801" style="margin-left:2em">Yunmen said, "Hearing sound, one awakens to the Way; seeing form, one clarifies the mind." Then he said, "Avalokiteśvara Bodhisattva
<lb n="0379c09" ed="J" />took money to buy a foreign cake, then put it down and said, 'So it turns out to be just a steamed bun.'"<g ref="#CB05286" /></p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c10" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c1001">Deaf and blind, without resource, he raises this story; yet he takes a foreign cake and calls it a steamed bun. Right and wrong do not reach the high cliff<g ref="#CB05286" />
<lb n="0379c11" ed="J" />Below, it again follows the spring wind, stirring the treetops.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c12" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c1201" style="margin-left:2em">Verses on Herding the Ox by Chan Master Puming</p>
<lb n="0379c13" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0379c1301" style="margin-left:2em">Not Yet Tamed</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c14" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c1401">At the low edge of dark clouds a single roar resounds; how could one believe the road beneath the feet is far? At that time the boy takes up the rope,
<lb n="0379c15" ed="J" />never paying attention to or cherishing the good seedlings.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c16" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c1601" style="margin-left:2em">First Taming</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c17" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c1701">Today the nostrils are first pierced; such wild nature requires only the whip. One must make it clearly understand ordinary
<lb n="0379c18" ed="J" />affairs, regardless of the whole body being dragged by black karma.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c19" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c1901" style="margin-left:2em">Under Control</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c20" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c2001">Now the paths are no longer run in vain; the whip and rope slowly consent to follow. At home the mountains, water, and grass are supplied as needed,
<lb n="0379c21" ed="J" />and one walks at ease, unwearied in graceful ease.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c22" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c2201" style="margin-left:2em">Turning the Head Back</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c23" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c2301">By the green willow dike and the blue stream’s source, the scene is clear and the wind gentle. The water buffalo turns its head and at last
<lb n="0379c24" ed="J" />consents of itself; under the bright moon the return path is slowly lingered upon.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c25" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c2501" style="margin-left:2em">Fully Tamed</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c26" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c2601">Wherever it comes from, it passes over here; turning left and right, all is peaceful. The yellow oriole calls until the mountain flowers
<lb n="0379c27" ed="J" />seem to smile—within sound and form, how could one not be pulled along?</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c28" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c2801" style="margin-left:2em">Without Obstruction</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0379c29" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0379c2901">Falling away into empty space, the myriad forms are such; man and ox roam freely without restraint. The whip and rope are cast aside without a trace,
<lb n="0379c30" ed="J" />leaving only the lingering inspiration of a single tune of plum blossoms.</p></cb:div>
<pb n="0380a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0380a" />
<lb n="0380a01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a0101" style="margin-left:2em">Natural Flow</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a02" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a0201">I rest in a single tranquil awakening; I let it wander the grassy path and play among fine moss. Fallen flowers reach the knees in the spring mountains,
<lb n="0380a03" ed="J" />and in the late evening still splash like richly brocaded red clouds.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a04" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a0401" style="margin-left:2em">Mutual Forgetting</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a05" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a0501">White clouds drift across the bright moon; moon and cloud become one unified color. In the realm of wisdom at this time, mostly there is no
<lb n="0380a06" ed="J" />understanding—what talk is there of north, south, east, or west?</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a07" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a0701" style="margin-left:2em">Solitary Illumination</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a08" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a0801">With the house broken and desolate, only four bare walls remain; now clouds are still and the moon is bright and calm. It is surely not a matter of displaying daily progress along the path,
<lb n="0380a09" ed="J" />yet it is still good to press through the barrier with one’s whole body.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a10" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a1001" style="margin-left:2em">Both Extinguished</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a11" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a1101">When all activity is exhausted, where can one seek traces of shadow? One should not carve emptiness within emptiness. Who would say it stands revealed, open and clear,
<lb n="0380a12" ed="J" />while bees and butterflies are deluded, lost in the clusters beneath the flowers?</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a13" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a1301" style="margin-left:2em">Linji School</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a14" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a1401">Staff blows like raindrops, shouts like thunder; sentient beings and Buddhas alike are allowed to split open their skulls. Since he extinguished the true Dharma eye,
<lb n="0380a15" ed="J" />fortunately there is nothing left to arrange.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a16" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a1601" style="margin-left:2em">Caodong School</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a17" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a1701">When incense fades in the ancient hall and lamps are extinguished, in the bright moon beyond the curtain one’s steps still linger. On the jade steps, as night falls, together with the clouds
<lb n="0380a18" ed="J" />stillness reigns, and the golden-locked mysterious gate is not easily peered into.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a19" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a1901" style="margin-left:2em">Yunmen School</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a20" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a2001">With an aura like a king, yet a disposition that is circuitous, he habitually sets up a single word as the pivot of a barrier; how could the myriad things and types
<lb n="0380a21" ed="J" />be counted, when even the breath in the throat is blocked and gone?</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a22" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a2201" style="margin-left:2em">Guiyang School</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a23" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a2301">Father and son, the whole household, are all dreamlike bodies; playing with marbles, their activity and rest are all ungraspable. When the workings are exhausted and emotions forgotten,
<lb n="0380a24" ed="J" />at that point, who is the one who calls donkey and deer?</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a25" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="orig"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a2501" style="margin-left:2em">Fayan School</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a26" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="commentary"><p xml:id="pJ27p0380a2601">Green mountains and clear waters form the gateway to the profound; jeweled nets interweave before the eyes. Once the patterns are laid out and gathered up,
<lb n="0380a27" ed="J" />all is exhausted—utterly bare, the four similes empty and desolate.</p></cb:div></cb:div>
<lb n="0380a28" ed="J" />
<lb n="0380a29" ed="J" />
<lb n="0380a30" ed="J" />
<pb n="0380b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0380b" />
<lb n="0380b01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Image Praise</cb:mulu><head>Image Praise</head>
<lb n="0380b02" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Great Bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara (requested by Shenyuan Hermitage)</cb:mulu><head>Great Bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara<note place="inline">深遠庵請</note></head>
<lb n="0380b03" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380b0301">You, senior seat! Sitting silently in a cold place, dull and dazed—what are you thinking of? I imagine that at that time,
<lb n="0380b04" ed="J" />finding yourself without any way out, you once stood by the Luoyang Bridge, selling off all your elegance, and on the Golden Sand Beach you once made
<lb n="0380b05" ed="J" />a marital promise; in Purple Bamboo you manifested form, in white robes you displayed dignity, with the thirty-two manifestations, adapting to circumstances and understanding affairs, with a thousand eyes
<lb n="0380b06" ed="J" />and a thousand hands—bringing blessings and calamities, responding to cries and saving beings from suffering, adding salt and vinegar, making strange demons and marvels. Why is this so?
<lb n="0380b07" ed="J" />Why? Who is not a true man? Countless, countless. If you pick them out, all become mere idle talk. Rather than this,
<lb n="0380b08" ed="J" />today return to the east dormitory of Shenyuan Hermitage, let go of the mind with its countless longings; as a stick of incense burns out
<lb n="0380b09" ed="J" />and a vase of flowers stands there, in broad daylight no one sees it.</p>
<lb n="0380b10" ed="J" />
<p cb:type="head3" xml:id="pJ27p0380b1001">Again</p>
<lb n="0380b11" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380b1101">The winds and waves of the Southern Sea are perilous and deep; in the Three Tianzhu Temples there are few who understand. Lightly I hide myself within the painter’s
<lb n="0380b12" ed="J" />brush—sending a message to people of the time: do not search in vain. If not searched in vain, the willow branch still stands in the pure vase.</p>
<lb n="0380b13" ed="J" />
<p cb:type="head3" xml:id="pJ27p0380b1301">Again</p>
<lb n="0380b14" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380b1401">Cloud mountains, Purple Bamboo, white parrot; green willow, pure vase, mind of water and moon—this is the true face of Perfect Penetration,
<lb n="0380b15" ed="J" />each time it is depicted, it appears newly.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380b16" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Treading-the-Turtle Image</cb:mulu><head>Treading-the-Turtle Image</head>
<lb n="0380b17" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380b1701">Beneath Purple Bamboo, treading the head of the giant turtle, full of heroic spirit; holding a willow branch to sprinkle sweet dew, it is pure compassion.
<lb n="0380b18" ed="J" />It makes Good Wealth stand until his feet ache; even the parrot flying high is still a little short of it.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380b19" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Image of Great Bodhisattva Samantabhadra</cb:mulu><head>Image of Great Bodhisattva Samantabhadra</head>
<lb n="0380b20" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380b2001">He is the King of Great Vows; manifesting traces from the original ground, with not a single thought arising, the all-seeing eye is hard to find. One might think he rides a white
<lb n="0380b21" ed="J" />elephant, or even wish to become a wandering fugitive, but encountering the old master Puming, one is seen through with a cool gaze. Tell me, what is seen?
<lb n="0380b22" ed="J" />A bowl falling to the ground, a plate breaking into seven pieces.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380b23" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Image of the Cloth Bag Monk (requested by Nesheng for praise)</cb:mulu><head>Image of the Cloth Bag Monk<note place="inline">訥生求讚</note></head>
<lb n="0380b24" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380b2401">Carrying the cloth bag, he is scorned by some, smiling cheerfully; he is also loved by others. Once in the street he begged for a single coin; behold,
<lb n="0380b25" ed="J" />you can never repay the debts of the human world.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380b26" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Image of the Venerable Southern Bright, our root teacher</cb:mulu><head>Image of the Venerable Southern Bright, our root teacher</head>
<lb n="0380b27" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380b2701">In the old ascetic at Xinfeng Temple, wild and unrestrained—who could do anything about his mad roaring? With a single cry, chess and wine both rise in value,
<lb n="0380b28" ed="J" />everything is exhausted; he suddenly tramples over the ancient Vairocana. In front of the Three-cedar Hall he probes the stream and measures the water; on the Five Elders Peak
<lb n="0380b29" ed="J" />he stirs up waves and raises tides, using hammer and tongs on the monks, examining fine and coarse capacities. In the end, what final instruction is given? The fishing hook
<lb n="0380b30" ed="J" />line sinks into the river; lazily he sings no more.</p></cb:div>
<pb n="0380c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0380c" />
<lb n="0380c01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Image of Great Master Lianchi of Yunqi</cb:mulu><head>Image of Great Master Lianchi of Yunqi</head>
<lb n="0380c02" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380c0201">Tearing open the Confucian robe, donning the purple kāṣāya, striking through all seven strokes, followed by students from all directions. He cleared away the thickets of the Five Clouds,
<lb n="0380c03" ed="J" />straightened the ancient base of taming tigers, replacing people’s eyes with black beans, cutting off life itself with
<lb n="0380c04" ed="J" />the hammer and tongs. Alas! How many times at the bamboo window he picked up the iron pen, while fragrant winds spread through the Lotus Flower Pond.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380c05" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Image of Great Master Zhenjiwen (requested by Huiji)</cb:mulu><head>Image of Great Master Zhenjiwen<note place="inline">慧基請</note></head>
<lb n="0380c06" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380c0601">With a single heart of an old mother, he straightens out the hands and feet of people of his time; with a fiercely sharp tongue, he scolds until even blind groping
<lb n="0380c07" ed="J" />Chan study is overturned. Treasuring goodness and purity and compassion, nothing is not right; in greatness there is samadhi, in wisdom there is the foundation—taking errors
<lb n="0380c08" ed="J" />and fitting them onto errors. If you ask about the family style of Zhenji, do not try to measure it by shadows.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380c09" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Half-portrait of Elder Hao at seventy</cb:mulu><head>Half-portrait of Elder Hao at seventy</head>
<lb n="0380c10" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380c1001">Praise for this old worthy: his life has reached the age of seventy. He displays long-eared features and finely arched brows. As for his family style,
<lb n="0380c11" ed="J" />it is without intention and without action. He deeply tastes prajñā, meeting joy and anger at the proper times. At times like sudden thunder and fierce wind, he is no less
<lb n="0380c12" ed="J" />fierce than the wrath of an asura; at times like spring flowers and autumn moon, he is even more compassionate than Avalokiteśvara.
<lb n="0380c13" ed="J" />Though the world has the marvelous hands of Zhang and Wu, who could imitate his whole body? I dare ask the younger generations: where is that half
<lb n="0380c14" ed="J" />body? Ah!<unclear></unclear></p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380c15" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Self-portrait (general title)</cb:mulu><head>Self-portrait<note place="inline">總題</note></head>
<lb n="0380c16" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380c1601">So emaciated that he can barely bear his clothes, his mind is so sharp it is hard to tell truth from falsehood; sitting upright, there is no place for entering correct mindfulness,
<lb n="0380c17" ed="J" />in his presence there is no compassion, joy, or equanimity; he holds a white staff across his arms—if a Buddha comes, he strikes him; if a demon comes,
<lb n="0380c18" ed="J" />he strikes him too.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0380c19" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Painting and colophon of Layman Huang of Sumen Cultivating His Aspiration</cb:mulu><head>Painting and colophon of Layman Huang of Sumen Cultivating His Aspiration</head>
<lb n="0380c20" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380c2001">Exquisitely patterned rocks, coiling ancient pines, vast clouded mountains—cranes and deer move with ease. Within it are father and son,
<lb n="0380c21" ed="J" />as in the moment of passing through the courtyard. Not bound to poetry and rites, they quietly dwell in stillness. With filial intent in nurturing, how could one be stuck on outward appearance?
<lb n="0380c22" ed="J" />Graceful and gentle at the knees of elders, joyfully lingering together; household servants present offerings—could it be even jujube fruit? Asked whether there is any surplus,
<lb n="0380c23" ed="J" />the reply is that there is no lack. On the clean table are flowers for appreciation; the sutra cases have not been opened, yet all affairs are already settled.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0380c2301" n="0380c2301" /><anchor xml:id="beg0380c2301" n="0380c2301" /><anchor xml:id="end0380c2301" />
<lb n="0380c24" ed="J" />In this very grove and dwelling, how is it different from the Land of Ultimate Bliss? Over a hundred thousand miles away, it is only a single awakening.</p>
<lb n="0380c25" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0380c2501" style="margin-left:2em">When the layman’s late father changed his mat and passed away, his final instructions had long been given; thus he was able to remember past kindness and paint
<lb n="0380c26" ed="J" />this picture called Cultivating Aspiration, and also to take his place in giving refuge and precepts, giving him the Dharma name Awakening Vow. May he
<lb n="0380c27" ed="J" />awaken in a single realization, and may practice and vow be equal. Puming therefore sincerely records this.</p></cb:div></cb:div>
<lb n="0380c28" ed="J" />
<lb n="0380c29" ed="J" />
<lb n="0380c30" ed="J" />
<pb n="0381a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0381a" />
<lb n="0381a01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Dharma Instructions</cb:mulu><head>Dharma Instructions</head>
<lb n="0381a02" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Layman Zanruo Huang</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Layman Zanruo Huang</head>
<lb n="0381a03" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0381a0301">The Buddha taught all dharmas in order to cross over all minds; if I have no such mind at all, what use are all the dharmas?
<lb n="0381a04" ed="J" />If even the true Dharma is not established, how could false teachings exist? When one speaks of right only in opposition to wrong, how can that right truly be obtained?
<lb n="0381a05" ed="J" />Right and wrong are merely names, with no real substance. Because sentient beings do not understand this, our school speaks of direct pointing.
<lb n="0381a06" ed="J" />Directly take it up at once; it is plainly the matter of everyday use. If one point is penetrated, all places are simultaneously resolved.
<lb n="0381a07" ed="J" />Looking back at these names and words, they too are dream speech; even dream speech is not established—what kind of realm is this?
<lb n="0381a08" ed="J" />Old bald slave Puming has spoken all this old-woman Chan; he should himself receive thirty blows—yet not even one blow can be measured against another.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0381a09" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Showing to Zen practitioner Zhao</cb:mulu><head>Showing to Zen practitioner Zhao</head>
<lb n="0381a10" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0381a1001">When literary patterns have not yet formed, how could one put brush to paper? Once the tip of the brush is set in motion, myriad traces appear. If the practitioner can see clearly here,
<lb n="0381a11" ed="J" />if he perceives it truly, it is like burning a red sun beneath the Persian sea.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0381a12" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Zen practitioner Huideng requesting instruction</cb:mulu><head>Zen practitioner Huideng requesting instruction</head>
<lb n="0381a13" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0381a1301">One's inherent wisdom lamp cannot be obtained even from before the kalpas; it arises only occasionally in accordance with conditions, and its light completely pervades everywhere.
<lb n="0381a14" ed="J" />It darkens even the brightness of buddhas and patriarchs, and yet it illuminates and shatters the darkness of all beings. I say to Zen practitioner Deng: do not take it as something special or fixed.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0381a15" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Du Huayu presents a fan and requests instruction</cb:mulu><head>Du Huayu presents a fan and requests instruction</head>
<lb n="0381a16" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0381a1601">When Yanguan specially sought the rhinoceros-horn fan, the clear river was stirred and the azure dragon appeared. If Mr. Du can also act with such sharpness,
<lb n="0381a17" ed="J" />acting fluently and decisively, then even iron caltrops would be tempered in a blazing furnace. At the tip of the flames, one speaks the unborn Dharma, and the buddhas of the three times stand
<lb n="0381a18" ed="J" />See right there on the ground. It is neither half nor full, neither partial nor complete, neither provisional nor real, neither sudden nor gradual. Sweep away all entangling vines
<lb n="0381a19" ed="J" />idle proclamations, and then you may sit in the hall of the Empty King with your robe on. If you mistake what appears in the streets and alleys as your own,
<lb n="0381a20" ed="J" />even then you still will not realize it.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0381a21" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Zen practitioner Zhiyi of Mount Jing requesting instruction</cb:mulu><head>Zen practitioner Zhiyi of Mount Jing requesting instruction</head>
<lb n="0381a22" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0381a2201">Zen practitioner Zhiyi has come from thousands of miles away, bringing letters from various gentry, inviting me
<lb n="0381a23" ed="J" />to return to Zhejiang to meet; monks and laypeople alike are tightly entangled, all concerned with the great matter of life and death. This is also the earnest concern of an old woman’s heart,
<lb n="0381a24" ed="J" />so extremely urgent. Yet the buddhas and bodhisattvas act without opposing the wishes of sentient beings, whereas this old and weary monk,
<lb n="0381a25" ed="J" />though sitting in laziness, also has this intention. But if one were to set out on the return road, with iron encircling mountains pressing from front and back,
<lb n="0381a26" ed="J" />and tigers, wolves, and lions on both sides, how would you advance then? If Zen practitioner Zhi can speak here,
<lb n="0381a27" ed="J" />and grasp the matter of going beyond, then take Dongshan’s three catties of hemp and weigh them up to the Thirty-three Heavens, and use Yunmen’s
<lb n="0381a28" ed="J" />dried shit-stick to pry open the ground until it splits in seven and eight directions.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0381a29" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Presented to Zen practitioner Deyun</cb:mulu><head>Presented to Zen practitioner Deyun</head>
<lb n="0381a30" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0381a3001">Deyun says: “Dwelling on the wondrous peak is just like trying to satisfy hunger with a painted cake.” Deyun does not dwell on the wondrous peak
<pb n="0381b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0381b" />
<lb n="0381b01" ed="J" />of the peak; it is also like running toward the sun while trying to flee its shadow. Both paths cut off are still not intimate; grasping the middle is still
<lb n="0381b02" ed="J" />a trap. Whether ancient or present, neither this nor that, neither paired nor single. Already in Yuzhang<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0381b0201" n="0381b0201" /><anchor xml:id="beg0381b0201" n="0381b0201" /><anchor xml:id="end0381b0201" />
<lb n="0381b03" ed="J" />under the prefecture, speaking of karmic conditions and peaceful dwelling, yet in Xuancheng, he snaps the rope blocking the road and visits
<lb n="0381b04" ed="J" />Chan masters from all directions. On Wu waters, an iron boat floats freely; over Yue mountains, the moon is not in the sky. At Tiantong, he randomly
<lb n="0381b05" ed="J" />swings his white staff. Under the Tung moon I add one word to you: when you return to the eighteen rapids of the Western River,
<lb n="0381b06" ed="J" />drink it all in one gulp until it is completely dry. Turn around and exhale a single phrase—then you will see a withered well give rise to waves.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0381b07" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to the physician Zou of Shangshui</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to the physician Zou of Shangshui</head>
<lb n="0381b08" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0381b0801">Pitiable is the human world—there is no one who is not ill. Master Zou, carefully reflect: your subtle diagnosis indeed reaches the truth,
<lb n="0381b09" ed="J" />cyperus is warming, coptis is cooling—each you take up is not wrong, and its use is appropriate. Yet even with this ability,
<lb n="0381b10" ed="J" />you still lack this one step. How about the patient who recovers without needing a donkey to carry medicine? Do you not see Vimalakirti,
<lb n="0381b11" ed="J" />the elder Vimalakirti, who made those around him circle and strike him; only Manjushri was slightly better, yet still inevitably ended up
<lb n="0381b12" ed="J" />buried in wild grass. And do you not see Xie Sanlang, who cleverly raised the “three illnesses” to mock the various schools, only to be pierced by others
<lb n="0381b13" ed="J" />so that he could not open his mouth, his full intent turning into shame and embarrassment.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0381b14" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to the scholar Shi Zhaishi</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to the scholar Shi Zhaishi</head>
<lb n="0381b15" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0381b1501">This sick monk originally has no tongue in his mouth and has never been able to babble or speak. Now I ask Master Shi of Liaoheng:
<lb n="0381b16" ed="J" />who is it that relies on to light incense and sweep the ground? If one day you find this person,
<lb n="0381b17" ed="J" />you will then escape the cave of birth and death. At that time, seize and defeat the old yellow-faced one—better yet, become a street thief who steals in broad daylight. Thief! Thief! Thirty
<lb n="0381b18" ed="J" />blows of the staff you must also receive.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0381b19" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Zen practitioner Wuxiang</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Zen practitioner Wuxiang</head>
<lb n="0381b20" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0381b2001">What is fragrance, and who is the one who awakens to it? If you clearly see through it, you still inevitably linger on the roadside crossing.
<lb n="0381b21" ed="J" />Therefore, with a single urgent thought one travels seeking teachers, going from Jiangxi to Hunan to inquire of spiritual friends; yet in the mouths of those teachers it is all watery talk
<lb n="0381b22" ed="J" />dripping and flowing—when spoken of too closely, it becomes hard to point out. Suddenly, when you break through the soles of your straw sandals, even the rubble at your feet is
<lb n="0381b23" ed="J" />all gold. Jianxi water becomes a single choking gulp; Iron Lion Peak roars like thunder. At that time, you roam freely
<lb n="0381b24" ed="J" />at ease in your nature, with nothing to rejoice or worry over, and no joy or sorrow to be worried about. Amid waters and forests, with grass remaining, in idle moments you sing
<lb n="0381b25" ed="J" />a little la-la-li.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0381b26" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to layman Wang Ruliang</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to layman Wang Ruliang</head>
<lb n="0381b27" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0381b2701">Lifting an iron ruyi as if it were thunder, how swift and direct is realization in that very moment? Here, in utter obscurity, there is nothing
<lb n="0381b28" ed="J" />known, and yet thorns still grow beneath your feet. When you investigate until you go beyond mind, intention, and consciousness, a wooden horse in the fire gives birth
<lb n="0381b29" ed="J" />to a foal. When study reaches the point where the paths of sage and ordinary are cut off, the mud ox under the whip even bleeds. Neither investigating, nor
<lb n="0381b30" ed="J" />studying—only then can a true man’s mind be vast and open. All dharmas are originally empty and at ease; how could one bind oneself without ropes
<pb n="0381c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0381c" />
<lb n="0381c01" ed="J" />and yet bind oneself? Stop binding yourself—leave the hole like a smoking rabbit wearing two horns.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0381c02" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Layman Wu Junxian presents a fan and requests instruction</cb:mulu><head>Layman Wu Junxian presents a fan and requests instruction</head>
<lb n="0381c03" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0381c0301">Not a single thread is hung—just a plain white silk; no brushstrokes added—yet it is a complete piece of colored pattern. If you understand it this way,
<lb n="0381c04" ed="J" />it is eighteen thousand miles. If you do not understand it this way, you lose your eyes. Do you not see when Layman Pang went to see Mazu,
<lb n="0381c05" ed="J" />he swallowed the West River in one gulp, poured all his wealth into the Xiang Sea, and under a broken bamboo strainer
<lb n="0381c06" ed="J" />made a living in a different way. From then on his great name overwhelmed the world, his lofty spirit not easily expressed. If Master Wu
<lb n="0381c07" ed="J" />is willing to follow such fragrant traces, even recognizing a gourd as an imperial vessel, he must directly tread down the summit of Vairocana
<lb n="0381c08" ed="J" />before he can be called an extraordinary man.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0381c09" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Attendant Zheng Yinguo requests instruction</cb:mulu><head>Attendant Zheng Yinguo requests instruction</head>
<lb n="0381c10" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0381c1001">Attendant Zheng Yinguo joins his palms and asks for instruction. What could this sick and decayed monk possibly say? Anything said would not be reliable.
<lb n="0381c11" ed="J" />In the past, the old master Niaoke was not free from falling into a snare—he picked up a piece of cotton fluff and blew it, and the attendant monk immediately awakened.
<lb n="0381c12" ed="J" />Now those who study the Way must not follow words and phrases. Simply look at the colors before your eyes: a pine broom sweeping the green of the mountain,
<lb n="0381c13" ed="J" />And again, hearing the sounds by the ear, the wind in the stream reveals a subtle meaning. Cutting off the six senses and consciousness, one does not abide in either emptiness or existence.
<lb n="0381c14" ed="J" />When there is sound, sound is heard of itself; when there is form, form is not avoided. Like an arrow once it leaves the bowstring, it goes straight with no turning back.
<lb n="0381c15" ed="J" />In the four daily postures, in every blink of an eye, it is good to take up and understand. Before your father and mother were born, where do you establish your body?
<lb n="0381c16" ed="J" />When you suddenly run into it, everywhere is not yourself. A iron snake drills into a diamond ring, a heron kicks<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0381c1601" n="0381c1601" /><anchor xml:id="beg0381c1601" n="0381c1601" /><anchor xml:id="end0381c1601" />
<lb n="0381c17" ed="J" />and topples Mount Sumeru into pieces.</p></cb:div></cb:div>
<lb n="0381c18" ed="J" />
<lb n="0381c19" ed="J" />
<lb n="0381c20" ed="J" />
<cb:juan n="1" fun="close"><cb:jhead>Recorded sayings of Chan Master Yong of Yuanhu, resident of Puming Chan Monastery in Jianning Prefecture, Fujian, end of fascicle one</cb:jhead></cb:juan>
<milestone n="2" unit="juan" />
<pb n="0382a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0382a" />
<lb n="0382a01" ed="J" />
<cb:mulu n="2" type="卷"></cb:mulu><cb:juan n="2" fun="open"><cb:jhead>Recorded sayings of Chan Master Yong of Yuanhu, resident of Puming Chan Monastery in Puming Chan Monastery in Jianning Prefecture, Fujian, fascicle two</cb:jhead></cb:juan>
<lb n="0382a02" ed="J" />
<byline cb:type="editor">Compiled by Dharma heirs and disciples Wujin, Wuyuan, and others</byline>
<lb n="0382a03" ed="J" />
<byline cb:type="other">Reprinted by Dharma-grandson Zhenzhi of Tui’an at Changshui</byline>
<lb n="0382a04" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Letters</cb:mulu><head>Letters</head>
<lb n="0382a05" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Letter to Layman Jiang Hairuo</cb:mulu><head>Letter to Layman Jiang Hairuo</head>
<lb n="0382a06" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0382a0601">In spring, I was honored by your gracious visit and the generous gift of fertile fields, which I feel again and again both grateful and ashamed for. Only this old
<lb n="0382a07" ed="J" />layman, whose virtue is abundant and whose body is well-nourished, grows stronger with age; he may be called one in a wealthy family who is not moved by wealth,
<lb n="0382a08" ed="J" />and who naturally preserves his spirit in the inner teachings and draws near those beyond the world. The scriptures say: “A bodhisattva, by past
<lb n="0382a09" ed="J" />reliance on the power of prajna, is not turned by sound and form.” In the six perfections and the four immeasurables,
<lb n="0382a10" ed="J" />every thought urges progress, every thought brings completion; one who never forgets even for a moment must surely not be from just one or two
<lb n="0382a11" ed="J" />lifetimes of cultivation. I now hear that a new Buddha hall is being built behind your residence, and that you are strict in pure practice, which greatly
<lb n="0382a12" ed="J" />satisfies my humble intention. The teaching also says: “When the heavenly drum suddenly sounds of itself, it tells the sons of heaven: ‘All dharmas
<lb n="0382a13" ed="J" />are suffering and empty, without any true reality; do not crave the five desires for a moment’s pleasure.’ One should strive for the fruit of the Way, and
<lb n="0382a14" ed="J" />realize the original nature.” But tell me, how is the fruit of the Way to be sought? How is the original nature to be realized? Yet since the elder layman
<lb n="0382a15" ed="J" />reveres the Three Jewels and fully performs Buddhist works, he may also once attend to the matter of the original nature. As for this original
<lb n="0382a16" ed="J" />nature, once it is understood, then in the streets and crossroads, whether tea songs or wine calls, nothing is not one’s own
<lb n="0382a17" ed="J" />original affair. At that time, even holding children and playing with grandchildren will be nothing but Buddhist activity, and even this original
<lb n="0382a18" ed="J" />If one seeks blessings through principle, then blessings are ever exalted; if one prays for longevity, then longevity is ever enduring, adorning the Dharma realm without
<lb n="0382a19" ed="J" />the accomplishment of the original matter.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0382a20" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply to Layman Zhu Qiliang</cb:mulu><head>Reply to Layman Zhu Qiliang</head>
<lb n="0382a21" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0382a2101">On receiving and reading your letter, I saw in detail your full account and sincere disclosure; truly it is a very earnest mind for the Way
<lb n="0382a22" ed="J" />The intention is extremely earnest. It is only that one has not yet been able to transcend and thoroughly integrate it. As for your discussion of deluded conditioned emotional thoughts,
<lb n="0382a23" ed="J" />they are like tea and meals in the house; how could they be removed or cut off? Did not the Buddha say: Mind, Buddha, and
<lb n="0382a24" ed="J" />sentient beings—these three are without difference. Yet sentient beings, through beginningless habituation, cannot realize entry; it is not the Buddha's
<lb n="0382a25" ed="J" />fault. It is all because they lack resolute intent; birth and death are not taken urgently, and practice is not vigorous, thus they willingly
<lb n="0382a26" ed="J" />drift in saṃsāra. For those on your side, this great matter must be believed to the utmost. Having believed it to the utmost,
<lb n="0382a27" ed="J" />how could one still willingly drift? You also say: If thoughts of body and family are light, the matter of birth and death is great. If so,
<lb n="0382a28" ed="J" />since you know the matter of birth and death is great, there is nowhere that is not a great matter; why then must one concentrate the spirit in silent sitting,
<lb n="0382a29" ed="J" />only then consider it attainment? Moreover, do you not know that in the past there were Wang Pang and Wujin Danian
<lb n="0382a30" ed="J" />and many such figures recorded in the Transmission of the Lamp—those fellows without any fixed footing—yet do you not know that today there are also lay practitioners
<pb n="0382b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0382b" />
<lb n="0382b01" ed="J" />as well? In this matter there is no distinction between this and that. If one is truly a man of spirit, raising the eyebrows, sharing life with life and death with
<lb n="0382b02" ed="J" />death, going straight forward without hesitation, only then is there a slight correspondence. As for Buddha-dharma and worldly dharma, originally there is no
<lb n="0382b03" ed="J" />difference between the two; how could they obstruct each other? You also say, If there are no affairs for several months one investigates; if there are affairs one abandons it. Since
<lb n="0382b04" ed="J" />the great matter is in oneself, how could it be taken away? You also wish this poor monk to point out a skillful means. Indeed there is
<lb n="0382b05" ed="J" />This expedient is neither mind, nor Buddha, nor things—ultimately what is it? At this
<lb n="0382b06" ed="J" />A single bite breaks it; at that moment there is indescribable joy! Even so, it is precisely fitting to receive the blow. Why
<lb n="0382b07" ed="J" />Why? Under the gate of Puming, one does not travel in vain.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0382b08" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">To Huang Lianxian, Censor of Anzhai</cb:mulu><head>To Huang Lianxian, Censor of Anzhai</head>
<lb n="0382b09" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0382b0901">Since meeting at the start of summer, it is now deep autumn without noticing. How swiftly time flows! I privately rejoice that the old
<lb n="0382b10" ed="J" />layman, in times of heat and vexation, does not suffer with the world, but enters the mountains and forests alone to savor the secluded state,
<lb n="0382b11" ed="J" />but I do not know whether the original investigation has gained a flash of insight. Yesterday I heard of your journey to Shuangjing and very much wished to meet,
<lb n="0382b12" ed="J" />but I am again ill and have not had time to meet immediately.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0382b13" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">To Venerable Miyun Wu</cb:mulu><head>To Venerable Miyun Wu</head>
<lb n="0382b14" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0382b1401">Since parting from your seat, nearly ten years have counted on my fingers. Now that Venerable has reached his seventieth year, alas my humble body has often
<lb n="0382b15" ed="J" />been in illness; how could I endure travel? Yet morning and evening my thoughts turn to you, recalling Venerable's vast and expansive Dharma path, opening
<lb n="0382b16" ed="J" />and instructing humans and devas. If there is even one person who does not accept transformation, ultimately how should he be taken in? Respectfully
<lb n="0382b17" ed="J" />I send this as a proxy greeting, offering a modest birthday gift to convey my intention.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0382b18" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">To Xu Chunyuan (Zhenhou)</cb:mulu><head>To Xu Chunyuan (Zhenhou)</head>
<lb n="0382b19" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0382b1901">At the meal at the monastery, I received the layman’s mention of the causal conditions of Duanfeng and Dule; it depends solely on one's own discernment, earnestly<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0382b1901" n="0382b1901" /><anchor xml:id="beg0382b1901" n="0382b1901" /><anchor xml:id="end0382b1901" />
<lb n="0382b20" ed="J" />do not seek approval from others’ mouths. This sick monk, in response to the layman's question, spoke deliriously for a moment,
<lb n="0382b21" ed="J" />If speaking from the gate of the Zen lineage, even thirty blows cannot be compared as one is better than another. Yet in this gate,
<lb n="0382b22" ed="J" />there have never been words, nor any dharma to give to people. The ancients said: "If there were an actual dharma to give people, even water
<lb n="0382b23" ed="J" />could not dissolve it." How could this be deceiving people? Earnestly, earnestly!</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0382b24" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">To Layman Zhu Quichen</cb:mulu><head>To Layman Zhu Quichen</head>
<lb n="0382b25" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0382b2501">Since parting, my words have become stiff and cannot flow from the mouth; yet we come and go on both sides, not for a short time, and I also deeply
<lb n="0382b26" ed="J" />I know you have long been attentive to this path, so why are you not free and unburdened, as a truly outstanding man should be? Recently
<lb n="0382b27" ed="J" />has there been any progress worth looking at with new eyes? Just as Layman Pang asked Master Ma: "What kind of person is one who does not accompany the ten thousand dharmas
<lb n="0382b28" ed="J" />as companions?" The answer was: "Wait until you can gulp down the waters of West River in one mouthful, then I will tell
<lb n="0382b29" ed="J" />you." Look! Where is this fellow's great mouth? Why not gain a sudden insight here
<lb n="0382b30" ed="J" />and become a man of no affairs? Would that not be the greatest joy of your life? Also, as Zhaozhou said: "All of you
<pb n="0382c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0382c" />
<lb n="0382c01" ed="J" />are used by the twelve hours, while this old monk uses the twelve hours." Now see on what principle
<lb n="0382c02" ed="J" />he speaks such words. It is simply: when hungry, eat; when cold, add clothes; when guests come, respond
<lb n="0382c03" ed="J" />in conversation; when guests leave, close the door and sleep soundly. This is not a second person apart from the defilements, nor is it falling into emptiness
<lb n="0382c04" ed="J" />and departing. If you can glimpse a bit of this, you can also make use of it according to conditions. But if you take it further upward and grasp it, it is precisely fitting
<lb n="0382c05" ed="J" />to receive the blow.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0382c06" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply to Huang Xiaolian of Sumen (Dharma name Wudi)</cb:mulu><head>Reply to Huang Xiaolian of Sumen<note place="inline">法名悟第</note></head>
<lb n="0382c07" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0382c0701">I have received your letter and the songs written on the fan; I read them without putting them down. Wherever there is empty praise, I cannot help but feel
<lb n="0382c08" ed="J" />ashamed. You ask about the three phrases of mind-seal, but I do not know what you call a seal of mind.
<lb n="0382c09" ed="J" />What do you call mind itself? You must not hide your roots in stone or jade. Also, in your song, the phrases about body
<lb n="0382c10" ed="J" />and mind both being liberated, and surpassing the enlightenment of a single night—on your side, can you truly be liberated
<lb n="0382c11" ed="J" />or not? Can you truly attain the awakening of one night or not? Let liberation aside—what is it that is awakened
<lb n="0382c12" ed="J" />in the end? If there is indeed some realization, quickly send word and I will rejoice for you.
<lb n="0382c13" ed="J" />How about it?</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0382c14" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply to Layman Huang Qingbo</cb:mulu><head>Reply to Layman Huang Qingbo</head>
<lb n="0382c15" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0382c1501">I have read your letter and learned that your illness has flared up again. I have long reflected on your devoted attention to this matter over many years,
<lb n="0382c16" ed="J" />and now, can you tell where your original life-moment truly rests? I see your faculties are extraordinary; however
<lb n="0382c17" ed="J" />consider how Nanyue Rang once studied under the Sixth Patriarch. The Patriarch asked: "What thing is this that has thus come?" Rang said: "To say it is a thing
<lb n="0382c18" ed="J" />already misses the mark." The Patriarch said: "Is cultivation and realization still necessary?" Rang said: "Cultivation and realization are not nonexistent, but defilement
<lb n="0382c19" ed="J" />"If defilement is not present, it is also not attainable." I hope you can break through this point; then you may freely eat when hungry and drink when thirsty, in cold or heat,
<lb n="0382c20" ed="J" />whether in warmth or coolness. Seeing forms and hearing sounds, respond in the moment; throughout the twenty-four hours and in all four postures, nothing is not manifested
<lb n="0382c21" ed="J" />as complete. Whatever is taken up is nothing other than it; do not give rise to doubt in its use. Earnest admonition!</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0382c22" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply to Xu Xiaolian of Luyi</cb:mulu><head>Reply to Xu Xiaolian of Luyi</head>
<lb n="0382c23" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0382c2301">Living in remote mountains, I am honored to receive your esteemed letter. I respectfully read it, and that you wish me to give instruction is beyond
<lb n="0382c24" ed="J" />shame. Yet I dare not bury your sincere intent, and cannot help but respond based on your letter,
<lb n="0382c25" ed="J" />pointing out a few things. You say the dusty world is vexing and worthy of rejection. In my view, this is precisely the most
<lb n="0382c26" ed="J" />crucial initial practice. In the midst of vexation, if you set one eye upon it—who is it that is in the dust
<lb n="0382c27" ed="J" />and toil? Who is it that rejects it? If you suddenly see through it, in daily life you naturally gain mastery without
<lb n="0382c28" ed="J" />thinking of it as defilement, and without thinking of it as something to reject.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0382c29" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply to Layman Du Huayu</cb:mulu><head>Reply to Layman Du Huayu</head>
<lb n="0382c30" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0382c3001">I carefully read your verses and see that this monk has broad learning and good understanding. If he can make his speech
<pb n="0383a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0383a" />
<lb n="0383a01" ed="J" />accord with conduct, with practice and understanding unified, and undergo much forging and tempering with steady practice, then becoming Buddha or ancestor is not
<lb n="0383a02" ed="J" />something from outside; it is originally one's own affair and therefore not difficult. In time, nurturing the sacred embryo and reaching
<lb n="0383a03" ed="J" />profound virtue, there will naturally be the impartial judgment of dragons and devas, leading to the jeweled lotus throne, preaching the Dharma and benefiting beings, even
<lb n="0383a04" ed="J" />criticizing Buddhas and scolding patriarchs, all depending on the time and conditions. Yet nowadays those who study the Way, having learned a little
<lb n="0383a05" ed="J" />imitation language and patched together a few crude lines of writing, immediately claim enlightenment. When
<lb n="0383a06" ed="J" />everywhere deceiving others, they do not fear karmic retribution; they only want verbal excitement. Do not think that having learning
<lb n="0383a07" ed="J" />and intellectual understanding will suffice for one's life. I only fear that one day, when brought before Yama, judgment will follow one's karma and
<lb n="0383a08" ed="J" />offenses, where then is the pardon document? At that time, whom could one possibly rely on for rescue? Thus the ancient worthies
<lb n="0383a09" ed="J" />said: "In our school, it is hard to attain its subtlety; one must apply the mind with utmost care." They also said: "An eighty-year-old elder entering
<lb n="0383a10" ed="J" />the examination hall—this is truly not child's play." I understand you wish to test the truth or falsity of my worn-out verses,
<lb n="0383a11" ed="J" />and I have unintentionally produced such tangled explanations. I hope you will apply yourself and penetrate your original nature<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0383a1101" n="0383a1101" /><anchor xml:id="beg0383a1101" n="0383a1101" /><anchor xml:id="end0383a1101" />
<lb n="0383a12" ed="J" />When matters come before your eyes at that time, there is no need to ask others; you will know true and false for yourself.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0383a13" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply to Layman Wu Junxian</cb:mulu><head>Reply to Layman Wu Junxian</head>
<lb n="0383a14" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0383a1401">Your letter asks how one could leave this shell-and-leaking vessel in order to cultivate the supreme vehicle Dharma. Why such words
<lb n="0383a15" ed="J" />of misunderstanding? But right now, who is it that carries this shell-and-leaking vessel? And who is it that wants to leave it?
<lb n="0383a16" ed="J" />Who is it? And what is this shell-and-leaking vessel? If you see through this, you will smile in ease. Even so,
<lb n="0383a17" ed="J" />it is not yet permitted that you have seen through it. Why? If you try to force such insight, it only adds another layer of affliction.
<lb n="0383a18" ed="J" />Respectfully admonished.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0383a19" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">To Chan Master Liangxu</cb:mulu><head>To Chan Master Liangxu</head>
<lb n="0383a20" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0383a2001">Though we share the same wind and moon, our streams and mountains differ. Separated in two places, it is not without stirring of thought. I often recall the senior monk,
<lb n="0383a21" ed="J" />whose innate capacity is excellent, and who in this gate has applied effort and moved forward; compared with monks of this degenerate age, he is truly like clouds
<lb n="0383a22" ed="J" />and mud. Yet one should not laugh at those who run fifty steps after running a hundred; one should press forward directly with courage
<lb n="0383a23" ed="J" />and vigor, becoming a banner of diligence and a model for later generations—this is what this worn-out monk hopes for.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0383a24" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">To Hualin</cb:mulu><head>To Hualin</head>
<lb n="0383a25" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0383a2501">Since parting, nearly a week has passed in haste. I trust you have completed your former vow of copying with blood, and should now open a simple<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0383a2501" n="0383a2501" /><anchor xml:id="beg0383a2501" n="0383a2501" /><anchor xml:id="end0383a2501" />
<lb n="0383a26" ed="J" />vegetarian practice and nurture your physical body to good health, and take up your own great task—throughout the twenty-four hours<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0383a2601" n="0383a2601" /><anchor xml:id="beg0383a2601" n="0383a2601" /><anchor xml:id="end0383a2601" />
<lb n="0383a27" ed="J" />carefully investigate it: where is it that is not called Hualin? Do not always
<lb n="0383a28" ed="J" />sit on the throne of the Dharma King acting out false practices and posing, performing great repentance rites and reciting the Lotus Sutra, attending today
<lb n="0383a29" ed="J" />at the Li household and tomorrow going to the Zhang household, unaware that your whole body is trapped in a ten-thousand-ren deep well,<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0383a2901" n="0383a2901" /><anchor xml:id="beg0383a2901" n="0383a2901" /><anchor xml:id="end0383a2901" />
<lb n="0383a30" ed="J" />where even your two ears can hardly hold fast. Reflect, reflect. These words of this sick and decayed monk today,
<pb n="0383b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0383b" />
<lb n="0383b01" ed="J" />are surely unpleasant and hard to hear; yet on another day before Yama, when you receive iron blows,
<lb n="0383b02" ed="J" />if you then recall my words, it will be too late for regret. Take them deeply to heart; do not treat them as wind in the treetops. Earnest admonition.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0383b03" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Farewell Petition for the Guanyin Hall at Jing Mountain, Second Request</cb:mulu><head>Farewell Petition: Second Request for the Guanyin Hall at Jing Mountain</head>
<lb n="0383b04" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0383b0401">The opening of teaching and transformation has no ultimate origin apart from causes; before the mountain of Right Awakening, I cannot help but reveal my own shortcomings and clumsy remnants,
<lb n="0383b05" ed="J" />like leftover skill spit out by the Nairanjana River. I itch to display my petty wares; occasionally I pick up a flower and hastily speak of a separate transmission of the mind seal,
<lb n="0383b06" ed="J" />then suddenly break into laughter and speak of entrusting the golden robe. Mutual exposition and transmission is a heavy burden,
<lb n="0383b07" ed="J" />handed back and forth—how could this be a minor connection? I deeply consider my own dullness; what good affinity could I have? Before Five Elders Peak I once joined
<lb n="0383b08" ed="J" />a gathering, not without strange encounters; beneath the Great Compassion Pavilion I long kept my head down, ashamed of my dim confusion. Even now I remain delayed,
<lb n="0383b09" ed="J" />like a lame turtle always ashamed; like the useless wood of former years, I have merely followed after the ancestral halls. Moreover, my past faults are like an ocean, and my sick bones
<lb n="0383b10" ed="J" />are like firewood. Reflecting deeply, I have not even an awl of achievement in the Way—how could I contribute anything to the Dharma gate? I can only hide my form in a humble village corner,
<lb n="0383b11" ed="J" />and barely prolong these remaining years. Humbly receiving Chan Master Miaoxuan and the respected elders of Heshan, who<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0383b1101" n="0383b1101" /><anchor xml:id="beg0383b1101" n="0383b1101" /><anchor xml:id="end0383b1101" />
<lb n="0383b12" ed="J" />do not abandon my vulgarity and again send their honored letters, I open and reverently read them, as if holding the bright moon in my palm, and repeatedly reviewing the text
<lb n="0383b13" ed="J" />only makes my thatched hut gain undeserved radiance. As for the praise of being a pillar and banner, it exceeds mere encouragement; sweet nectar and compassionate
<lb n="0383b14" ed="J" />rain—how mistaken such praise is. And to further bestow various gifts and provisions only makes me increasingly blush with shame. I recall
<lb n="0383b15" ed="J" />the legacy of the former master, faintly heard as if from wall and broth; yet with regard to the virtue and presence of the elder teachers, I have scarcely had the fortune to sit face to face, almost
<lb n="0383b16" ed="J" />wishing to climb to the summit to seek instruction, but my staff is frail and I am unable to travel; thus I have repeatedly been honored with invitations yet cannot immediately
<lb n="0383b17" ed="J" />come near to receive your teaching, and now respectfully offer these few lines in reply. I humbly wish your noble spirit be broad and magnanimous, forgiving this
<lb n="0383b18" ed="J" />unworthy one; may your bright wisdom be vast and clear, and may you kindly accept this small intention. Having failed to comply with your request, I earnestly ask for compassionate understanding.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0383b19" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Farewell Petition to the Dharma Protectors of Puming in Jiaxing</cb:mulu><head>Farewell Petition to the Dharma Protectors of Puming in Jiaxing</head>
<lb n="0383b20" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0383b2001">I have rashly entered the Buddhist institution and vainly received the support of donors; I am ashamed to have participated in the ancestral assembly for many years, yet I truly lack even a single
<lb n="0383b21" ed="J" />basket of merit. I certainly have no sharp eyes like an eagle or vulture; my mind is as cold as ice; I am accustomed to hiding among deer and boars, and
<lb n="0383b22" ed="J" />due to illness only a frame of firewood-like bones remains. I guard a withered meditation practice, bringing no benefit to the Dharma gate and only increasing faults and offenses. How could I repay such kindness?
<lb n="0383b23" ed="J" />Now, receiving the support of many officials and scholars, without having carefully reflected, I am suddenly entrusted with a heavy responsibility,
<lb n="0383b24" ed="J" />with empty praise of my writings, hoping that this sick monk would accept, along with offerings of gifts, only making the Paulownia Moon feel ashamed. Moreover
<lb n="0383b25" ed="J" />this ancient monastery of Puming, though its merit does not lie in grandeur, still answers the shared wishes of the city of He; how could the matter depend
<lb n="0383b26" ed="J" />on one so insignificant as I? If this matter were spread abroad, it would make people everywhere laugh. As I struggle in a quiet room, it is not without some strange
<lb n="0383b27" ed="J" />even if I seem to be scolding the mountain spirits. I dare to reveal my sincere heart and respectfully take leave of the donors. These words may be absurd, but the Three Jewels can themselves bear witness
<lb n="0383b28" ed="J" />and verify them; my intent is truly sincere, and all the sages can clearly attest to it. Since we are mutually acquainted, I humbly ask for your understanding.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0383b29" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply to Governor Zhu of Lianyue</cb:mulu><head>Reply to Governor Zhu of Lianyue</head>
<lb n="0383b30" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0383b3001">This poor monk’s foundation in the Way is not firm, and his learning and understanding are especially crude. I have improperly taken a place among the monastic ranks, merely bringing shame upon the Dharma teaching. Humbly considering
<pb n="0383c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0383c" />
<lb n="0383c01" ed="J" />that the layman does not forget the legacy spoken on Vulture Peak, and as a descendant of Ziyang he gladly serves as a pillar of this precious land,
<lb n="0383c02" ed="J" />becoming a strong protector of the region and a bright banner in literary circles. As for me, what sort of person am I, that I should dare receive such remembrance and distant
<lb n="0383c03" ed="J" />precious letters illuminating even this remote mountain? I respectfully receive and read them, but the praise is far beyond my worth, and this poor monk cannot but
<lb n="0383c04" ed="J" />be overcome with shame and fear. However, when Master Taoshan travels and expounds the Dharma in Fujian, it is widely known that those beneath his teaching platform are well ripened for transformation; outwardly
<lb n="0383c05" ed="J" />he protects and skillfully applies his teaching, making the Dharma gate as secure as golden ramparts and a pillar of the nation; wherever he goes, it is entirely appropriate. In former times
<lb n="0383c06" ed="J" />I once wandered at ease with my staff and paused for rest, admiring the benevolence of Zhicheng and delighting in its mountains and waters,
<lb n="0383c07" ed="J" />and I considered requesting a thatched roof to shelter my head, merely to prolong my remaining idle and sickly days. How could I dare to defile such a famed and blessed place
<lb n="0383c08" ed="J" />by making it my long-term dwelling like a hanging gourd? I have since heard that this temple, though not grand, is still a gathering place for the community,
<lb n="0383c09" ed="J" />and how could a decayed and useless person like me presume to occupy such a renowned monastery? If I firmly refuse, I fear it would go against your honorable command,
<lb n="0383c10" ed="J" />especially at this time when sacred images suffer hardship and temple halls are in disrepair. Since lay supporters are kindly establishing fields of merit,
<lb n="0383c11" ed="J" />how could this poor monk remain coldly indifferent? I will temporarily accept and hang my hat there for a time, awaiting later worthies to further the teaching. Humbly
<lb n="0383c12" ed="J" />I pray for your noble illumination.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0383c13" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply to the Gentry</cb:mulu><head>Reply to the Gentry</head>
<lb n="0383c14" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0383c1401">This poor monk has mistakenly donned the monastic robe; he is nothing but ashes soaked through by rain. I have wrongly entered the forest of monks, and in the end remain a decayed
<lb n="0383c15" ed="J" />useless tree, bringing shame upon the descendants of Kapilavastu and staining the ancestral halls of Jishang. Examining myself and touching my heart,<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0383c1501" n="0383c1501" /><anchor xml:id="beg0383c1501" n="0383c1501" /><anchor xml:id="end0383c1501" />
<lb n="0383c16" ed="J" />I am fearful day and night. Humbly considering that you laymen are well versed in the Dharma garden and are all trusted donors; at Ehu, the staff
<lb n="0383c17" ed="J" />flies, receiving the initial teaching of entering the Way; when Master Shouchang arrives, one gains excellent conditions for further progress. At Bolao, the golden
<lb n="0383c18" ed="J" />needle is applied; at Jiamì and Tiantong, iron rods are mercilessly used; at Taoshan’s assembly, I have personally received instruction for many years; at Jianyitang
<lb n="0383c19" ed="J" />I am daily and nightly admonished and guided. Lotus Peak is auspicious and beautiful, celestial flowers drift with fragrance; such sacred places naturally produce many outstanding people
<lb n="0383c20" ed="J" />Indeed. How could this be unrelated to the long-circulating influence of the Zen tradition, yet remain untouched by its sweeping breeze? Yet now I have been honored with your distant and excellent letter,
<lb n="0383c21" ed="J" />I respectfully read its ornate language, but such excessive praise leaves me overwhelmed with shame. In former years, this poor monk, afflicted with illness,
<lb n="0383c22" ed="J" />withdrew into seclusion with staff and alms bowl in hand; I was unable to explore the blue waters and crimson mountains, only intending to beg for a thatched roof over my head. How could I
<lb n="0383c23" ed="J" />claim to have followed the noble traces of streamside vegetable gatherers and hemp weavers, or to imitate the pure style of those who cook oranges and simmer taro? How could there be
<lb n="0383c24" ed="J" />any subtle intention of benefiting or transforming beings within this? I later heard that the Eastern Peak monastery is solemn and
<lb n="0383c25" ed="J" />a splendid site; now to entrust it to a useless person like myself—how could only the mountain spirits object? I fear even the heavenly dragons would not
<lb n="0383c26" ed="J" />protect and bless it. Therefore I cannot easily shoulder this responsibility; it is like testing boiling water. Yet I also pity the desolate monastery,
<lb n="0383c27" ed="J" />where the golden images are peeling and decaying, and already there has been the invitation of Anāthapiṇḍika and the dedication of Jeta’s grove. If this poor monk<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0383c2701" n="0383c2701" /><anchor xml:id="beg0383c2701" n="0383c2701" /><anchor xml:id="end0383c2701" />
<lb n="0383c28" ed="J" />does not manage this matter, I fear deeply betraying the great intentions of the donors. Otherwise, one may have to go along with the situation as it is,
<lb n="0383c29" ed="J" />waiting for benevolence in the present and cultivating it in the future. I have merely expressed these rough words to respectfully reply to your intention,
<lb n="0383c30" ed="J" />and cannot elaborate further.</p></cb:div></cb:div>
<pb n="0384a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0384a" />
<lb n="0384a01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Gāthās and Verses</cb:mulu><head>Gāthās and Verses</head>
<lb n="0384a02" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to the Huayan Lecture Master</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to the Huayan Lecture Master</head>
<lb n="0384a03" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384a0301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">It is idle talk to say everyone has the great scripture; that great scripture was once said to be in a single mote of dust. Buried and unrecognized, who would think the lonely
<lb n="0384a04" ed="J" />one could reveal it—yet only one beyond measure can open it up. The freely roaming elephant king often looks back and pauses; the fierce and majestic lion
<lb n="0384a05" ed="J" />may roar in vain; within this there is meaning difficult to analyze—when the pillar blooms, its colors are renewed.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384a06" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Flower Treasury World (during the plum rain season)</cb:mulu><head>Flower Treasury World<note place="inline">時值梅雨</note></head>
<lb n="0384a07" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384a0701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Dense rain and thick mist blur presence and absence; villages upon villages are all indistinct—how many worlds as numerous as the Ganges sands could there be,
<lb n="0384a08" ed="J" />all together forming the present Flower Treasury realm before the eyes.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384a09" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Layman Huang Qingbo in Illness</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Layman Huang Qingbo in Illness</head>
<lb n="0384a10" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384a1001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Sickness and suffering are things no one can avoid—who can escape their gradual wearing away? You must urgently fix your gaze on the source
<lb n="0384a11" ed="J" />of it—what then are sickness and the one who is sick?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384a12" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Two Poems on a Visit from Xie Dianbang of the Imperial Court Office</cb:mulu><head>Two Poems on a Visit from Xie Dianbang of the Imperial Court Office</head>
<lb n="0384a13" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384a1301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">In front of the hermitage, the path grass is over a zhang deep; how can your lofty carriage illuminate this desolate grove? When we meet, I am unable to say even a single word,
<lb n="0384a14" ed="J" />only hearing mountain birds sing their fine notes.</l></lg>
<lb n="0384a15" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384a1501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">This mountain wilderness was never the realm of Foyin; I do not take the four elements as a meditation seat. It is pitiful to think of Dongpo in former days,
<lb n="0384a16" ed="J" />the old scholar who lost his jade belt and treasured it away with fondness.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384a17" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reflections on the Beginning of Autumn</cb:mulu><head>Reflections on the Beginning of Autumn</head>
<lb n="0384a18" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384a1801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">There is a practitioner who grieves the early autumn; the passing years have become my enemy as well. In the mirror my reflection appears, my appearance much
<lb n="0384a19" ed="J" />changed; leaning on a bamboo staff I can barely walk. The bright moon shines on people, soothing the ears; the west wind strikes the face, covering
<lb n="0384a20" ed="J" />dim eyes. Once again heaven and earth fade away—what further means is there now to bring this to rest?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384a21" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Huang Xiaolian of Sumen</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Huang Xiaolian of Sumen</head>
<lb n="0384a22" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384a2201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Fame and success are easily spat aside; with a pure heart one turns to the Buddha and wanders far away. Joyfully from the first stage one opens the heart,
<lb n="0384a23" ed="J" />embracing it, causing the green mountains to seem to smile. There is a goose in the jar that must be let out properly; without harmony at one’s fingertips, it is vain
<lb n="0384a24" ed="J" />to pluck empty sounds. If you grasp the meaning before words arise, even draining the West River in one gulp would still be difficult.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384a25" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Dai Jiulin, Xiaolian</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Dai Jiulin, Xiaolian</head>
<lb n="0384a26" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384a2601" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Everywhere green mountains are piled with white clouds; do not hide them away in your sack or blanket. In the furnace of red flames, if you can grasp the
<lb n="0384a27" ed="J" />moon, then in the clusters of grapes your two eyes will open.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384a28" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Yong Shutong, Xiaolian</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Yong Shutong, Xiaolian</head>
<lb n="0384a29" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384a2901" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Frost intoxicates the red trees and myriad mountain flowers; with a single brushstroke it is painted into brocade-like clouds of glow. If you know the way of coming,
<lb n="0384a30" ed="J" />and the place of return, what need is there for Puming to chatter on and on?</l></lg></cb:div>
<pb n="0384b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0384b" />
<lb n="0384b01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Xu Xiaolian of Luyi</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Xu Xiaolian of Luyi</head>
<lb n="0384b02" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384b0201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Vibrantly alive and brightly luminous, yet the moment you step forward you are already in a maze; if you come asking about this matter,
<lb n="0384b03" ed="J" />even Great and Small Stonehead can speak of it intimately.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384b04" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Wei Xiaolian of Kanghou</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Wei Xiaolian of Kanghou</head>
<lb n="0384b05" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384b0501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Cold winds toss and disorder the monastic robe; beside the brazier, formal propriety is neglected. If you can understand it, then in a snap of the fingers when we meet,<g ref="#CB05958" />
<lb n="0384b06" ed="J" />you will grasp the intent—like a mud ox giving birth beneath the sea.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384b07" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Lin Xiaolian of Yanpo</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Lin Xiaolian of Yanpo</head>
<lb n="0384b08" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384b0801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">At Puming there is truly not a single word; if you try to come and ask, it is not intimate either. In mountain dwellings everywhere there is autumn
<lb n="0384b09" ed="J" />scenery; only the one concerned may see it truly.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384b10" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Zhang Xiaolian of Tianxian</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Zhang Xiaolian of Tianxian</head>
<lb n="0384b11" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384b1101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">At Puming there is a path and nothing is concealed; even the finest hair of the great cosmos is taken into account. Red trees across myriad mountains are intoxicated with frost,
<lb n="0384b12" ed="J" />their colors—before the kalpas began, if you had eyes, you would do well to observe.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384b13" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Zhu Xiaolian of Lianyue</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Zhu Xiaolian of Lianyue</head>
<lb n="0384b14" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384b1401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">It is neither mind, Buddha, nor things; with a single rub the clay figure reveals its bones. At a glance you already know you have been mistaken,<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0384b1401" n="0384b1401" /><anchor xml:id="beg0384b1401" n="0384b1401" /><anchor xml:id="end0384b1401" />
<lb n="0384b15" ed="J" />so how could you still go on squeezing juice from a foreign flatbread?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384b16" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Xiaolian of Wohouqiu</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Xiaolian of Wohouqiu</head>
<lb n="0384b17" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384b1701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">In the quiet hills, birds play in the clear clouds of dawn; at the tips of myriad grasses lies the lavish intent of the Patriarchs. Even when form and sound are clearly present,
<lb n="0384b18" ed="J" />if you try to raise a question, it is as distant as the edge of the sky.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384b19" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Xie Dianbang of the Imperial Court Office</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Xie Dianbang of the Imperial Court Office</head>
<lb n="0384b20" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384b2001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">A single ancient road is straight as a drawn string, yet you must know that even in straightness there is bending. Through level and uneven places alike one has traveled extensively;
<lb n="0384b21" ed="J" />it is no harm to pass again through the Puming checkpoint.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384b22" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Ye Xiaolian of Zhongzi</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Ye Xiaolian of Zhongzi</head>
<lb n="0384b23" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384b2301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Each frost-covered tree is like ink filled with cinnabar; all around, autumn clouds cannot be painted. Travelers on the road all have dim eyes,
<lb n="0384b24" ed="J" />so I ask you, what do you seek in coming here?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384b25" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">On behalf of the faithful requesting a memorial for a fire site</cb:mulu><head>On behalf of the faithful requesting a memorial for a fire site</head>
<lb n="0384b26" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384b2601" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">With scorched heads and blistered faces as honored guests, brows and beards fallen away—what good karmic conditions! Thus, stripped bare,
<lb n="0384b27" ed="J" />when departing, there is no harm in becoming a Buddha or being born in heaven.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384b28" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Verses in Rhyme on the Old Worthy’s “Fly Passing Through a Window”</cb:mulu><head>Verses in Rhyme on the Old Worthy’s “Fly Passing Through a Window”</head>
<lb n="0384b29" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384b2901" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The foolish fly blindly keeps drilling forward, not knowing whether exit is hard or easy. If it were willing to accept someone pointing it out,
<lb n="0384b30" ed="J" />then even the vast world could not be concealed from it.</l></lg></cb:div>
<pb n="0384c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0384c" />
<lb n="0384c01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Layman Qi Qingqing</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Layman Qi Qingqing</head>
<lb n="0384c02" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384c0201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">In the turmoil of the world there is no end; you must urgently refine careful contemplation within your own heart. Look deeply into the time before your parents were born—
<lb n="0384c03" ed="J" />where then is the place to establish your life and stand your ground?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384c04" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Xu Xiaolian of Zhenhou</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Xu Xiaolian of Zhenhou</head>
<lb n="0384c05" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384c0501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">In every moment I think of you as if mad; when we meet over a cup of wine, there are countless separations. The old public affairs of seven days in those years—
<lb n="0384c06" ed="J" />now, has the bottom of the bucket fallen away or not?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384c07" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Digging a Well</cb:mulu><head>Digging a Well</head>
<lb n="0384c08" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384c0801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Digging a well in ordinary times is not going beyond one's duty; one must guard against thirst before thirst arises. In this world, who can avoid thirst?
<lb n="0384c09" ed="J" />Yet when the disease of thirst arrives, do not let it be too late to regret seeking water.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384c10" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to the monk Benkong of Jinling on investigating the emptiness of the four great elements</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to the monk Benkong of Jinling on investigating the emptiness of the four great elements</head>
<lb n="0384c11" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384c1101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Tearing down the eastern fence to patch the western wall, a beggar exposed and pitiful, depending on others’ compassion. Take care, monk Ben of Beicheng,
<lb n="0384c12" ed="J" />why dig into the earth in search of the blue sky?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384c13" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">To Layman Liyan<g ref="#CB01323" /></cb:mulu><head>To Layman Liyan<g ref="#CB01323" /></head>
<lb n="0384c14" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384c1401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">I often recall how your household is fond of chatter, barking indiscriminately without abiding in the proper measure; after I myself have examined and broken through, I returned to
<lb n="0384c15" ed="J" />Fujian—on some future day, who will be able to examine and break through you?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384c16" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction in response to the rhymes of Scholar Zhou</cb:mulu><head>Instruction in response to the rhymes of Scholar Zhou</head>
<lb n="0384c17" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384c1701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Having seen through the worldly calls of oxen and horses, you move back and forth claiming the path of cranes and clouds. What is directly pointed out is originally not
<lb n="0384c18" ed="J" />a realm; face to face it is upheld like pouring from a clean vessel. The three realms are your home, not a place of exile; your own body is not
<lb n="0384c19" ed="J" />called solitary. This wandering monk has long cherished the joy of living on a boat; why not come together and learn to drift upon the lake?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384c20" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Layman Fan Miran</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Layman Fan Miran</head>
<lb n="0384c21" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384c2101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">If you wish to know whence life and death come and go, a fan suddenly leaps up into the sky, striking the backbone of Śakra,
<lb n="0384c22" ed="J" />and the Persian falls in pain before the gate of the sea.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384c23" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Layman Xu Dawu</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Layman Xu Dawu</head>
<lb n="0384c24" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384c2401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">What is the meaning of seven days in the community? Before conceptual thought arises, a single shout is given, startling the Dharma body up to the Northern Dipper,
<lb n="0384c25" ed="J" />where a mud ox beneath the sea bites into raw iron.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384c26" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Layman Zou Limen</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Layman Zou Limen</head>
<lb n="0384c27" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384c2701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Like insects gnawing wood, forming patterns by chance, you pass through the eighty-four thousand gates of defilement; before the eye, a single mechanism chases lightning
<lb n="0384c28" ed="J" />shadow—on the tip of a needle you carve down a thousand catties of iron.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0384c29" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Layman Jiang Tianru</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Layman Jiang Tianru</head>
<lb n="0384c30" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0384c3001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Before the mouth moves there is not a single phrase; once one word is spoken, whence does it come? Layman Jiang, if you can discern this
<pb n="0385a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0385a" />
<lb n="0385a01" ed="J" />clearly, lotus petals will open one by one upon the stone.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385a02" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Layman Xie Chunyi</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Layman Xie Chunyi</head>
<lb n="0385a03" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385a0301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">When we meet, if one opens the mouth yet does not speak of metaphysics, and does not seek forms or sounds, it is still not so; only when the crown of the head opens to the true
<lb n="0385a04" ed="J" />eye will waves surge up to the summit of Mount Huanghua.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385a05" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">The master took leave of Scholar Yang Fuzi and other literati</cb:mulu><head>The master took leave of Scholar Yang Fuzi and other literati. The scholars asked: “What is the most intimate phrase at the moment of departure?”
<lb n="0385a06" ed="J" />The master silently shifted one step; the assembly did not understand. Then he composed a verse to show them.</head>
<lb n="0385a07" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385a0701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">At the banks of Fusha City we spoke our farewell—do you truly understand the intimate teaching for guiding others? Across ten thousand rivers and a thousand mountains it is vividly
<lb n="0385a08" ed="J" />spoken—why should this old monk chatter endlessly?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385a09" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Scholar Weng Zhengong</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Scholar Weng Zhengong</head>
<lb n="0385a10" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385a1001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">That old case of seven days in former years—have you had a sudden insight into it today or not? At the street of Jiao Li you personally saw it,
<lb n="0385a11" ed="J" />and clearly saw that Bodhidharma was originally an old foreign barbarian.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385a12" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Moving the Mountain Road</cb:mulu><head>Moving the Mountain Road</head>
<lb n="0385a13" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385a1301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">If you can move the primordial unity into levelness, you can make every path smooth and even. Do not say that because the road is flat there is nothing
<lb n="0385a14" ed="J" />to do—you must still see the iron snake lying across your feet.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385a15" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Paying respects at the stupa of Chan Master Yue of Baiyun</cb:mulu><head>Paying respects at the stupa of Chan Master Yue of Baiyun</head>
<lb n="0385a16" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385a1601" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The gate of Baiyun opens wide to the sky; disregarding the body, one is covered in dust and earth. Supporting a frail body upon bamboo
<lb n="0385a17" ed="J" />staff, accompanied by many followers, breaking through the ancient moss. Broken steles and ruined carvings—how could they be worth viewing? Even white ox and dark slave likewise
<lb n="0385a18" ed="J" />are filled with sorrow. After three bows and rising, one more glance is added—what year will there be a return to set things in order again?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385a19" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">In harmony with Venerable Wen’s verses on the animal release society</cb:mulu><head>In harmony with Venerable Wen’s verses on the animal release society</head>
<lb n="0385a20" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385a2001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The gate of life opens to a city of ten thousand homes—who could not cherish life? On this day Jingci again proclaims it,
<lb n="0385a21" ed="J" />revealing what once was flowing water and a famed reputation. Constantly recalling the Buddha’s name with earnest exhortation, all night heavenly flowers drift and
<lb n="0385a22" ed="J" />flutter lightly; fish and dragons in ravines, birds beyond the clouds—each freely enjoys its own nature and ease.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385a23" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Thoughts on the Pure Land, shown to a person of Wuxing</cb:mulu><head>Thoughts on the Pure Land, shown to a person of Wuxing</head>
<lb n="0385a24" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385a2401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">What concern has mind or Pure Land with east or west? Blue lotus is everywhere equally present. Layered cloud mountains and jade steps
<lb n="0385a25" ed="J" />are pure; flowers and trees are lush, rows of trees stand low. Dew is cold, the compassionate face like a dim night moon; wind turns the Buddha’s name, wild
<lb n="0385a26" ed="J" />birds call it forth. The great cosmos is gathered in the potter’s hand—when directly seen, do not speak of a hundred thousand delusions.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385a27" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply in rhyme to Layman Zhu Yuru</cb:mulu><head>Reply in rhyme to Layman Zhu Yuru</head>
<lb n="0385a28" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385a2801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Meeting beyond worldly things, I would speak of the profound, yet I am ashamed my sparse capacity is not yet equal to it. At Baishe I am often startled by your excellent
<lb n="0385a29" ed="J" />verses; in black robes I lose the jewel and almost fall into confusion. By a guest window I would match the room of Ziyang, yet in wild temples I am ashamed to be called the lazy
<lb n="0385a30" ed="J" />Zanchan. You have something of the leisurely spirit of Zong and Lei; we might well sit together and cultivate lotus planting.</l></lg></cb:div>
<pb n="0385b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0385b" />
<lb n="0385b01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Inscription on Xingshan Monastery (with preface)</cb:mulu><head>Inscription on Xingshan Monastery<note place="inline">有引</note></head>
<lb n="0385b02" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0385b0201" style="margin-left:2em">Since the Buddha Bathing Day of the year Wuxu I entered this monastery, and through negligence until the year Wushen I was able to travel to various
<lb n="0385b03" ed="J" />places; yet the events of this place have ultimately vanished into nothingness, which is quite laughable. In the year Wuchen
<lb n="0385b04" ed="J" />in summer, weary from travel, I again rested here. Just then Brother Dacheng and Brother Tongren kindly visited, not disdaining
<lb n="0385b05" ed="J" />the desolation but instead appreciating its quiet solitude. We examined inscriptions and records, and roughly understood its outline. Occasionally gentlemen
<lb n="0385b06" ed="J" />composed poems; though I know little of tonal patterns, I also composed two pieces.</p>
<lb n="0385b07" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385b0701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The old order of the Dharma is now deeply submerged; Liang and Song inscriptions—where can their traces be found? The green-vine niche is closed, the monks
<lb n="0385b08" ed="J" />keep still; the white hut door stands open, letting the grasses grow deep. Curtains rolled up, wild wind carries the shepherd’s flute; the temple chime strikes the empty green haze,
<lb n="0385b09" ed="J" />brushing through sparse forest. I alone lament that the flame of wisdom has no new blaze, and with shaven head I often scratch, sighing over past and present.</l></lg>
<lb n="0385b10" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385b1001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Tall trees and a clear stream encircle the deep monastery; short bridges are sought in several places. Pagodas stand side by side, startling the morning
<lb n="0385b11" ed="J" />birds; fragrant halls are unevenly set in the slanting daytime shade. Pine paths sealed in cloud must be freely roamed; willow ponds pulling the moon stir
<lb n="0385b12" ed="J" />long chants. The eminent one who wandered with staff and inscribed the scenic site still makes me ashamed of my former student’s heart.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385b13" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply to Chan Master Dacheng’s visit</cb:mulu><head>Reply to Chan Master Dacheng’s visit</head>
<lb n="0385b14" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385b1401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">My old friend earnestly comes to break the summer heat; in welcoming him I unconsciously put my shoes on backwards. Asking you about affairs on the road,
<lb n="0385b15" ed="J" />how were they? Smiling, you point to a drop of rain before the eaves. Before words arise, the mechanism is activated and the eye alone is clear; facing the moon, chanting, the mind
<lb n="0385b16" ed="J" />is filled together. At this gathering it is not easy to meet like this—may we avoid having clouds fly up beneath our feet.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385b17" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply to Chan Master Tongren’s visit</cb:mulu><head>Reply to Chan Master Tongren’s visit</head>
<lb n="0385b18" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385b1801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Lingering in a desolate monastery, how could it be called a home? Indeed people may find the village road too distant. My thin body has only just begun to rest,
<lb n="0385b19" ed="J" />yet why does a lofty practitioner travel far by carriage? Discussing Chan under the moon, pines and clouds are still; composing verses in the wind, bamboo
<lb n="0385b20" ed="J" />rhythms are excellent. Remembering the old paths of the Five Peaks, beyond the forest the sound of flutes is like Hu melodies.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385b21" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply to Chan Master Muyun’s letter</cb:mulu><head>Reply to Chan Master Muyun’s letter</head>
<lb n="0385b22" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385b2201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Frosty sky, cold moon under vine shade; it is as if traces of poetry brush across half the forest. Why do things and sentiments know intent so well,
<lb n="0385b23" ed="J" />after so long, already filling plain paper with deep longing? Our separation is not like falling into worldly dust; in dreams I still sketch your smiling<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0385b2301" n="0385b2301" /><anchor xml:id="beg0385b2301" n="0385b2301" /><anchor xml:id="end0385b2301" />
<lb n="0385b24" ed="J" />words in search—only cold plum blossoms remain at this moment; it is fitting to pick them to send to a true friend.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385b25" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Consoling the Transplanted Plum</cb:mulu><head>Consoling the Transplanted Plum</head>
<lb n="0385b26" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385b2601" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">In the fragrant courtyard, year after year spring is splashed with beauty; in transplanting it here, do not mind too much solitude. Still the moonlight remains, thinning the old
<lb n="0385b27" ed="J" />shadows, while fresh rain and dew nourish new branches. In the secluded grove there is already enough vitality shared; there is no need for settled dreams
<lb n="0385b28" ed="J" />When depicting such places, fortunately it is all on deeply fertile ground; enduring the cold is originally what allows flowers to take form.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385b29" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Writing on the Flower Ornament Sutra for a friend</cb:mulu><head>Writing on the Flower Ornament Sutra for a friend</head>
<lb n="0385b30" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385b3001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Dew-drop farming in mist amid mixed blossoms; a single thought arises without cause, imitating wild hemp; in the colored clouds and blue heavens the brush moves
<pb n="0385c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0385c" />
<lb n="0385c01" ed="J" />vast and free, green bamboo and clear wind write extravagant verses. At the inkstone the ocean of fragrant waters is stirred; at the brush tip the assembly of
<lb n="0385c02" ed="J" />Suras is overturned. Meeting and asking for guidance, there are no extraordinary lines to give—please look instead at the slanting shadows of coral trees.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385c03" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Layman Zixing on visiting Tiantong</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Layman Zixing on visiting Tiantong</head>
<lb n="0385c04" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385c0401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">In the eighth month you travel to Yue; in autumn mountains everywhere reveal the golden wind. Only observe how the river thus sends flying
<lb n="0385c05" ed="J" />waves—do not ask how the moon fills the sky. Before Mount Taibai all is fully assented; above Hejia Pond all traces are utterly
<lb n="0385c06" ed="J" />gone. Taking up once more the intimate words at parting, at dawn the boat curtain is pushed aside and the sun is bright red.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385c07" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Two quatrains on climbing the Misty Rain Pavilion</cb:mulu><head>Two quatrains on climbing the Misty Rain Pavilion</head>
<lb n="0385c08" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385c0801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Clear scenery is lovingly present in the wheat-harvest season; a few of us hire a ferry and try climbing the pavilion. On a clear day, do not say there is no mist and
<lb n="0385c09" ed="J" />rain—empty green haze and shaded depths float before the eyes.</l></lg>
<lb n="0385c10" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385c1001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Water pavilions and fishing boats are each serene; painting scrolls and poetic moods spread near and far. Reclining in ease, one does not notice the sky about to
<lb n="0385c11" ed="J" />dusk, while in the salt warehouses and myriad wells cooking smoke rises everywhere.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385c12" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply in rhyme to Chan Master Fushi</cb:mulu><head>Reply in rhyme to Chan Master Fushi</head>
<lb n="0385c13" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385c1301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The Eastern Ji monastery preserves an ancient style of the world; relying on lofty integrity, one may again follow its traces. Plum blossom fragrance is carried to South Lake,
<lb n="0385c14" ed="J" />through winding bends—why must consolation rely on formal greetings?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385c15" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Reply to Chan Master Konglin’s visit, two poems</cb:mulu><head>Reply to Chan Master Konglin’s visit, two poems</head>
<lb n="0385c16" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385c1601" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">I was just lamenting the vanished fish and wild geese, when unexpectedly you crossed the wild fields; meeting, we can stay together for a night or two, and that is better than many years apart.
<lb n="0385c17" ed="J" />I grieve that the Dharma has declined from ancient times, and in sorrow over the age I strike the tea mat. I admire your humble learning, and rejoice that you further seek completeness.
<lb n="0385c18" ed="J" />With eyes as strong as sinew and bone, you gaze upon the vast world; even worldly folk are made not to fall into dust and defilement.
<lb n="0385c19" ed="J" />Wherever I go I am among clouds and mountains; at all times flowers and willows are neighbors. Heaven and earth all belong to me—how could living experience be called poverty?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385c20" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Venerable Miyin Zhenlin honored me with a visit</cb:mulu><head>Venerable Miyin Zhenlin honored me with a visit</head>
<lb n="0385c21" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385c2101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">For twenty years your lofty forest traces—how did you come to this distant village? Separation only adds to the years; meeting now, we learn of each other's warmth and cold.
<lb n="0385c22" ed="J" />Our friendship aspires to the ancients; in forgetting age you graciously lower yourself in respect. I am ashamed, being but useless timber, yet we still discuss name and principle.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385c23" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">In harmony with the Ten Practices of Longmen</cb:mulu><head>In harmony with the Ten Practices of Longmen</head>
<lb n="0385c24" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="3" type="其他">Seated in meditation</cb:mulu><head>Seated in meditation</head>
<lb n="0385c25" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385c2501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Breaking free from the original mother's single body of bones, supporting heaven and propping up earth with nothing obstructed; cutting off Buddha and Mara in seated stillness with nothing remaining,
<lb n="0385c26" ed="J" />where could heavenly maidens even find flowers to scatter?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385c27" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="3" type="其他">Entering the room</cb:mulu><head>Entering the room</head>
<lb n="0385c28" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0385c2801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">As soon as one enters the gate, a shout is given; even if a lion loses all its majesty. If Chan practitioners again move their lips,
<lb n="0385c29" ed="J" />they should receive another blow to the back of the head.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0385c30" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="3" type="其他">General labor assembly</cb:mulu><head>General labor assembly</head>
<pb n="0386a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0386a" />
<lb n="0386a01" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386a0101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">When the signal is struck in Uttarakuru, monks in Jambudvipa become busy; this sick monk has no strength to bear the burden,
<lb n="0386a02" ed="J" />so he can only carry Mount Sumeru as a desk peak.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386a03" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="3" type="其他">Receiving food</cb:mulu><head>Receiving food</head>
<lb n="0386a04" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386a0401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Calling out, “Bodhisattva, come eat!”—even the Golden Ox would open its mouth without ceremony. But how does this compare with those in Tongyue Hermitage,
<lb n="0386a05" ed="J" />who with iron necks and bronze heads cannot be called back?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386a06" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="3" type="其他">Washing clothes</cb:mulu><head>Laundry</head>
<lb n="0386a07" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386a0701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Mud-smeared, water-dragging birth-given trousers, cleansing filth still relies on the Anavatapta Lake, the lofty Jambudana sandalwood tree
<lb n="0386a08" ed="J" />On top, in later days scorched by sun and blown by wind.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386a09" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="3" type="其他">Walking meditation</cb:mulu><head>Walking meditation</head>
<lb n="0386a10" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386a1001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The front step has not yet moved, already rushing after the next; who would know each step never actually meets the other, circling the great thousand-world realm once
<lb n="0386a11" ed="J" />Yet under the soles, when has there ever been the slightest movement?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386a12" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="3" type="其他">Sweeping the floor</cb:mulu><head>Sweeping the floor</head>
<lb n="0386a13" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386a1301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Last night the empty sky fell down, scattering dust all over the ground, in the old monk’s eyes it is hard to tolerate
<lb n="0386a14" ed="J" />Grains of dust, just swept away with an iron broom</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386a15" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="3" type="其他">Chanting sutras</cb:mulu><head>Chanting sutras</head>
<lb n="0386a16" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386a1601" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Casually walking once to the meditation couch, the rolling recitation resounds so high, those who know each other rejoice as fellow-robed companions
<lb n="0386a17" ed="J" />As guests, even a foolish old woman is not granted three inches of leniency</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386a18" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="3" type="其他">Prostrations</cb:mulu><head>Prostrations</head>
<lb n="0386a19" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386a1901" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The present Buddha does not bow to past Buddhas; it has already become foul and stinking throughout all directions, the old monk bows diligently every day<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0386a1901" n="0386a1901" /><anchor xml:id="beg0386a1901" n="0386a1901" /><anchor xml:id="end0386a1901" />
<lb n="0386a20" ed="J" />Tell me, how can it be compared?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386a21" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="3" type="其他">Dharma talk</cb:mulu><head>Dharma talk</head>
<lb n="0386a22" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386a2201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Mud people and wooden puppets chance to meet, furrowed brows and tangled faces, talk grows lively, bamboo stools and incense altar accompany the night sitting
<lb n="0386a23" ed="J" />Sitting through the night, vase flowers fill the seat, laughing in the spring breeze</l></lg></cb:div></cb:div>
<lb n="0386a24" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Ten poems composed in response to Master Xue’s mountain dwelling</cb:mulu><head>Ten poems composed in response to Master Xue’s mountain dwelling</head>
<lb n="0386a25" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386a2501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Green mountains only allow companionship with white clouds; a gourd hut lets me be buried there as well; the cold mountain face looks upon me
<lb n="0386a26" ed="J" />Vast mist and cloud shadows reveal the monk’s straw sandals</l></lg>
<lb n="0386a27" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386a2701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Lethargic and detached from the world, unlike other companions, I bury my form deep within myself; reckoning with past idle bones
<lb n="0386a28" ed="J" />I regret having worn out several pairs of shoes</l></lg>
<lb n="0386a29" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386a2901" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Completely forgetting old companions, a solitary ascetic buried alone in desolation; sitting through the empty mountain with no affairs
<lb n="0386a30" ed="J" />Ordinarily not even costing a pair of worn-out shoes</l></lg>
<pb n="0386b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0386b" />
<lb n="0386b01" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386b0101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">At times I suddenly recall old companions, burying fame and profit in deep pits with all effort; how unlike the mountain dweller without affairs
<lb n="0386b02" ed="J" />Who idly accompanies a bamboo staff and straw sandals</l></lg>
<lb n="0386b03" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386b0301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Clear wind and white moon belong to our kind; mountain colors and stream sounds are buried within; in countless lives of wandering places
<lb n="0386b04" ed="J" />Green moss cushions the feet, no shoes are worn</l></lg>
<lb n="0386b05" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386b0501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Monkeys and wild deer are my companions; daily I tend a thatched fire; salt and sauce have never been lacking through the years
<lb n="0386b06" ed="J" />Noble households never reach the old monk’s shoes</l></lg>
<lb n="0386b07" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386b0701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Spring mountains after rain delight our kind; green trees and red flowers are buried in clouds; in high spirits I cross streams to climb and gaze afar
<lb n="0386b08" ed="J" />From what place could rain have wet my shoes?</l></lg>
<lb n="0386b09" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386b0901" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Alas, within the monastery there is such a one, buried headless in a thicket of vines; if someday there is a return to the mountains
<lb n="0386b10" ed="J" />I would still regret having often worn out my shoes</l></lg>
<lb n="0386b11" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386b1101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Seeking Buddha or immortality, each has their own kind; all become trapped in their own ruts; in former days they spoke of loving the black pearl
<lb n="0386b12" ed="J" />Today it is seen as merely broken straw sandals</l></lg>
<lb n="0386b13" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386b1301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Body and shadow circling as if companions, green mountains laugh at me buried in stillness; today I sit steadily watching ease
<lb n="0386b14" ed="J" />How many times have I worn through iron-soled shoes</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386b15" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Glad Rain</cb:mulu><head>Glad Rain</head>
<lb n="0386b16" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386b1601" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">A few clouds added to spur poetry, a single plough of new rain brings joy to ten thousand homes, heard as line after line of peace and prosperity
<lb n="0386b17" ed="J" />Meandering bends; looking out over rippling field and wild water patterns. Under heaven, who does not repay the highest virtue; by the north window, who is not joyful
<lb n="0386b18" ed="J" />Southern breeze; even begging with a gourd ladle can sustain the remainder of life; in my downcast poetic mood, inspiration is abundant</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386b19" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Composed on the theme of cocks crowing in unison west of the stream</cb:mulu><head>Composed on the theme of cocks crowing in unison west of the stream</head>
<lb n="0386b20" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386b2001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">In a single room I seek seclusion, delighted to dwell beside the stream; is Hangu Pass perhaps west of the stream? The river city lies distant and dim, war drums sinking into silence
<lb n="0386b21" ed="J" />Drums; the villages bustle loudly as dawn cocks herald the day. The slanting moon is dim and hazy, its sound should be slow; the fresh morning breeze revives all things, singing
<lb n="0386b22" ed="J" />coming together in unison; at times they seem vivid like butterflies, deceiving one into hearing them cry beneath my window</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386b23" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Two poems on the boat hermitage</cb:mulu><head>Two poems on the boat hermitage</head>
<lb n="0386b24" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386b2401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">A thatched roof like a skiff moored on a misty lake; pure dreams are nothing but journeys upon water; the cooking stove often borrows fishermen’s lights
<lb n="0386b25" ed="J" />to seek; mountain boys are often called as boatmen. In the shade of paulownia, a sharp wind startles the awning to turn; moonlight on the window shifts, as if
<lb n="0386b26" ed="J" />waves rise and support it; before the hermitage in sparse shadows stand a thousand bamboo stalks, well suited for fishing river perch on level ground</l></lg>
<lb n="0386b27" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386b2701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Lingering in clouded ravines I settle my traces; the wild scenes of the vast river can scarcely be described; moonlight soaks the steps and spreads flat across them
<lb n="0386b28" ed="J" />water; high dwelling pine shade densely covers the awning. From afar the flying waterfall seems like floral waves in motion; nearby neighbors appear to host guests
<lb n="0386b29" ed="J" />when boats meet; let others point to those dwelling in the mountains; I alone make my pact of the heart with seagulls</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386b30" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Returning clouds</cb:mulu><head>Returning clouds</head>
<pb n="0386c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0386c" />
<lb n="0386c01" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386c0101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Idle clouds especially favor the wild monk’s dwelling, repeatedly flying to the green cliffs, erasing a line of wild geese in formation
<lb n="0386c02" ed="J" />geese; confused about their return, how many crows search for nests. Lightly tinting the plum blossoms with faint cold flowers, heavily hanging in front of the woods, slender
<lb n="0386c03" ed="J" />slanting bamboo; it is idle talk that one has long dwelt and rested in the mountains, for the spring breeze still allows emergence into rosy mists</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386c04" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Frozen clouds</cb:mulu><head>Frozen clouds</head>
<lb n="0386c05" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386c0501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The long sky’s clouds are cold and dull as if stubborn; dimly they hang low as if they could be pulled down; without rain they should not yet have formed into frozen color
<lb n="0386c06" ed="J" />color; if there is wind, why not ride it back to the mountains? Wandering traces may briefly become empty husks, but fixed traces are not the same as obstruction
<lb n="0386c07" ed="J" />at the pass of travelers; in myriad wells of the riverside village, night fires cook and rise, chaotic smoke striking and breaking into mottled patterns</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386c08" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Sitting in the Rain</cb:mulu><head>Sitting in the Rain</head>
<lb n="0386c09" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386c0901" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Rain sounds in disorder wash the green mountains; the traveler sits in desolation as drip after drip falls in idle stillness; clear rhythms lightly strike the bones of poetry
<lb n="0386c10" ed="J" />Cold; damp marks repeatedly spatter the patched monk’s robe in mottled stains. Wind combs through empty bamboo greedily wrapped in mist; jade-dewed cold plum blossoms, lazy
<lb n="0386c11" ed="J" />Smiling face; seated embracing a red brazier, what intention is there? In several places rushing streams murmur and trickle</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386c12" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Sending Off the Moon</cb:mulu><head>Sending Off the Moon</head>
<lb n="0386c13" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386c1301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Smiling as I play with the icy disc, meaning seems delayed; walking on and on, how could we speak of parting? I pity you, becoming solitary in empty stillness
<lb n="0386c14" ed="J" />departing, it draws me into clear chanting, thinking of you. As it gently reaches the plum blossom marker I try to hold it back, as compared to the sudden shifting of flower shadows
<lb n="0386c15" ed="J" />urging movement; if the empty forest allows a night’s appointment, then better to send this poem widely tonight itself</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386c16" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Chanting Snow in the Mountains</cb:mulu><head>Chanting Snow in the Mountains</head>
<lb n="0386c17" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386c1701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The wild monk endures the cold while watching snow fly; which peak is not covered and concealed? Beneath the bamboo, the old plum secretly breaks through
<lb n="0386c18" ed="J" />jade; before the eaves tame birds urgently seek the beam. Graceful moonlight is wholly without shadow; each falling petal’s beauty ultimately
<lb n="0386c19" ed="J" />is without fragrance; facing you I chant in lofty spirit many times, fearing even my disheveled hair will turn gray</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0386c20" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Imitating the Ancient Style of Master Guanxiu, Five Poems</cb:mulu><head>Imitating the Ancient Style of Master Guanxiu, Five Poems</head>
<lb n="0386c21" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386c2101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Howling winds sweep the autumn sky, roaring and startling the forest thickets; thus within the universe, things are often like being tightly bound in a pouch
<lb n="0386c22" ed="J" />Stirring through the ten thousand transformations, all creeping things are ensnared; yet my aged heart does not accept their reckless sway
<lb n="0386c23" ed="J" />What are heaven and earth after all? The myriad sounds are but dregs; peacefully beneath the clouded pavilion, I merge indifferently with vast emptiness
<lb n="0386c24" ed="J" />From this I understand nothing at all; even having eyes, one is not truly seeing; titles are in utter confusion, and I yield a great laugh</l></lg>
<lb n="0386c25" ed="J" />
<p cb:type="head3" xml:id="pJ27p0386c2501">Second</p>
<lb n="0386c26" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0386c2601" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">All things undergo transformation together; if not true, can it be called false? In the bustling human world, it is hard to act as the creator
<lb n="0386c27" ed="J" />Suffering and joy have their origin; glory and decay each have their dwelling place. Why are people themselves so deluded, rushing confusedly up and down
<lb n="0386c28" ed="J" />Most grieve over losing a horse, not knowing it may return; if one understands this principle in life, then a hundred years may be lived in ease and freedom
<lb n="0386c29" ed="J" />My Way is originally thus, not subject to their shaping and refining. You ask what it does? I do not know.</l></lg>
<lb n="0386c30" ed="J" />
<p cb:type="head3" xml:id="pJ27p0386c3001">Section Three</p>
<pb n="0387a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0387a" />
<lb n="0387a01" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387a0101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">On South Mountain there is a man of stature, truly heroic in spirit; he has climbed Mount Tai and Mount Hua, and has explored the waves of the boundless sea.
<lb n="0387a02" ed="J" />His attainments are not shallow, and his vision is also very high; seated grandly on his couch, he looks down upon the toil of living beings.
<lb n="0387a03" ed="J" />Bright and full like the moon in the laurel sky; facing it I am filled with joy. Heavenly fragrance comes from beyond the clouds, and I would draw it in and hold it fast.</l></lg>
<lb n="0387a04" ed="J" />
<p cb:type="head3" xml:id="pJ27p0387a0401">Section Four</p>
<lb n="0387a05" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387a0501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The heart of heaven and earth is vast and empty, visible yet not to be imitated; it is lodged in spring flower branches and still entrusted to the autumn wind.
<lb n="0387a06" ed="J" />Glory and withering clearly have no two meanings; thus the ancient noble ones saw all things as themselves.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0387a0601" n="0387a0601" /><anchor xml:id="beg0387a0601" n="0387a0601" /><anchor xml:id="end0387a0601" />
<lb n="0387a07" ed="J" />Living beings have never been different; it is only that they do not know restraint. Who would carefully ponder this and return to the principle of ceaseless generation?</l></lg>
<lb n="0387a08" ed="J" />
<p cb:type="head3" xml:id="pJ27p0387a0801">Section Five</p>
<lb n="0387a09" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387a0901" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Modern friendships and ancient friendships share the same principle; why distinguish old and new? Only observe what one does.
<lb n="0387a10" ed="J" />The Way and emotion interweave; each direction has its kind. If one takes the Way as intent, where would there be anything other than right relation?
<lb n="0387a11" ed="J" />Because those who hold to the Way are few, even face to face they are already apart; most are attached to emotion, outwardly sincere yet inwardly false.
<lb n="0387a12" ed="J" />Thus there is no intent to share gold; in a single morning it is lightly abandoned. Alas, I hesitate again, as long as the clear wind has not yet fallen.
<lb n="0387a13" ed="J" />If one can have the conduct of pine and cypress, I wish to form companionship with such a one.</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0387a14" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to disciples</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to disciples</head>
<lb n="0387a15" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387a1501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">The family tradition of frugality is not my stinginess; from of old, expenses come from the human world. One must be ashamed that the practice of the Way is largely neglected
<lb n="0387a16" ed="J" />and slackened; do not frequently visit wealthy patrons. Simply remedy hunger and injury with coarse food, and carefully preserve this illusory body
<lb n="0387a17" ed="J" />in remote mountains. If you wish to truly know it step by step at the very root, how could you lightly let your effort be set aside in idleness?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0387a18" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Bai Sheng Kaisun</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Bai Sheng Kaisun</head>
<lb n="0387a19" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387a1901" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">When opening a text, do not let it slip by as swiftly as shooting stars; when speaking aloud and pronouncing words, they must be clear and harmonious. Before the scriptures, if the mind is blocked and cramped like empty space
<lb n="0387a20" ed="J" />phrases, let me ask you: do you understand it now?</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0387a21" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction on Precepts</cb:mulu><head>Instruction on Precepts Section</head>
<lb n="0387a22" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387a2201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">With a snap of the fingers, enter the latrine with calm dignity; arranging matters so even dripping water is properly placed; from the rear rack of the bucket hoop comes a single sound
<lb n="0387a23" ed="J" />of a sudden burst; one picks up the two brows of ancient worthies</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0387a24" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Shiqu</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Shiqu</head>
<lb n="0387a25" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387a2501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">To travel and inquire one must have the eye of inquiry; in chaotic shouts and wild gestures one must discern what is true; having worn through straw sandals one should oneself
<lb n="0387a26" ed="J" />cherish them; do not be greedy in wandering tirelessly among mountains and rivers</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0387a27" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Kechu</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Kechu</head>
<lb n="0387a28" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387a2801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Do not say it is easy to serve guests and offer tea; in Dou Lao’s time a single word went astray; the breakthrough did not come because of Han Da
<lb n="0387a29" ed="J" />Bo; how could one so easily distinguish dragon from snake</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0387a30" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Yuefan</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Yuefan</head>
<pb n="0387b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0387b" />
<lb n="0387b01" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387b0101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Leaving home is surely not by chance; diligent practice must strive to be first; one must see for oneself that a disciple of the Buddha is not easily
<lb n="0387b02" ed="J" />so; the heavy burden must be carefully shouldered</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0387b03" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Qufan</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Qufan</head>
<lb n="0387b04" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387b0401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">When coarse delusive ignorance is laid down, in humble study one must bow the head low; if one can indeed set a fixed term for the practice of the Way
<lb n="0387b05" ed="J" />to accomplish it, one should properly regulate conduct and seek the discipline of the precepts</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0387b06" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Instruction to Jinghua</cb:mulu><head>Instruction to Jinghua</head>
<lb n="0387b07" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387b0701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">With steady and reliable conduct, travel to various places; lodging at temples is no hindrance to requesting entry into the hall; straighten the backbone as if in ice and snow
<lb n="0387b08" ed="J" />cold; how could one endure idle chatter that wastes time</l></lg></cb:div>
<lb n="0387b09" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Five Poems on Wealth, Sex, Fame, Food, and Sleep</cb:mulu><head>Five Poems on Wealth, Sex, Fame, Food, and Sleep</head>
<lb n="0387b10" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387b1001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Gold, silver bullion, and green cash coins, amassed like mountains, are still pitiable; it is laughable that the old Pang could pour out the sea
<lb n="0387b11" ed="J" />at its bottom; how could there be any harm in simply following whatever is needed according to circumstances</l></lg>
<lb n="0387b12" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387b1201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Clearly a charming and radiant branch of flower; whoever encounters it cannot help but cover their eyes; this is always the old monk’s affection
<lb n="0387b13" ed="J" />for a long time; at times I alone reach toward it in the mirror</l></lg>
<lb n="0387b14" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387b1401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">A formless thing fills the nine realms; the wise and foolish, the honored and base, each is fully filled within the heart; who can escape
<lb n="0387b15" ed="J" />from such a rut; I too am entirely buried within it</l></lg>
<lb n="0387b16" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387b1601" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Do not speak lightly of coarse food filling the skin-bag; do not envy fine dishes, for their taste is sweet of itself; on the tongue, coarse and fine become one<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0387b1601" n="0387b1601" /><anchor xml:id="beg0387b1601" n="0387b1601" /><anchor xml:id="end0387b1601" />
<lb n="0387b17" ed="J" />taste; delight and aversion arise of themselves, without any concealment or confusion</l></lg>
<lb n="0387b18" ed="J" />
<lg xml:id="lgJ27p0387b1801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:0em;"><l style="text-indent:0em">Before dusk one already wants to sleep; half-awake at dawn one still craves slumber; in hazy dimness all things are without cause
<lb n="0387b19" ed="J" />and clarity; waking and sleeping together are stirred into one mass</l></lg></cb:div></cb:div>
<lb n="0387b20" ed="J" />
<lb n="0387b21" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Miscellaneous Writings</cb:mulu><head>Miscellaneous Writings</head>
<lb n="0387b22" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Hanging the Cloud Board</cb:mulu><p xml:id="pJ27p0387b2201">Hanging the Cloud Board. The master said: The cloud board hangs high, the signal of the monastery; all with eyes can see it, yet those who know gratitude
<lb n="0387b23" ed="J" />are few; all with ears can hear it, yet those who betray gratitude are many. Suddenly he raised the mallet and said: Great virtuous ones, is there anyone who can strike
<lb n="0387b24" ed="J" />a blow? Yet the handle is in this mountain monk’s hand. Then he struck once and said: One strike
<lb n="0387b25" ed="J" />shatters empty space into dust; all copper-headed and iron-faced ones return</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0387b26" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Preface to the Verses of the Perfect Enlightenment Society</cb:mulu><head>Preface to the Verses of the Perfect Enlightenment Society</head>
<lb n="0387b27" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0387b2701">The Golden-Faced Gautama is accustomed to digging caves in empty space; the twelve great bodhisattvas all seek ice within flames
<lb n="0387b28" ed="J" />Where is there to seek the monastery of Perfect Enlightenment? What do you call the teachings of the sutras? Now you good people yourselves
<lb n="0387b29" ed="J" />can eat your fill of white rice and drain the South Lake; why not take it upon your whole body, yet still wish to form a society and cultivate
<lb n="0387b30" ed="J" />practice? This is precisely what is called in broad daylight under the blue sky, being possessed by ghosts and demons. Even so, you good people still
<pb n="0387c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0387c" />
<lb n="0387c01" ed="J" />are unwilling to hastily accept it, and do not fall into the careless confusions of the present age; this is truly rare. Slowly they take out their hands
<lb n="0387c02" ed="J" />scrolls, join palms in reverence, and ask me for written words of instruction; even this sick monk cannot avoid following delusion and chasing evil
<lb n="0387c03" ed="J" />I will briefly add a few words, and further append a verse: “In equal peace and dwelling, how should one act? In streets and alleys, do not
<lb n="0387c04" ed="J" />be careless and procrastinate; suddenly break through the road home, and be able to swallow South Lake in a single gulp.”</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0387c05" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Preface to the Flower-raising Society</cb:mulu><head>Preface to the Flower-raising Society</head>
<lb n="0387c06" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0387c0601">From the moment the World-Honored One was born, strange and unusual, wild and unrestrained, he strode forth boldly and freely,
<lb n="0387c07" ed="J" />speaking grandly and widely, as if spitting blood upon others and so defiling his own mouth. Then at the foot of the Mountain of Right Awakening,
<lb n="0387c08" ed="J" />seeing a star he awakened to the Way, and exclaimed: “Marvelous are beings! They all possess the wisdom and virtue of the Thus Come One.” Thus he
<lb n="0387c09" ed="J" />spoke sudden and gradual teachings, spoke emptiness and existence, and it became increasingly unendurable. When it came to the very end, there was still
<lb n="0387c10" ed="J" />one remaining burden not yet discarded; amid the assembly he picked up a flower, and at that time a hundred
<lb n="0387c11" ed="J" />thousand beings of gods and humans, each and every one full of vigor—yet who looked with the true eye? Still it was slightly lacking. Occasionally
<lb n="0387c12" ed="J" />there was the golden ascetic who broke into a faint smile, as if the household could not restrain itself and had produced such a rebellious child
<lb n="0387c13" ed="J" />coming forth. He also said: “I have the treasury of the true Dharma eye, the wondrous mind of nirvana, entrusted to Mahakashyapa.” Again
<lb n="0387c14" ed="J" />and again it falls into ruin. Fortunately now the lay followers of Zuili each have eyes that can swallow the Buddhas and patriarchs, covering all regions
<lb n="0387c15" ed="J" />about to capture and defeat it; two old rogues have formed a Chan society, called Flower-raising. This is truly like
<lb n="0387c16" ed="J" />a lotus in fire, rare in the world. I dwell in a corner of South Lake village, ill and staying put, eating full meals
<lb n="0387c17" ed="J" />and dozing off to pass the days, having done nothing for a long time. Receiving the laymen’s request to consult this sick
<lb n="0387c18" ed="J" />monk, I had no choice but to scribble a rough piece. If there are any nearby who are unwilling to accept it,<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0387c1801" n="0387c1801" /><anchor xml:id="beg0387c1801" n="0387c1801" /><anchor xml:id="end0387c1801" />
<lb n="0387c19" ed="J" />break this sick monk’s legs and give him a thorough beating with a rotten club, I would have no excuse.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0387c20" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Preface to the Verse on Installing an Image of Great Compassion in the Xingchan Monastery Hall</cb:mulu><head>Preface to the Verse on Installing an Image of Great Compassion in the Xingchan Monastery Hall</head>
<lb n="0387c21" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0387c2101">I bow in homage to Great Compassion; through its pervasive fragrance one attains perfect penetration; it manifests without end, and is not bound by any place
<lb n="0387c22" ed="J" />Now at Xingchan Monastery it again appears in the world to teach the Dharma; all birds become parrots—how is this different from the Small White Flower
<lb n="0387c23" ed="J" />Carving and gold lacquer, costing as much as thousands in gold; may it spread into the minds of the multitude, who keep in contemplation the image of the Bodhisattva
<lb n="0387c24" ed="J" />In the minds of millions, there are millions of Bodhisattvas; each is not different from the other, all are the Venerable of Perfect Penetration
<lb n="0387c25" ed="J" />Naturally a joyful mind arises, aiding those who establish this cause; whether copper coins or green coins, what matter is it whether much or little
<lb n="0387c26" ed="J" />All faithful followers receiving this list should encourage one another; donations gathered like grains of sand will surely result in superior merit and virtue.
<lb n="0387c27" ed="J" />This is planting the cause of Perfect Penetration, which will surely yield the fruit of Perfect Penetration; these few verses are truly not empty or false words.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0387c28" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Preface to the fundraising for robes and alms bowl by attendant Jingyuan</cb:mulu><head>Preface to the fundraising for robes and alms bowl by attendant Jingyuan</head>
<lb n="0387c29" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0387c2901">Our Buddha, out of compassionate grace, taught the disciplinary law for a time; Upali followed his path and extended the monastic regulations into the latter age.
<lb n="0387c30" ed="J" />Now the gate of emptiness is desolate; not even a single alms bowl is complete; worldly conditions are sparse and declining—how can the three robes be provided? From great heights
<pb n="0388a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0388a" />
<lb n="0388a01" ed="J" />drifting silk threads cannot yet be drawn through a needle to make thread; cloud fragments in midair do not allow scissors to descend and form garments.
<lb n="0388a02" ed="J" />It is necessary to rely on offerings from faithful lay supporters, so that the morning sun will not patch the ragged robe; thus even idle monks
<lb n="0388a03" ed="J" />may remain pure, and gladly face the moon while finishing the remaining scriptures. This wandering ascetic truthfully reports that
<lb n="0388a04" ed="J" />this merit is true merit.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0388a05" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Petition for the fundraising of bell and drum</cb:mulu><head>Petition for the fundraising of bell and drum</head>
<lb n="0388a06" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0388a0601">The Jingci Hermitage was founded by Great Master Wen of Taoshan in western Zhejiang. The master, carrying
<lb n="0388a07" ed="J" />both urgency in discipline and broad propagation of Chan and Pure Land, traveled everywhere with his staff, transforming and guiding both monastics and laity; especially through his actionless activity
<lb n="0388a08" ed="J" />he moved like a blade in open space. Wherever he arrived at Xintin and Jiantin, countless red banners were raised. Moreover
<lb n="0388a09" ed="J" />in the samadhi of compassionate mind, he took pity on all beings in water and on land, flying and crawling creatures, and each month initiated the release of life
<lb n="0388a10" ed="J" />protection societies, thus establishing places for releasing life. Yet while urgently saving beings as if one’s eyebrows were on fire, regarding
<lb n="0388a11" ed="J" />the instruments of the Dharma not yet complete, this is self-evident. Thus monasteries are established and bells and drums prepared. Alas!
<lb n="0388a12" ed="J" />Is it merely a matter of monasteries? It depends on having the right people. Is it merely a matter of bells and drums? It depends on spreading the Dharma.
<lb n="0388a13" ed="J" />Recalling the spiritual Vulture Peak of Kapilavastu, whenever the Great Enlightened World-Honored One opened a Dharma assembly, he would first sound the bell to gather the assembly,
<lb n="0388a14" ed="J" />and beat the drum to ascend the platform, intending that all beings on earth would realize before words are spoken and understand beyond sound in an instant,
<lb n="0388a15" ed="J" />in an instant go from delusion to awakening, transform from ordinary to holy; such instruments and their Dharma benefits are vast and extensive—how could
<lb n="0388a16" ed="J" />their scope be easily measured? Thus in the Jetavana grove, the striking of the bell once revealed the nature of hearing; at Grdhrakuta
<lb n="0388a17" ed="J" />Mountain, the great Dharma drum was sounded to proclaim immeasurable meanings; these are standards unerased through the ages. Now this hermitage
<lb n="0388a18" ed="J" />is entrusted to so-and-so as its senior steward. We all consider ourselves unworthy descendants, yet we must follow in the noble traces
<lb n="0388a19" ed="J" />Suddenly, with the intent of Perfect Penetration, they cast a drum, and with a heart of raw iron they cast a bell, not wishing to rely solely on the assent of
<lb n="0388a20" ed="J" />individual effort to accomplish the task, but instead wishing to fully bow before the gathering of myriad conditions; observing their intention, it is truly good. How could
<lb n="0388a21" ed="J" />there be any wise lay supporters who would not gladly take up the brush and joyfully contribute? Hearing this, I am greatly pleased, and say
<lb n="0388a22" ed="J" />there is now a monastery, and there are now bells and drums; therefore, without avoiding lack of literary elegance, I place this at the beginning of the scroll.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0388a23" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Revision of the Commentary on the Flower Ornament Sutra</cb:mulu><head>Revision of the Commentary on the Flower Ornament Sutra</head>
<lb n="0388a24" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0388a2401">The great master Nagarjuna took up a small portion of the Garland of Flowers, and the venerable Yutian translated it into hundreds of billions of
<lb n="0388a25" ed="J" />thousands of words. In the land of China, all is the body of Vairocana; is not the Eastern Radiance Hall itself the realm of the Flower Treasury? The mounting
<lb n="0388a26" ed="J" />having lasted long, heavenly silk brocades are nearly turning to ashes; as years repeatedly pass, flying squirrels and bookworms are about to feast their fill.
<lb n="0388a27" ed="J" />The Chan practitioner Lang deeply laments this and wishes to shoulder the task of repair; the stinginess of lay households will thereby naturally be broken,
<lb n="0388a28" ed="J" />and he requests that the storerooms be opened and the boxes unsealed. Know that this is a good karmic condition in response; surely, when the form is upright the shadow will be straight, and the planting
<lb n="0388a29" ed="J" />of blessings will return with abundant fruits of merit; responses will surely be harmonious like echo following sound. Reading these few words, who would not gladly offer support?</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0388a30" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Postface to the Dharma Instructions of Chan Master Zhongfeng Given to Magistrate Zhuang</cb:mulu><head>Postface to the Dharma Instructions of Chan Master Zhongfeng Given to Magistrate Zhuang</head>
<pb n="0388b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0388b" />
<lb n="0388b01" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0388b0101">To the northwest of Tong county, about half a stage away, there is a hermitage called Huaiyuan. Within it is a monk called Zhongyan, who
<lb n="0388b02" ed="J" />is my Dharma brother of the same lineage; he has long traveled and inquired of various masters, and has already consented to rest his wandering. One day, by chance,<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0388b0201" n="0388b0201" /><anchor xml:id="beg0388b0201" n="0388b0201" /><anchor xml:id="end0388b0201" />
<lb n="0388b03" ed="J" />he picked up a scrap of paper among crumbling dusty walls and carefully examined it; it was the handwritten Dharma words of the Old Man of Illusory Dwelling,
<lb n="0388b04" ed="J" />left for me to read. I said: “The old master’s complete writings are full of tangled vines—how could this single passage be missing?” It is especially
<lb n="0388b05" ed="J" />absent even from the extensive recorded sayings, which is even more strange, so I have treasured it for a long time. Just then, Elder Xu
<lb n="0388b06" ed="J" />and another lay practitioner came to the hermitage to undertake a seven-day meditation retreat; they joined palms and requested instruction, while my tongue was already worn out and
<lb n="0388b07" ed="J" />my throat hoarse, so I merely used this to respond. The two gentlemen, upon seeing it, were unexpectedly delighted and immediately ordered it to be preserved,
<lb n="0388b08" ed="J" />treating it as if it were jade though it is only stone. Alas! One blind person leads many blind people away.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0388b09" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Postface by the Filial Licentiate, Layman Huang of Sumen, to the Dharma Instructions for Gentry by Old Patriarch Foguog</cb:mulu><head>Dharma Instructions for Gentry by Old Patriarch Foguog, written by the Filial Licentiate, Layman Huang of Sumen
<lb n="0388b10" ed="J" />Postface</head>
<lb n="0388b11" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0388b1101">Old Patriarch Foguog is regarded as the eleventh generation from Linji. Outstanding in the Zen lineage, his insight is transcendent, therefore
<lb n="0388b12" ed="J" />his responses to conditions and teachings are like a bright pearl rolling on a tray, vivid and free, direct and incisive, pointing straight to the essence
<lb n="0388b13" ed="J" />and guiding accordingly; thus his Dharma instructions to literati and officials fill many scrolls, how could they be limited? Now I select this
<lb n="0388b14" ed="J" />one piece, which pierces worldly affairs, intimate and simple, truly well expounding the essential Dharma. Even so, it is still
<lb n="0388b15" ed="J" />a provisional teaching for a certain time, still somewhat lingering on the lips and teeth. Now since the layman wishes to see through the dust of the world and
<lb n="0388b16" ed="J" />become a true master of the household, he must have the swift hawk eye that instantly sees through the ground, somersault in empty space, and break through the enclosures of the ancients
<lb n="0388b17" ed="J" />and painted confines; sitting and cutting off even the heads of reward and transformation Buddhas, he can then seize and block the vital passes of the eight great crossroads, using stick and shout
<lb n="0388b18" ed="J" />of past and present, scolding Buddhas and patriarchs—yet one may still say that Puming does not know good or evil, speaking of long and short, saying
<lb n="0388b19" ed="J" />this and that, binding and engraving people’s good men and good women into the karma of birth and death. At that time, Puming
<lb n="0388b20" ed="J" />can only let you step forward. Even so, there is still a blunt axe, and the handle is still
<lb n="0388b21" ed="J" />in Puming’s hand; if you can utter a truly intimate phrase, it will be handed over to you with both hands.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0388b22" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Inscription on the Diamond Pagoda Written in Blood</cb:mulu><head>Inscription on the Diamond Pagoda Written in Blood</head>
<lb n="0388b23" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0388b2301">Who is Master Xi? He has attained the power of the samadhi of illusion; he regards the body as a bubble shadow and blood as spittle.
<lb n="0388b24" ed="J" />His carving finds no joints to enter, his brush moves like a swift wind; not a single dot is added to the text, not a single stroke is misplaced.
<lb n="0388b25" ed="J" />Thus he writes this sutra, which is also called this pagoda. When it is raised up, the ringing wind resounds on its own, coral brilliance
<lb n="0388b26" ed="J" />glows in the cold of night light; the stone man sleeps with bent arm without dreams, while the bright moon often comes to gaze in silence.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0388b27" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Record of the Crab-Stone Rack</cb:mulu><head>Record of the Crab-Stone Rack</head>
<lb n="0388b28" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0388b2801">A sage suddenly arose, manifesting wondrous auspicious signs; from what mountain’s spirit does this Crab Stone come? With a little skilled craftsmanship,
<lb n="0388b29" ed="J" />it becomes naturally exquisite and translucent, with openings on all sides and water flowing through. From ancient times to now, it has been called the Crab-Stone Rack,
<lb n="0388b30" ed="J" />before names and forms arose there was not the slightest seam; when crab is not seen as crab and stone is not seen as stone, once names and forms arise
<pb n="0388c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0388c" />
<lb n="0388c01" ed="J" />even a tortoise is taken as a soft-shelled turtle.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0388c02" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Inscription for the Sutra Casket</cb:mulu><head>Inscription for the Sutra Casket</head>
<lb n="0388c03" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0388c0301">This kitchen vessel too is named according to circumstance; in principle it is originally empty, yet it can contain the sutras. Though its form is quiet and silent,
<lb n="0388c04" ed="J" />it vividly proclaims and spreads the teaching; I bow in homage to this named vessel, which is indeed the great jewel king.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0388c05" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Inscription on Eyeglasses</cb:mulu><head>Inscription on Eyeglasses</head>
<lb n="0388c06" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0388c0601">When this is picked up, light becomes manifest; every mote of dust across the great earth is completely laid bare and examined.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0388c07" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">Sending off the monk Ke on his pilgrimage</cb:mulu><head>Sending off the monk Ke on his pilgrimage</head>
<lb n="0388c08" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0388c0801">On the distant road yet to be traveled, why worry about a single step of the heel? A broken gourd and ragged robe are utter freedom.
<lb n="0388c09" ed="J" />In the moon one’s shadow is reflected in mourning; beyond things one keeps company with water and clouds. The ladle handle, east or west, long or short,
<lb n="0388c10" ed="J" />shallow or deep at the stream’s head; what is before the eyes is gathered without intent before the eyes. Rice fragrance over a thousand acres of green; cold mist over ten thousand homes in autumn.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0388c11" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="2" type="其他">In response to Su Dongpo’s rhyme on selling new silk in the second month and new grain in the fifth</cb:mulu><head>In response to Su Dongpo’s rhyme on selling new silk in the second month and new grain in the fifth</head>
<lb n="0388c12" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0388c1201">I resent that creation is too unjust; in the human world there is only prosperity and decline. I was born among farmsteads with mulberries and cudrania trees
<lb n="0388c13" ed="J" />and plowed fields of grain; in recent years I have seldom seen full ears, and the granaries are utterly empty. Men and women and family
<lb n="0388c14" ed="J" />relations—how few there are, struggling just to muddle through. In the second month of spring one sells new silk in advance, temporarily to
<lb n="0388c15" ed="J" />patch the mouth; how can one wait for delay until the autumn rent ripens? Even rice seedlings are planted on borrowed new grain; who knows my feelings<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0388c1501" n="0388c1501" /><anchor xml:id="beg0388c1501" n="0388c1501" /><anchor xml:id="end0388c1501" />
<lb n="0388c16" ed="J" />of intense heart-suffering and hollowed anguish? I sigh that past causes have formed habits, and misery rushes on all day without pause.</p></cb:div></cb:div>
<lb n="0388c17" ed="J" />
<lb n="0388c18" ed="J" />
<lb n="0388c19" ed="J" />
<cb:juan n="2" fun="close"><cb:jhead>End of the Recorded Sayings, Volume Lower, of Chan Master Yong from Yuan Lake, abbot of Puming Chan Monastery in Jianning Prefecture, Fujian</cb:jhead></cb:juan>
<lb n="0388c20" ed="J" />
<lb n="0388c21" ed="J" />
<lb n="0388c22" ed="J" />
<lb n="0388c23" ed="J" />
<lb n="0388c24" ed="J" />
<lb n="0388c25" ed="J" />
<lb n="0388c26" ed="J" />
<lb n="0388c27" ed="J" />
<lb n="0388c28" ed="J" />
<lb n="0388c29" ed="J" />
<lb n="0388c30" ed="J" />
<pb n="0389a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0389a" />
<lb n="0389a01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="w"><cb:mulu level="1" type="附文">Biography</cb:mulu><head>Biography of Chan Master Yuan Lake of Puming Monastery in Jianning</head>
<lb n="0389a02" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0389a0201">The master, personal name Miaoyong, style Yuanhu, was a son of the Zheng family of Yanguan; he was born in the Dinghai year of the Wanli reign at the tenth
<lb n="0389a03" ed="J" />month, seventh day, at the hour of You. In youth he disliked meat and fish, and aspired to transcend the mundane; at twelve he went to Xingchan
<lb n="0389a04" ed="J" />Monastery and took Jizhou as his master. At seventeen he shaved his head; constantly reflecting on how there was no way to escape birth and death, he went to pay respects to
<lb n="0389a05" ed="J" />the Old Man Wuhuan of Chexi and sought instruction on the essentials of investigation. He then went up to Jing Mountain to attend the great master Nanming
<lb n="0389a06" ed="J" />master. One day he happened to read the Sutra of Brahma Heaven Asked for Instruction and had an awakening, presenting a verse; Nanming saw it and reprimanded him, and thus
<lb n="0389a07" ed="J" />He did not compose verses. Later, upon seeing Baiyun Duan bring up the Fifth Patriarch, and clearly receiving the descending clear wind, he finally broke free
<lb n="0389a08" ed="J" />and became unobstructed. In the autumn of Gengshen, Nan was gravely ill; he raised Xiangyan’s verse to question the master. Just as he was about to speak, Nan
<lb n="0389a09" ed="J" />Shouwei gave a thunderous shout. When the master again tried to speak, Nan shouted once more; the master then nodded, and Nan immediately entrusted him with
<lb n="0389a10" ed="J" />the verse: “No transmission, no receiving Dharma; no transmission, no receiving mind. It is entrusted to the one without hands, who pulls apart the sinews of empty
<lb n="0389a11" ed="J" />space.” He further instructed: “You must maintain this; in the future, if you obtain even one or half a person, you may continue the lineage of Broken Bridge
<lb n="0389a12" ed="J" />one line, and not fail the entrustment of former worthies.” Then Nan passed away; after the master completed the funeral affairs, he only
<lb n="0389a13" ed="J" />carried his staff and hat, following conditions with a dry and simple naturalness; sometimes by the water or under trees, sometimes alone in Lu hermitage, sometimes leading
<lb n="0389a14" ed="J" />retreating into the rosy canopy, so that people could not fathom him. In the year Yihai, the official Cao of Shicang in He prefecture and others
<lb n="0389a15" ed="J" />invited the master to take the abbacy at Puming; after nearly a year he finally took up his staff and went to Fujian, concealing his traces in the mountains of Jiyang
<lb n="0389a16" ed="J" />for three years. In the spring of Gengchen, the gentry Zhu Lianyue and Huang Sumen respectfully invited him together with the assembly to reside at
<lb n="0389a17" ed="J" />Yunfeng Puming; at that time monks gathered like wheels to spokes, and the master examined and debated them, but none were in accord. In the winter of Xinsi,
<lb n="0389a18" ed="J" />Venerable Shiyu led the lay supporters in earnestly requesting him to open the Dharma, and the master, unable to refuse, ascended the seat to instruct the assembly.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0389a1801" n="0389a1801" /><anchor xml:id="beg0389a1801" n="0389a1801" /><anchor xml:id="end0389a1801" />
<lb n="0389a19" ed="J" />He expounded the unresolved case of Master Nan; both monastics and laity in Fujian all revered him. The censorial official An
<lb n="0389a20" ed="J" />Zhai Huang took leave and asked for a final phrase before departure, requesting the master’s instruction. The master said: “Three thousand miles away,
<lb n="0389a21" ed="J" />when meeting people, do not misapply it.” In the year Renwu he showed illness, asked for a brush, and wrote a verse: “In life it is mistaken, in death it is
<lb n="0389a22" ed="J" />mistaken; the iron lion snaps the golden rope.” He threw down the brush and said “De!” and thus passed away. At that time, the fifteenth year of Chongzhen
<lb n="0389a23" ed="J" />on the tenth month, eleventh day, at the hour of Chen; his worldly age was fifty-six, and his monastic seniority was thirty-
<lb n="0389a24" ed="J" />nine years, with three Dharma heirs. Following his final instructions, his relics were interred in the original mountain, and later respectfully placed in a stupa
<lb n="0389a25" ed="J" />behind Xingchan Monastery. The master’s conduct was outstanding; his frame was lean and pure; his comings and goings were measured; in speech and laughter
<lb n="0389a26" ed="J" />he observed propriety of timing; thus many students looked up at the cliff and withdrew. Even those with a little understanding, he would not readily
<lb n="0389a27" ed="J" />approve. Now I have briefly recorded his outline, so that later readers may know how highly the master was esteemed.</p>
<lb n="0389a28" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0389a2801" style="margin-left:8em">Memorial presented in reverence by junior monk Wujin of Jinming</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0389a29" ed="J" />
<lb n="0389a30" ed="J" />
<pb n="0389b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0389b" />
<lb n="0389b01" ed="J" />
<cb:div type="w"><cb:mulu level="1" type="附文">Stupa Inscription</cb:mulu><head>At Puming Hall on Purple Cloud Mountain in Jianning, Fujian, holder of the orthodox Linji lineage, thirtieth generation
<lb n="0389b02" ed="J" />Stupa Inscription for Chan Master Yong of Yuan Lake</head>
<lb n="0389b03" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0389b0301">The Chan master Jiean Jin of the Dharma hall of Jinming Monastery in Zuili, respectfully, on behalf of his root teacher, Chan Master Yong of Yuan Lake,
<lb n="0389b04" ed="J" />submits the Recorded Sayings and Biography of the Venerable, as well as the Biography of the Old Master Xuanwei written by Layman Liyan, and Gao<g ref="#CB01323" />
<lb n="0389b05" ed="J" />Pavilion Chan Master Xuliangming’s Record of Subtle Expositions of the Dharma Gate, requesting the Daoist of Sweeping to compose an inscription
<lb n="0389b06" ed="J" />for the stupa, in order to record its immortality. It is because in former times the Venerable Yuan and the Daoist of Sweeping, at Bai Zhu Puming
<lb n="0389b07" ed="J" />abandoned monastery, early on met through the Buddha Dharma and lingered together in humble circumstance for more than a day. To be able to
<lb n="0389b08" ed="J" />compose this final inscription—if not the Daoist of Sweeping, who else? Since Master Jie, together with Chan Master Yichuyuan, from
<lb n="0389b09" ed="J" />times of great upheaval and war, traveled thousands of miles back and forth, carrying the sacred relics back to He, and again, together with Fusheng
<lb n="0389b10" ed="J" />Xin and Layman Bai Kai, selected the site and built the stupa at the old Xingchan monastery, thus bringing the matter to final completion.
<lb n="0389b11" ed="J" />Initially, in the case of Venerable Yuan, it was a return to origin; in the case of Masters Jie and Yiliang, it was filial upholding of the root of the Way,
<lb n="0389b12" ed="J" />one may say they were good at continuing and transmitting. The Daoist of Sweeping thoroughly read the biographies and records, and saw the Way of Venerable Yuan
<lb n="0389b13" ed="J" />understanding; further reading the Record of Manifest Subtleties, he saw the practice of Venerable Yuan. An ancient adept said: “When practice and understanding correspond,
<lb n="0389b14" ed="J" />only then can one be called a patriarch. A partial understanding is not sufficient to be a teacher.” As for Venerable Yuan, cultivation and realization were both fully attained,
<lb n="0389b15" ed="J" />practice and understanding both perfectly complete; therefore it would be improper not to erect a stele. Moreover, from the former masters Wuqukong, Wuhuan Chong, and Nan
<lb n="0389b16" ed="J" />Ming Guang, the three great Venerables, there are also recorded sayings and biographies showing the transmission lineage, and the robe and bowl have already<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0389b1601" n="0389b1601" /><anchor xml:id="beg0389b1601" n="0389b1601" /><anchor xml:id="end0389b1601" />
<lb n="0389b17" ed="J" />been made manifest, though not yet engraved in stone; therefore one must carefully arrange the full account and combine it into a stele inscription. The text
<lb n="0389b18" ed="J" />reads as follows:</p>
<lb n="0389b19" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0389b1901">The Venerable Yuan of Yuan Lake, Dharma name Miaoyong, style Xuanwei, his father was Zheng Qiru of Haiyan, Hangzhou,
<lb n="0389b20" ed="J" />and his mother was of the Lu family. As a child he naturally ate vegetarian food and delighted in revering the Three Jewels. At twelve he left home and took refuge at Jia
<lb n="0389b21" ed="J" />He Monastery Xingchan, taking Jizhou as his master; at seventeen he shaved his head and immediately knew there was a matter beyond the summit. At that time
<lb n="0389b22" ed="J" />in the year Wushen, Chan Master Nanming Guang, who had received the Dharma from Chan Master Wuhuan Chong, had originally also
<lb n="0389b23" ed="J" />shaved at Xingchan Monastery; just then he was returning with his staff from Jing Mountain to his former temple. The master, upon seeing him, aspired inwardly and said:
<lb n="0389b24" ed="J" />“At last I have found my place of refuge.” He then followed him to Yunqi to receive full ordination. Nanming returned to Jing
<lb n="0389b25" ed="J" />Mountain, and the master then hurried to Chexi to pay respects to the Old Master Wuhuan and seek instruction, investigating the essential points of Chan. In the following spring,
<lb n="0389b26" ed="J" />Nanming and the other masters of Wengu established a meditation retreat at Jing Mountain; the master attended the evening session and heard the raising of the osmanthus
<lb n="0389b27" ed="J" />incense case; from then on he exerted himself with such determination that he forgot sleep and food. That autumn, Jing Mountain invited Wuhuan of Chexi to preside over the Dharma,
<lb n="0389b28" ed="J" />but within a year Wuhuan showed illness and descended the mountain, appointing Nanming to succeed him; his exhortations became even more intense. One night the master
<lb n="0389b29" ed="J" />read the Commentary on the Brahma Heaven Sutra of Vimalakirti and gained insight, immediately presenting a verse on no-birth: “Who can smash iron walls and silver mountains,
<lb n="0389b30" ed="J" />daring to break them? The thief-like body suddenly presses forward; we look at each other and realize we were old acquaintances. At that instant, shame and confusion
<pb n="0389c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0389c" />
<lb n="0389c01" ed="J" />turn into smiling faces.” He also said: “Through countless kalpas of hardship, the scenery has flowed on until this very day; music and
<lb n="0389c02" ed="J" />song, carriages and horses, the gates like a market; yet the inner courtyard remains locked in silence.” Nan read it and sharply reprimanded him,
<lb n="0389c03" ed="J" />whereupon he vowed never again to compose verses, and to hold only to his original topic of investigation. In the winter of Xinhai, the master together with Great Master Xueqiao Xin
<lb n="0389c04" ed="J" />were sitting around the stove when Xue said: “What is the meaning of a snow lion facing the fire?” The master said: “Dew.” Xue nodded in approval.
<lb n="0389c05" ed="J" />In the year Renzi, the master was on the meditation platform, increasingly resolute and deeply mindful of birth and death. After each sitting of incense, when he saw the divided meal
<lb n="0389c06" ed="J" />offerings, he would choke and be unable to swallow, and would withdraw behind his seat. In the year Guichou, Nan descended the mountain and closed himself in seclusion at Gaoting Yongqing
<lb n="0389c07" ed="J" />Monastery. The master guarded the retreat for four years without the slightest slackness. At that time Venerable Yunmen Zhan opened a Dharma hall at
<lb n="0389c08" ed="J" />the Eastern Pagoda of Jiahe; the master went to visit and asked: “There is no Dharma before the eyes, yet the meaning is in what is before the eyes—how is this to be understood?”
<lb n="0389c09" ed="J" />Zhan said: “I hear your teacher is about to leave seclusion?” The master said: “If it is not a Dharma before the eyes, and not something within the reach of eyes and ears,
<lb n="0389c10" ed="J" />then how is it?” Zhan bowed and said: “Please leave; I wish to enter quiet sitting.” The master then withdrew.<note place="inline">丙辰</note>
<lb n="0389c11" ed="J" />At Longju a meditation session was established, and Nan was invited out of seclusion to preside. At that time Chan Master Shiyu Fang was studying under Nanming,
<lb n="0389c12" ed="J" />and the master traveled with him to Baixia and Hecheng, where they were closely in accord. In the autumn of Wuwu, Nan fell ill; the master served him as attendant, preparing medicine and decoctions
<lb n="0389c13" ed="J" />for three years without a trace of weariness. When Nan descended the mountain to seek medical treatment at Jituo Hermitage in Hecheng, one day he raised
<lb n="0389c14" ed="J" />Xiangyan’s verse to question the master; as the master was about to answer, Nan shouted, and when he tried again to speak, Nan shouted once more; the master
<lb n="0389c15" ed="J" />nodded and shed tears. Nan then entrusted him with a verse: “No transmission, no receiving Dharma; no transmission, no receiving mind;
<lb n="0389c16" ed="J" />it is entrusted to the one without hands, who snaps the sinews of empty space.” He further instructed: “You must diligently maintain it; in the future
<lb n="0389c17" ed="J" />if you obtain even one or half a person, you will not fail the entrustment of former worthies.” Soon after, Nan passed away. This was the moment when the great master Yuan
<lb n="0389c18" ed="J" />received Dharma in the inner chamber through encounter and realization. As for the lineage and teaching sayings handed down from above that can be systematically recorded,
<lb n="0389c19" ed="J" />It is from Chan Master Duanqiao Lun that this line of transmission first branches off. Duanqiao and Xueyan Qin both came from Master Wuzhun Fan
<lb n="0389c20" ed="J" />Chan Master’s gate; both are descendants of the Linji lineage, all tied to the Buddha and Patriarchs’ life of wisdom, not a matter of side or main, nor of severed
<lb n="0389c21" ed="J" />or continuation that could admit partial views. From Wuzhun’s transmission to Duanqiao, the Dharma verse says: “True principle is straight as
<lb n="0389c22" ed="J" />a string; what need is there for silence or speech? I now well entrust this, showing that mind is originally without attainment.” Duanqiao transmitted to Fang
<lb n="0389c23" ed="J" />Shan Bao, and down to Wuqu Kong, there are ten generations of transmission verses, fully recorded in the Record of the Lamp, with no
<lb n="0389c24" ed="J" />Wuqu entrusted Wuhuan Chong, saying: “The master transmits the lineage of the Flower Picking, showing me the Dharma of the subtle smile, and personally hands it down to
<lb n="0389c25" ed="J" />you, to uphold and offer it throughout all dust realms.” Wuhuan entrusted Nanming Guang, saying: “To attain the source is to have nothing attained; transmission is also
<lb n="0389c26" ed="J" />nothing to transmit. Now I entrust the Dharma of no transmission; east and west share the same sky.” This is the lineage of Dharma transmission received by the great master Yuan from above.
<lb n="0389c27" ed="J" />As for the source of the Dharma; regarding the master’s conduct after inheriting the Dharma, he skillfully concealed throughout the entire course of hidden
<lb n="0389c28" ed="J" />guidance and secret practice, there is still more that can be recorded. When the master’s teacher Nan passed away, after completing the posthumous affairs, though he had received
<lb n="0389c29" ed="J" />heavy entrustment, he never fully accepted it for himself, but dwelt in quiet detachment and indifference, staying in seclusion at Xiawu Mountain for a long time. One day
<lb n="0389c30" ed="J" />he read Yongming’s verse: “An illusory person asks the illusory adept; valley echoes answer the sound of springs. If you wish to know the meaning of my school,
<pb n="0390a" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0390a" />
<lb n="0390a01" ed="J" />the clay ox walks upon water.” Thus he became freely unobstructed. He also read Baiyun Duan’s pointer on awakening at the Fifth Patriarch
<lb n="0390a02" ed="J" />Yan’s episode, and for the first time clearly understood the descending clear breeze. At that time Master Xue, according to an old agreement, invited him to reside at Jing Mountain
<lb n="0390a03" ed="J" />Thousand-Monk Hermitage; the master went there and stayed for three months. One night during the waxing moon while viewing the moon, Xue pointed to the moon and said
<lb n="0390a04" ed="J" />“Where has this half gone?” After a long silence the master said: “Do you understand?” Xue said: “It is still only half
<lb n="0390a05" ed="J" />a moon.” The master said: “Where has this half gone?” Xue again fell silent. The master said: “It is still only half
<lb n="0390a06" ed="J" />a moon.” They both laughed heartily. In the spring of Jiazi he descended the mountain, returned to Xingchan and closed off retreat for two years. Hearing that Miyun
<lb n="0390a07" ed="J" />Wu had opened a Dharma hall, Master Jinsu went to pay respects and said: “I have come specially to have a personal audience.” Miyun raised his fist and said: “Do you see it?”
<lb n="0390a08" ed="J" />The master said: “I see.” Miyun said: “What do you see?” The master said: “Everyone is right here.” Miyun then ceased.
<lb n="0390a09" ed="J" />He was then invited to serve as head of the assembly; after the term ended he retired to seclusion at Lu Hermitage by Longshui, with sparse fences and broken huts, living alone
<lb n="0390a10" ed="J" />for two years. Each day he wore a hemp robe and kasaya, went village by village holding his alms bowl, following the ritual of the Seven Buddhas, teaching with equality
<lb n="0390a11" ed="J" />and transforming beings. At meal times he would always offer to birds, animals, and even creatures of the deep, explaining the precepts; at the two daily offerings to spirits and ghosts, his food was especially
<lb n="0390a12" ed="J" />reverent and careful. The master was often ill and his body could hardly bear his robes, yet he maintained utmost simplicity; when offerings of fruit were presented, he never privately
<lb n="0390a13" ed="J" />partook of them. Even if a few coins’ worth of water or fermented steamed food lasted four days, tea was always reboiled and re-dried, and his feet were wrapped in ragged robes
<lb n="0390a14" ed="J" />left over. Master Liang of Gaoting offered a new foot-wrapping cloth. The master said: “Even the sincere respect of a donor is hard to accept,
<lb n="0390a15" ed="J" />how much less shared clothing?” Liang blushed with shame and bowed again; from then on he also did not casually make new garments. A
<lb n="0390a16" ed="J" />certain master presented incense money in homage, but the master firmly refused. He then moved to Tongyue Hermitage by Yuan River, which is
<lb n="0390a17" ed="J" />now Ruru Hermitage of Chan Master Wanru. In his early years Wan also left lay life at Xingchan and was a senior disciple of the master,
<lb n="0390a18" ed="J" />sharing the same succession of great good teachers with the master, tracing back to Nanming, and the three masters stayed at Yuan
<lb n="0390a19" ed="J" />River for several years; this is the origin of the name Yuanhu. At that time, a group including the Licentiate Xu Zhenhou
<lb n="0390a20" ed="J" />planned to form a practice association. The Chan master urged them with plain and direct guidance, did not engage in unnecessary affairs, and declined them. In the Chongzhen
<lb n="0390a21" ed="J" />years Gengwu and Xinwei, Layman Liyan made great efforts to restore the ruined Baizhu Puming Temple site.<g ref="#CB01323" />
<lb n="0390a22" ed="J" />In the Tianfu era of Later Jin, the site of Chan Master Puming’s monastery had the “Ten Oxherding Verses,” along with
<lb n="0390a23" ed="J" />ten illustrations. The Great Master Yunqi printed and transmitted them; this was the very place where that monastery had been established.
<lb n="0390a24" ed="J" />Liyan specifically sought those with genuine practice and real awakening, mature and steady, to plant the staff and open the wilderness. Seeing the master<g ref="#CB01323" />
<lb n="0390a25" ed="J" />outwardly composed and inwardly detached, and his responses to situations were steady and fitting, he donated funds to build a quiet hut. Local gentry such as Censor Cao
<lb n="0390a26" ed="J" />Shicang, Remonstrator Huang Anzhai, and Official Tan Saoan strongly urged the master to reside there and preside. At that time
<lb n="0390a27" ed="J" />foxes and hares ran rampant, sparrows and mice quarreled; those who loved him urged the master to withdraw far away, while those who disliked him feared he would flee by night.
<lb n="0390a28" ed="J" />The master alone remained untouched by gain and loss, standing firm and unmoved. When the turmoil subsided, he took up his staff and went to Fujian,
<lb n="0390a29" ed="J" />in the autumn of Bingzi year. The master concealed his traces at Jiyang Mountain in Jianning for three years; Licentiate Huang
<lb n="0390a30" ed="J" />Sumen, Zhu Lianyue and others sought the Way and reached him, and led the assembly to the ruined temple site at Ziyun Mountain
<pb n="0390b" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0390b" />
<lb n="0390b01" ed="J" />to rebuild the monastery gate and request the master to spread the teaching; the master therefore named the temple Puming and began teaching there.
<lb n="0390b02" ed="J" />This was not forgetting the karmic connection with Puming of Zuili, and expressed the meaning of manifesting in all places, just as in the past
<lb n="0390b03" ed="J" />he had changed his name to Yuanhu. Not long after spreading the teaching, all neglected matters were restored; the two Chan masters Shiyu and Wanru
<lb n="0390b04" ed="J" />were then both abbotting monasteries in Fujian and successively invited the master to ascend the seat; he also visited Shiyu at Lingfeng, where all the donors
<lb n="0390b05" ed="J" />gathered requesting him to give a Dharma talk. He raised the whisk and said: “Do you understand? ‘Mind itself is Buddha’ is still confused,
<lb n="0390b06" ed="J" />neither mind nor Buddha offers any direction to follow; not mind, not Buddha, not even a thing, like a butterfly weaving through flowers
<lb n="0390b07" ed="J" />seen deep within. It cannot be taken, cannot be abandoned; within the unattainable, thus is attainment—like a dragonfly touching water,
<lb n="0390b08" ed="J" />gently flying. Puming’s way of expounding thus struck the itch of Lingfeng, recalling the one who had left home
<lb n="0390b09" ed="J" />a roaming abode, walking with great ease and breadth; towering and solitary, utterly clean and utterly bare, he trampled down
<lb n="0390b10" ed="J" />the crowns of all sages, holding fast the crucial gate. At times he held firm, at times he let go, at times he held firm<g ref="#CB00576" />
<lb n="0390b11" ed="J" />while letting go, and at times letting go while still holding firm. Do you know that in a sandalwood forest it is nothing but sandalwood,
<lb n="0390b12" ed="J" />and in a lion’s cave there is nothing but lions? Among the assembly, a sharp-witted one stepped forth and said: ‘Puming
<lb n="0390b13" ed="J" />has needlessly exposed the hidden essence of Lingfeng.’ The mountain monk only replied to him: ‘It is only because we once shared the same bed
<lb n="0390b14" ed="J" />that I thoroughly know where the blanket is torn.’” He struck his staff and descended the seat. From the time the master opened the teaching, those who received his transmission
<lb n="0390b15" ed="J" />and continued the lineage were three: Yunfeng Jun, Jiean Jin, and Yichu Yuan. His transmission verse said: “Along the flowing stream
<lb n="0390b16" ed="J" />this single matter has neither head nor tail; I entrust it to the lion cubs, whose roaring fills the great earth.” When the master first
<lb n="0390b17" ed="J" />resided at Puming in Fujian, there was a prediction that his stay would be limited to three years, and it indeed came to pass. When it reached the Renwu year
<lb n="0390b18" ed="J" />in early winter he showed signs of illness and said to the assembly: “In general, those in the Chan community who leave family and cut off attachment and consume alms from the faithful all
<lb n="0390b19" ed="J" />rely on the compassionate light of the Three Jewels. The highest are those who investigate Chan and study the Way; next are those who are diligent in both precepts and discipline; and further
<lb n="0390b20" ed="J" />are those who resolve their mind to practice; the rest are merely trivial and not worth mentioning. I, this sick and decayed one, have also passed through here
<lb n="0390b21" ed="J" />coming and going. Now although wind and fire are about to disperse, I have been able to see through a single matter and not be bound by past conditions, and furthermore
<lb n="0390b22" ed="J" />how would this one matter of the sick and decayed be expressed? Clear wind, geese falling, sound after sound of feathers; autumn rain on parasol trees,
<lb n="0390b23" ed="J" />mountains with lingering veins. Take care.” He then asked for a brush and bade farewell to the protecting donors, saying: “This poor monk once in earlier years was at the ancestral
<lb n="0390b24" ed="J" />court and heard the two words ‘birth and death,’ which are the marrow of Chan. Arriving here, even Chan cannot be obtained,
<lb n="0390b25" ed="J" />and birth and death cannot be obtained either. Now as wind and fire disperse, only Puming Chan Monastery remains; it was originally
<lb n="0390b26" ed="J" />established by the protecting donors, and now I return it to the protecting donors. I trust the entrustment of Vulture Peak will surely not be forgotten
<lb n="0390b27" ed="J" />indeed. Humbly I bid farewell.” He then wrote the verse: “Birth is wrong, death is wrong; the iron lion snaps the golden
<lb n="0390b28" ed="J" />chain.” He threw down the brush, gave a shout, and passed away. It was the eleventh day of the tenth month, Chen hour, in the Chongzhen Renwu year,
<lb n="0390b29" ed="J" />he having been born on the seventh day of the tenth month, You hour, in the Wanli Dinghai year, with an age of fifty-six years,
<lb n="0390b30" ed="J" />and a Dharma seniority of forty-four years. Daoist Sao once said: among those who have received the Dharma in Chan, secret practice is especially important. The Fourth Patriarch
<pb n="0390c" ed="J" xml:id="J27.B196.0390c" />
<lb n="0390c01" ed="J" />after inheriting the ancestral style, kept his mind gathered without sleep, never lying down on his side for sixty years. The Fifth Patriarch also said:
<lb n="0390c02" ed="J" />“The one who receives the robe has a life as if suspended by a thread.” Chan Master Yuansou Duan, when summoned to reside at Mount Jing, for many years the most
<lb n="0390c03" ed="J" />long in duration, even up to his passing into quiescence never once loosened his robe to sleep at night; how could it merely be for inheriting the Dharma and teaching as something superior
<lb n="0390c04" ed="J" />freely at ease and happy in himself? In the Record of Subtle Illuminations it is recorded that the master’s calligraphy was ancient and austere; he once copied the Avatamsaka Sutra,
<lb n="0390c05" ed="J" />and several Mahayana texts of the Prajnaparamita. Whenever paper, brush, or binding materials were needed, he never misused them; scraps
<lb n="0390c06" ed="J" />of leftover paper used for drafts were then burned, and not a single character was seen scattered or wasted; in every moment and every situation,
<lb n="0390c07" ed="J" />it was nothing other than the mind of the ancient Buddhas. This is utterly different from those who neglect small conduct and thereby ruin great virtue. As for
<lb n="0390c08" ed="J" />his power to reverse declining currents, his profound subtlety and hidden silence, and his freedom in coming and going, he is especially a teacher for a hundred generations in the Dharma gate.
<lb n="0390c09" ed="J" />is exemplary. Therefore it is fitting to compose this inscription. The inscription says:</p>
<lb n="0390c10" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0390c1001">Broken Bridge stone, iron within stone; Chexi water, moon within water. Refining stone to mend the sky, yet the sky is never lacking; pointing
<lb n="0390c11" ed="J" />to the moon, the stream is imprinted and the stream is never exhausted. It can make a rolled stone stand for Mount Tai’s peaks, and a drop of water deepen Caoxi
<lb n="0390c12" ed="J" />gorge. Alas! In Xingchan Monastery, generation after generation there are fallen lions buried without yin or yang grave openings. From Che arises Yuan
<lb n="0390c13" ed="J" />Lake, shaking the long source; the bridge connects Puming, shining upon the ancient tracks.</p>
<lb n="0390c14" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0390c1401">On the winter solstice day of the Jiawu year in the Shunzhi reign
<lb n="0390c15" ed="J" type="honorific" />by imperial appointment, Vice Director of the Imperial Academy and Acting Sacrificial Minister, formerly second-class jinshi of the Wuchen year, Ministry of Works
<lb n="0390c16" ed="J" />Department of Works, Forestry and Arsenal Bureau Director, and Vice Director of the Left Court of the Supreme Court</p>
<lb n="0390c17" ed="J" />
<p xml:id="pJ27p0390c1701">written by layman Saoan Tan Zhenmo Pantan, disciple of the Caoxi “Venerable Han” Patriarch, Fuzheng Daoyi</p></cb:div>
</body>
<back>
<cb:div type="apparatus">
<head>校注</head>
<p>
<app from="#beg0375c2001" to="#end0375c2001"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0376a0101" to="#end0376a0101"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0376a0201" to="#end0376a0201"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0376c1701" to="#end0376c1701"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">蝘</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig"><g ref="#CB16270">󳾎</g></rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0376c1702" to="#end0376c1702"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0376c2301" to="#end0376c2301"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">己</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0377a1501" to="#end0377a1501"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0377b0601" to="#end0377b0601"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0377c1301" to="#end0377c1301"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0380c2301" to="#end0380c2301"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0381b0201" to="#end0381b0201"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0381c1601" to="#end0381c1601"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">己</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0382b1901" to="#end0382b1901"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">己</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0383a1101" to="#end0383a1101"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">己</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0383a2501" to="#end0383a2501"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0383a2601" to="#end0383a2601"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">己</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0383a2901" to="#end0383a2901"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">己</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0383b1101" to="#end0383b1101"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0383c1501" to="#end0383c1501"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0383c2701" to="#end0383c2701"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0384b1401" to="#end0384b1401"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0385b2301" to="#end0385b2301"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0386a1901" to="#end0386a1901"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0387a0601" to="#end0387a0601"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">己</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0387b1601" to="#end0387b1601"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">羨</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">羡</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0387c1801" to="#end0387c1801"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0388b0201" to="#end0388b0201"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0388c1501" to="#end0388c1501"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0389a1801" to="#end0389a1801"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
<app from="#beg0389b1601" to="#end0389b1601"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.cbeta">已</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">巳</rdg></app>
</p>
</cb:div>
<cb:div type="add-notes">
<head>新增校注</head>
<p>
<note n="0375c2001" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0375c2001">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0376a0101" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0376a0101">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0376a0201" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0376a0201">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0376c1701" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0376c1701">蝘【CB】，<g ref="#CB16270">󳾎</g>【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0376c1702" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0376c1702">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0376c2301" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0376c2301">己【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0377a1501" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0377a1501">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0377b0601" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0377b0601">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0377c1301" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0377c1301">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0380c2301" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0380c2301">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0381b0201" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0381b0201">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0381c1601" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0381c1601">己【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0382b1901" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0382b1901">己【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0383a1101" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0383a1101">己【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0383a2501" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0383a2501">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0383a2601" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0383a2601">己【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0383a2901" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0383a2901">己【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0383b1101" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0383b1101">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0383c1501" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0383c1501">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0383c2701" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0383c2701">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0384b1401" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0384b1401">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0385b2301" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0385b2301">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0386a1901" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0386a1901">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0387a0601" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0387a0601">己【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0387b1601" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0387b1601">羨【CB】，羡【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0387c1801" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0387c1801">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0388b0201" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0388b0201">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0388c1501" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0388c1501">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0389a1801" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0389a1801">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
<note n="0389b1601" resp="#resp1" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0389b1601">已【CB】，巳【嘉興】</note>
</p>
</cb:div>
</back></text></TEI>