<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cbeta-org/xml-p5/master/schema/cbeta-p5.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cb="http://www.cbeta.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="T47n1987A">
<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
			<title level="s">Taishō Tripiṭaka</title>
			<title level="s" xml:lang="zh-Hant">大正新脩大藏經</title>
			<title level="m" xml:lang="zh-Hant">撫州曹山元證禪師語錄</title>
			<title>Taishō Tripiṭaka, Electronic version, No. 1987A 撫州曹山元證禪師語錄</title>
			<title xml:lang="zh-Hant">大正新脩大藏經數位版, No. 1987A 撫州曹山元證禪師語錄</title>
			<author>日本 慧印校</author>
			<respStmt>
				<resp>Electronic Version by</resp>
				<name>CBETA</name>
			</respStmt>
		</titleStmt>
		<editionStmt>
			<edition>XML TEI P5</edition>
			<respStmt xml:id="resp1"><resp>corrections</resp><name>orig</name></respStmt>
			<respStmt xml:id="resp2"><resp>corrections</resp><name>Taisho</name></respStmt>
			<respStmt xml:id="resp3"><resp>corrections</resp><name>CBETA</name></respStmt>
			<respStmt xml:id="resp4"><resp>corrections</resp><name>CBETA.maha</name></respStmt>
		</editionStmt>
		<extent>1卷</extent>
		<publicationStmt>
			<idno type="CBETA">
				<idno type="canon">T</idno>.<idno type="vol">47</idno>.<idno type="no">1987A</idno>
			</idno>
			<distributor>
				<name>財團法人佛教電子佛典基金會 (CBETA)</name>
				<address>
					<addrLine><email>service@cbeta.org</email></addrLine>
				</address>
			</distributor>
			<availability>
				<p>Available for non-commercial use when distributed with this header intact.</p>
			</availability>
			<date>2025-02-03 09:13:42 +0800</date>
		</publicationStmt>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>大正新脩大藏經</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	</fileDesc>
	<encodingDesc>
		<projectDesc>
			<p xml:lang="en" cb:type="ly">Text as provided by Mr. Hsiao Chen-Kuo, Text as provided by Electronic Buddhadharma Society (EBS), Text as provided by Anonymous from USA</p>
			<p xml:lang="zh-Hant" cb:type="ly">蕭鎮國大德提供，佛教電腦資訊庫功德會提供，北美某大德提供</p>
		</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl>
			<punctuation resp="#resp1"><p>原書標點</p></punctuation>
		</editorialDecl>
		<tagsDecl>
			<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
				<tagUsage gi="rdg">
					<listWit>
						<witness xml:id="wit.cbeta">【CB】</witness>
						<witness xml:id="wit.orig">【大】</witness>
						<witness xml:id="wit1">【原】</witness>
						<witness xml:id="wit2">【甲】</witness>
					</listWit>
				</tagUsage>
			</namespace>
		</tagsDecl>
		<charDecl>
			<char xml:id="CB01223">
				<charName>CBETA CHARACTER CB01223</charName>
				<charProp>
					<localName>composition</localName>
					<value>[口*耶]</value>
				</charProp>
				<mapping type="unicode">U+35BF</mapping>
				<mapping cb:dec="984263" type="PUA">U+F04C7</mapping>
			</char>
		</charDecl>
	</encodingDesc>
	<profileDesc>
		<langUsage>
			<language ident="en">English</language>
			<language ident="zh-Hant">Chinese (Traditional)</language>
		</langUsage>
	</profileDesc>
	<revisionDesc>
		<change when="2013-05-20">
			<name>CW</name><name>Ray Chou 周邦信</name>P4 to P5 conversion by p4top5a.py, intended for publication
		</change>
		<change when="2000-08-10T15:07:55">
			CW (ed.) Created initial TEI XML version with BASICX.BAT (00/01/24)
		</change>
	</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><body>
<milestone n="1" unit="juan"/>
<lb n="0526b24" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0526b25" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0526b26" ed="T"/><cb:docNumber>No. 1987A</cb:docNumber>
<lb n="0526b27" ed="T"/><note type="community" resp="dota2nub">Partial Translation using ChatGPT 5.2</note>
<cb:div type="xu"><cb:mulu level="1" type="序">Preface to the Recorded Sayings of Master Caoshan</cb:mulu><head><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0526001" n="0526001"/>Preface to the Recorded Sayings of Master Caoshan</head>
<lb n="0526b28" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0526b29" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0526b2901">Chan Master Benji, in relation to Dongshan, was as one who simply pours from a bottle. From the place of “going to the unchanging place,”
<pb n="0526c" xml:id="T47.1987A.0526c" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0526c01" ed="T"/>to the way of upholding the great Dharma, he was greatly distinct from the others.
<lb n="0526c02" ed="T"/>Only because he truly proclaimed did people reach true realization. Only what is true is profound, mysterious, and refined.
<lb n="0526c03" ed="T"/>Therefore it is difficult to fully perceive. The world takes him to be level and without lively function or heroic strategy. Alas,
<lb n="0526c04" ed="T"/>superficial people—how could they know that in any age, through truth and falsehood, the Way may flourish or decline?
<lb n="0526c05" ed="T"/>They truly do not understand; hence there are biased words. As for the essential points of the Master’s sayings, they lie in the Three Falls, which indicate the stages of cultivation and realization,
<lb n="0526c06" ed="T"/>bridging different kinds and communicating between ordinary and sage, clarifying the ripeness or immaturity of the Way.
<lb n="0526c07" ed="T"/>What Patriarch Dong said, “The Way accords with people, people accord with the Way; whether old or not old, the essential matter is subtle,”
<lb n="0526c08" ed="T"/>is precisely this. If one knows it cannot be concealed, yet nowadays concealment is indeed abundant.
<lb n="0526c09" ed="T"/>During the Yuanwen era, this record circulated alongside the Record of Dongshan; yet this too could not avoid being obscured by the multitude.
<lb n="0526c10" ed="T"/>In the autumn of the gengchen year, the assembly of monks at Jixiang requested that I compile this record.
<lb n="0526c11" ed="T"/>They carved the printing blocks, wishing it to circulate together with the Record of Patriarch Dongshan, in order to correct the delusions and errors of the times.
<lb n="0526c12" ed="T"/>It may be called a good intention, hoping for good recompense. They also came to request a preface. Thus I narrate
<lb n="0526c13" ed="T"/>the most essential points within the record and place them at its head. I only follow Caoshan’s intention in setting forth his model of the Way,
<lb n="0526c14" ed="T"/>merely giving voice to his meaning. At that time</p>
<lb n="0526c15" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0526c1501" style="margin-left:2em">On an auspicious day in the first month of the eleventh year of Baoli, the year Xinsi, Yinzhi Yue,
<lb n="0526c16" ed="T"/>after washing and burning incense, wrote this preface.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0526c17" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0526c18" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0526c19" ed="T"/><cb:juan n="001" fun="open"><cb:mulu n="1" type="卷"></cb:mulu><cb:jhead>Recorded Sayings of Chan Master Yuanzheng of Caoshan, Fuzhou</cb:jhead></cb:juan>
<lb n="0526c20" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0526c21" ed="T"/><byline cb:type="Other">Collated and edited by the distant descendant, Śramaṇa Huiyin</byline>
<lb n="0526c22" ed="T"/><cb:div type="other"><p xml:id="pT47p0526c2201">The Master’s personal name was Benji. He was a son of the Huang family of Putian in Quanzhou. In youth he studied Confucianism. At nineteen
<lb n="0526c23" ed="T"/>he went to Lingshi in Fuzhou to leave home. At twenty-five he received the full precepts. Soon he visited Dongshan. Dongshan
<lb n="0526c24" ed="T"/>asked, “Venerable, what is your name?” The Master said, “Benji.” Dongshan said, “Say something beyond that.”
<lb n="0526c25" ed="T"/>The Master said, “I will not say.” Dongshan said, “Why will you not say?” The Master said, “It is not named Benji.”
<lb n="0526c26" ed="T"/>Dongshan deeply valued him. From then on he entered the inner chamber and remained for several years. Then he took his leave. Dongshan
<lb n="0526c27" ed="T"/>secretly transmitted the essential meaning of the Dongshan lineage. He further asked, “Where are you going?”
<lb n="0526c28" ed="T"/>The Master said, “To the unchanging place.” Dongshan said, “If it is the unchanging place, how can there be any going?”
<lb n="0526c29" ed="T"/>The Master said, “Even going does not change.” He then went to Caoxi to pay homage at the Patriarch’s stupa and returned to Jishui. The assembly, having heard of the Master’s name,
<pb n="0527a" xml:id="T47.1987A.0527a" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0527a01" ed="T"/>invited him to open the Dharma. The Master admired the Sixth Patriarch and therefore named the mountain Cao. Soon
<lb n="0527a02" ed="T"/>there was bandit unrest, so he went to Yihuang. A faithful layman, Wang Ruoyi, donated He Wang Monastery
<lb n="0527a03" ed="T"/>and invited the Master to reside as abbot. The Master renamed He Wang as Heyu. Thus the Dharma seat greatly flourished.
<lb n="0527a04" ed="T"/>Students gathered like clouds. The Dongshan lineage reached its height with the Master.</p>
<lb n="0527a05" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0527a0501">A monk once asked about the essential formula of the Five Ranks of Lord and Minister. The Master said, “The proper rank is the realm of emptiness,
<lb n="0527a06" ed="T"/>originally without a single thing. The partial rank is the realm of form, with the forms of myriad phenomena. ‘The partial within the proper’
<lb n="0527a07" ed="T"/>means turning one’s back on principle and entering into phenomena. ‘The proper within the partial’ means leaving phenomena and entering into principle. ‘The concurrently inclusive’
<lb n="0527a08" ed="T"/>means responding mysteriously to all conditions, not falling into any existence, neither defiled nor pure,
<lb n="0527a09" ed="T"/>neither proper nor partial. Therefore it is said: The vast, mysterious great Way is the unattached true lineage. Since ancient times the former worthies have regarded this rank as the most wondrous
<lb n="0527a10" ed="T"/>and most mysterious. One must examine and discern it carefully. The lord is the proper rank; the minister is the partial rank. When the minister approaches
<lb n="0527a11" ed="T"/>the lord, this is the partial within the proper. When the lord regards the minister, this is the proper within the partial. When lord and minister accord in the Way, this
<lb n="0527a12" ed="T"/>is the language of concurrent inclusion.” The monk asked, “What is the lord?” The Master said, “Wondrous virtue honors the universe,
<lb n="0527a13" ed="T"/>lofty and bright, illuminating the great void.” He asked, “What is the minister?” The Master said, “Spiritual function broadens the sage’s Way,
<lb n="0527a14" ed="T"/>true wisdom benefits all beings.” He asked, “What is the minister approaching the lord?” The Master said, “Not falling into various
<lb n="0527a15" ed="T"/>different destinies, fixing one’s feeling in gazing upon the sacred countenance.” He asked, “What is the lord regarding the minister?” The Master said, “Though the wondrous
<lb n="0527a16" ed="T"/>countenance does not move, its light illumines without bias.” He asked, “What is the accord of lord and minister?” The Master said, “Merged without inside or outside,
<lb n="0527a17" ed="T"/>harmoniously level above and below.” The Master also said, “In speaking of lord and minister, partial and proper,
<lb n="0527a18" ed="T"/>it is so as not to violate the middle. Therefore the minister refers to the lord and does not dare to speak his name directly.
<lb n="0527a19" ed="T"/>This is the essential of my Dharma lineage.” He then composed a verse: “Students must first recognize their own
<lb n="0527a20" ed="T"/>lineage. Do not mix the true limit with stubborn emptiness. When the wondrous bright essence is fully known, it may cause harm upon contact; strength lies
<lb n="0527a21" ed="T"/>in meeting conditions without borrowing the middle. Speech should be such that even fire cannot burn it; in hidden conduct one must accord with the ancients.
<lb n="0527a22" ed="T"/>Without body yet having affairs, one transcends the forked roads; without affairs and without body, one falls into beginning and end.” He further
<lb n="0527a23" ed="T"/>made the Five Images.</p><p xml:id="pT47p0527a2304" cb:place="inline"><figure><graphic url="../figures/T/T47p0527_01.gif"></graphic></figure></p><p xml:id="pT47p0527a2306" cb:place="inline">The verse says: “One in white robes must bow to the prime minister—this is not strange.
<lb n="0527a24" ed="T"/>Those of accumulated generations of caps and tassels should not speak of times of downfall.”</p><p xml:id="pT47p0527a2410" cb:place="inline"><figure><graphic url="../figures/T/T47p0527_02.gif"></graphic></figure></p><p xml:id="pT47p0527a2412" cb:place="inline">The verse says: “At the hour of the Rat one stands in the proper rank.
<lb n="0527a25" ed="T"/>The bright proper is within lord and minister. Not yet leaving the Tusita realm, a black rooster walks upon the snow.”</p><p xml:id="pT47p0527a2516" cb:place="inline"><figure><graphic url="../figures/T/T47p0527_03.gif"></graphic></figure></p><p xml:id="pT47p0527a2518" cb:place="inline">The verse
<lb n="0527a26" ed="T"/>says: “Within flames cold ice forms; in the ninth month willow catkins fly. A clay ox bellows upon the water’s surface; a wooden
<lb n="0527a27" ed="T"/>horse neighs chasing the wind.”</p><p xml:id="pT47p0527a2705" cb:place="inline">○</p><p xml:id="pT47p0527a2707" cb:place="inline">The verse says: “On the day of first descent into the royal palace, the jade hare cannot depart.
<lb n="0527a28" ed="T"/>Without attaining the meaning of non-action, why are humans and gods so slow?”</p><p xml:id="pT47p0527a2811" cb:place="inline">●</p><p xml:id="pT47p0527a2813" cb:place="inline">The verse says: “Mingled and thus concealing principle
<lb n="0527a29" ed="T"/>and phenomena, the subtle signs are suddenly hard to discern. King Weiyin has not yet understood; how could Maitreya be fully awake?”<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0527001" n="0527001"/>
<pb n="0527b" xml:id="T47.1987A.0527b" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0527b01" ed="T"/></p><p xml:id="pT47p0527b0101" cb:place="inline">When the Master was traveling, he asked Chan Master Guanshi of Wushi, “What is the Dharma-body Lord of Vairocana?”
<lb n="0527b02" ed="T"/>Wushi said, “If I were to tell you, there would then be something separate.” The Master reported this to
<lb n="0527b03" ed="T"/>Dongshan. Dongshan said, “A good topic, only lacking a further word. Why not ask why he does not speak?”
<lb n="0527b04" ed="T"/>The Master then went back and advanced the question. Wushi said, “If I say I do not speak,
<lb n="0527b05" ed="T"/>that would make me mute. If I say I speak, that would make me stammer.” The Master returned and reported this to
<lb n="0527b06" ed="T"/>Dongshan. Dongshan said, “Ancient Buddha”<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0527002" n="0527002"/>。</p>
<lb n="0527b07" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0527b0701">Yunmen asked, “What is the conduct of a śramaṇa?” The Master said, “One who eats the crops of the monastery
<lb n="0527b08" ed="T"/>is.” Yunmen said, “If one goes on like this, what then?” The Master said, “Can you sustain it?”
<lb n="0527b09" ed="T"/>Yunmen said, “I can.” The Master said, “How do you sustain it?” Yunmen said, “Putting on clothes
<lb n="0527b10" ed="T"/>and eating food—what difficulty is there?” The Master said, “Why not say wearing fur and horns?”
<lb n="0527b11" ed="T"/>Yunmen then bowed.</p>
<lb n="0527b12" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0527b1201">The Master instructed the assembly, saying, “Everywhere they all cling to standards. Why not give them a turning word
<lb n="0527b13" ed="T"/>so they leave without doubt?” Yunmen, among the assembly, came forth and asked, “In the most secret place, why is it that one does not know?”
<lb n="0527b14" ed="T"/>The Master said, “Just because it is most secret, therefore one does not know.” Yunmen said,
<lb n="0527b15" ed="T"/>“How does one draw near to this person?” The Master said, “Do not draw near in the most secret place.”
<lb n="0527b16" ed="T"/>Yunmen said, “If not in the most secret place, then how?” The Master said, “Only then do you understand drawing near.”
<lb n="0527b17" ed="T"/>Yunmen said, “Yes, yes.” He also asked, “If a person who does not change comes,
<lb n="0527b18" ed="T"/>will you receive him?” The Master said, “Caoshan has no such idle time.”</p>
<lb n="0527b19" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0527b1901">Because Master Mi arrived and had not yet met him, Mi then sat upon the Chan seat. The Master did not
<lb n="0527b20" ed="T"/>come out. Mi then left. The steward asked,
<lb n="0527b21" ed="T"/>“Why was the Master’s Chan seat taken by someone else?” The Master said, “After he leaves, he will return.”
<lb n="0527b22" ed="T"/>Mi indeed came back and met the Master.</p>
<lb n="0527b23" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0527b2301">Zhiju came to pay respects and asked, “The ancients upheld those of that side—how should students
<lb n="0527b24" ed="T"/>comprehend this?” The Master said, “Step back and return to yourself; among ten thousand, you will not lose one.”
<lb n="0527b25" ed="T"/>Upon hearing these words, Zhiju suddenly forgot his abstruse understanding.</p>
<lb n="0527b26" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0527b2601">Jinfeng Zhi arrived. The Master asked, “What have you come for?” Zhi said, “To build a hut.”
<lb n="0527b27" ed="T"/>The Master said, “Is it finished?” Zhi said, “On this side it is finished.”
<lb n="0527b28" ed="T"/>The Master said, “What about the matter on that side?” Zhi said, “When the day’s work is done, I will come to the Master.”
<lb n="0527b29" ed="T"/>The Master said, “So it is, so it is.”</p>
<pb n="0527c" xml:id="T47.1987A.0527c" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0527c01" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0527c0101">Monk Qingrui asked, I am utterly poor; I ask the teacher to rescue and aid me. The master said, Reverend Rui,
<lb n="0527c02" ed="T"/>come closer. Rui stepped forward. The master said, Three cups of wine from the Bai family of Quanzhou, and after drinking them
<lb n="0527c03" ed="T"/>you still say your lips were not even wetted.</p>
<lb n="0527c04" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0527c0401">Jingqing asked, What is it like when moss grows on the path of mind. The master said, Hard to find one who can speak of it.<note place="inline">Pronounced dao</note>
<lb n="0527c05" ed="T"/>Qing said, Where has it gone. The master said, One only sees the moss growing, and does not know where
<lb n="0527c06" ed="T"/>it has gone. He also asked, When, in the principle of pure emptiness, there is ultimately no body, how is it.
<lb n="0527c07" ed="T"/>The master said, The principle is just thus; but what about the concrete matter. Qing said, As the principle, so the matter.
<lb n="0527c08" ed="T"/>The master said, You may fool Caoshan alone, but what can you do about the eyes of all the sages. Qing said,
<lb n="0527c09" ed="T"/>If there were no eyes of the sages, how could one discern that which is not thus. The master said, Official law does not allow
<lb n="0527c10" ed="T"/>even a needle, yet in private carts and horses pass through.</p>
<lb n="0527c11" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0527c1101">The Master asked Elder De, "A bodhisattva in samadhi hears a fragrant elephant crossing the river. From what scripture does this come?"
<lb n="0527c12" ed="T"/>The monk said, "It comes from the Nirvana Sutra." The Master said, "Did he hear it before samadhi, or after samadhi?" The monk
<lb n="0527c13" ed="T"/>said, "Master, you are dragging me along." The Master said, "You speak too much indeed. You have only spoken
<lb n="0527c14" ed="T"/>half of it." The monk said, "How about you, Master?" The Master said, "Receive it below the rapids." The Master again asked,
<lb n="0527c15" ed="T"/>"The Buddha's true dharma-body is like empty space; responding to things, it manifests form like the moon in water.
<lb n="0527c16" ed="T"/>How do you explain the principle of response?" De said, "Like a donkey looking into a well." The Master said, "Said well enough,
<lb n="0527c17" ed="T"/>but too much said. You have only said eighty percent." De said, "How about you, Master?" The Master
<lb n="0527c18" ed="T"/>said, "Like the well looking at the donkey."</p>
<lb n="0527c19" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0527c1901">The Wayfarer in Paper Robes came to pay respects. The Master asked, "Are you not the Wayfarer in Paper Robes?" He said, "I dare not."
<lb n="0527c20" ed="T"/>The Master said, "What is the matter beneath the paper robe?" The Wayfarer said, "As soon as a single cloak is hung
<lb n="0527c21" ed="T"/>on the body, the ten thousand dharmas are all thus." The Master said, "What is the function beneath the paper robe?" The Wayfarer
<lb n="0527c22" ed="T"/>stepped forward, answered, and immediately died standing. The Master said, "You only know how to go like this. Why not
<lb n="0527c23" ed="T"/>know how to come like this?" The Wayfarer suddenly opened his eyes and asked, "When the one numinous true nature does not rely on
<lb n="0527c24" ed="T"/>womb or embryo, how is it?" The Master said, "That is not yet subtle." The Wayfarer said, "What is
<lb n="0527c25" ed="T"/>subtle?" The Master said, "Borrowing without borrowing." The Wayfarer bade farewell and passed away. The Master then showed a verse, saying:
<lb n="0527c26" ed="T"/>The awakened nature is perfectly bright, the formless body. Do not, through knowledge and views, vainly make near and far. When thought differs, then
<lb n="0527c27" ed="T"/>the mysterious body is obscured. When mind deviates, it is not neighbor to the Way. When feeling divides the myriad dharmas, one sinks into prior
<lb n="0527c28" ed="T"/>objects. With consciousness reflecting in many ways, the original truth is lost. If within such lines one fully understands,
<lb n="0527c29" ed="T"/>then clearly there is nothing to do, like the people of old.</p>
<pb n="0528a" xml:id="T47.1987A.0528a" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0528a01" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528a0101">A monk cited: Minister Lu Geng asked Nanquan, "What is your surname?" Nanquan said, "My surname is Wang." Lu
<lb n="0528a02" ed="T"/>said, "Does the king still have attendants or not?" Nanquan said, "The four ministers are not obscured." Lu said,
<lb n="0528a03" ed="T"/>"In what place does the king reside?" Nanquan said, "Moss grows in the jade hall." He asked the Master, "What is the meaning of 'moss grows in the jade hall'?"
<lb n="0528a04" ed="T"/>The Master said, "He does not dwell in the central seat." The monk said, "When the eight directions come to pay court,
<lb n="0528a05" ed="T"/>how is it?" The Master said, "He does not receive their homage." The monk said, "Then what use is there in coming to court?" The Master said,
<lb n="0528a06" ed="T"/>"Disobey, and you are beheaded." The monk said, "Disobedience belongs on the ministers' side. I have not yet heard how it is on the ruler's side." The Master
<lb n="0528a07" ed="T"/>said, "The privy council does not obtain his intent." The monk said, "Then the whole work of ordering and governing returns
<lb n="0528a08" ed="T"/>to the ministers and chancellors." The Master said, "Do you yet know the ruler's intent?" The monk said, "Those outside dare not
<lb n="0528a09" ed="T"/>discuss or measure it." The Master said, "Just so, just so."</p>
<lb n="0528a10" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528a1001">A monk asked, "This student is sick through and through. Please, Master, heal me." The Master said, "I do not heal." The monk
<lb n="0528a11" ed="T"/>said, "Why do you not heal?" The Master said, "To make it so you cannot seek life, and cannot seek death
<lb n="0528a12" ed="T"/>either."</p>
<lb n="0528a13" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528a1301">A monk asked, "The ancients said, 'I have a great illness, not healed by the world.' What illness is this,
<lb n="0528a14" ed="T"/>exactly?" The Master said, "The illness that cannot be gathered together." The monk said, "Do all sentient beings also
<lb n="0528a15" ed="T"/>have this illness or not?" The Master said, "Every one of them has it." The monk said, "Does the Master also have
<lb n="0528a16" ed="T"/>this illness or not?" The Master said, "Here, no place of arising can be found." The monk said, "Why are all sentient
<lb n="0528a17" ed="T"/>beings not ill?" The Master said, "If all sentient beings were ill, then they would not be sentient
<lb n="0528a18" ed="T"/>beings." The monk said, "Do the Buddhas also have this illness or not?" The Master said, "They do." The monk
<lb n="0528a19" ed="T"/>said, "If they have it, why are they not ill?" The Master said, "Because they are awake."</p>
<lb n="0528a20" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528a2001">A monk asked, "Is not a śramana one endowed with great compassion?" The Master said, "Yes." The monk
<lb n="0528a21" ed="T"/>said, "If suddenly the six thieves come, then what?" The Master said, "One must also have great compassion."
<lb n="0528a22" ed="T"/>The monk said, "How does one have great compassion?" The Master said, "With one sword-stroke, cut them all down." The monk said,
<lb n="0528a23" ed="T"/>"After cutting them all down, then what?" The Master said, "Only then is harmony attained."</p>
<lb n="0528a24" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528a2401">A monk asked, "Do eyebrows and eyes recognize each other or not?" The Master said, "They do not." The monk
<lb n="0528a25" ed="T"/>said, "Why do they not recognize each other?" The Master said, "Because they are in the same place." The monk said,
<lb n="0528a26" ed="T"/>"Then they are not distinct." The Master said, "Eyebrows are not eyes; eyes are not
<lb n="0528a27" ed="T"/>eyebrows." The monk said, "What are eyes?" The Master said, "Go straight and true." The monk said, "What
<lb n="0528a28" ed="T"/>are eyebrows?" The Master said, "Caoshan instead doubts." The monk said, "Why does the Master instead
<lb n="0528a29" ed="T"/>doubt?" The Master said, "If there were no doubt, then it would be straight and true."</p>
<pb n="0528b" xml:id="T47.1987A.0528b" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0528b01" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528b0101">A monk asked, "How is it when, in the Five Ranks, one meets the guest?" The Master said, "Which rank are you asking from right now?"
<lb n="0528b02" ed="T"/>The monk said, "I come from the partial rank. I ask the Master to receive me from the upright rank."
<lb n="0528b03" ed="T"/>The Master said, "I do not receive you." The monk said, "Why do you not receive me?" The Master said, "For fear of falling into the partial rank
<lb n="0528b04" ed="T"/>again." The Master then asked the monk, "Tell me, in not receiving you, is that meeting the guest or not meeting the guest?"
<lb n="0528b05" ed="T"/>The monk said, "It already was meeting the guest." The Master said, "Just so, just so."</p>
<lb n="0528b06" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528b0601">A monk asked, "From where are the myriad dharmas born?" The Master said, "From inversion they are born." The monk said,
<lb n="0528b07" ed="T"/>"When there is no inversion, where are the myriad dharmas?" The Master said, "They are there." The monk said, "Where are they?"
<lb n="0528b08" ed="T"/>The Master said, "Why make inversion?"</p>
<lb n="0528b09" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528b0901">A monk asked, "Why can the grass that has not sprouted hide a fragrant elephant?" The Master said, "Venerable sir,<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0528b0901" n="0528b0901"/><anchor xml:id="beg0528b0901" n="0528b0901"/><anchor xml:id="end0528b0901"/>
<lb n="0528b10" ed="T"/>luckily you are a real hand. How would Caoshan answer?"</p>
<lb n="0528b11" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528b1101">A monk asked, "The three realms are in turmoil and the six destinies are dim and confused; how does one discern the colors?" The Master said, "Do not
<lb n="0528b12" ed="T"/>discern colors." The monk said, "Why not discern colors?" The Master said, "If you discern colors, then you are already dim
<lb n="0528b13" ed="T"/>and confused."</p>
<lb n="0528b14" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528b1401">Hearing the bell, the Master said, "Ah! Ah!" A monk asked, "Master, what are you doing?"<g ref="#CB01223"/><g ref="#CB01223"/>
<lb n="0528b15" ed="T"/>The Master said, "It struck my mind." The monk had no reply.</p>
<lb n="0528b16" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528b1601">The Master asked the disciplinarian, "Where have you come from?" He said, "I was dragging the vinegar vat along." The Master said, "If you come to
<lb n="0528b17" ed="T"/>a dangerous place, then how will you drag it?" The disciplinarian had no reply.</p>
<lb n="0528b18" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528b1801">One day the Master entered the monks' hall and went toward the fire. A monk said, "It is very cold today." The Master said,
<lb n="0528b19" ed="T"/>"You must know there is one who is not cold." The monk said, "Who is the one not cold?" The Master poked the fire and showed him.
<lb n="0528b20" ed="T"/>The monk said, "Do not say no one is good." The Master threw down the fire tongs. The monk said, "At this point
<lb n="0528b21" ed="T"/>I still do not understand." The Master said, "Sunlight shines on the cold pool, bright and yet brighter."</p>
<lb n="0528b22" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528b2201">A monk asked, "Who is the one who is not companion to the ten thousand dharmas?" The Master said, "Tell me:
<lb n="0528b23" ed="T"/>where have all the many people in Hongzhou city gone?"</p>
<lb n="0528b24" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528b2401">A monk asked, "What is the bladeless sword?" The Master said, "It is not made by quenching and forging." The monk
<lb n="0528b25" ed="T"/>said, "How is it for one who uses it?" The Master said, "Whoever meets it loses his life." The monk said, "And one who does not meet it,
<lb n="0528b26" ed="T"/>how is that?" The Master said, "His head too must fall." The monk said, "That one who meets it dies is understandable,
<lb n="0528b27" ed="T"/>but why does one who does not meet it lose his head?" The Master said, "Do you not see the saying: it can exhaust all
<lb n="0528b28" ed="T"/>things?" The monk said, "After all is exhausted, then what?" The Master said, "Only then do you know there is such a sword."</p>
<lb n="0528b29" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528b2901">A monk asked, "Within forms, what is true?" The Master said, "Form itself is truth." The monk said, "By what should it
<pb n="0528c" xml:id="T47.1987A.0528c" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0528c01" ed="T"/>be shown?" The Master lifted up the tray.</p>
<lb n="0528c02" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528c0201">A monk asked, "In illusion itself, what is true?" The Master said, "The root of illusion is originally true." The monk said, "Within illusion,
<lb n="0528c03" ed="T"/>by what is it revealed?" The Master said, "Illusion itself is the revealing." The monk said, "Then from beginning to end one never departs
<lb n="0528c04" ed="T"/>from illusion." The Master said, "Seek the marks of illusion and they cannot be found."</p>
<lb n="0528c05" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528c0501">A monk asked, "I will not ask about mind is Buddha. What is neither mind nor Buddha?" The Master
<lb n="0528c06" ed="T"/>said, "A rabbit's horns need no no; an ox's horns need no yes."</p>
<lb n="0528c07" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528c0701">Asked, "Who is the one who is always present?" The Master said, "Just now you happen to meet Caoshan stepping out for a moment." He said,
<lb n="0528c08" ed="T"/>"Who is the one who is always not present?" The Master said, "Hard to find."</p>
<lb n="0528c09" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528c0901">A monk asked, "Is conceptualizing not a kind?" The Master said, "Even not conceptualizing is still a kind." The monk
<lb n="0528c10" ed="T"/>said, "What is the different?" The Master said, "Can you fail to know pain and itch?"</p>
<lb n="0528c11" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528c1101">Someone asked, "The ancients said, 'Everyone completely has it.' I am sunk in dust and delusion. Do I still have it
<lb n="0528c12" ed="T"/>or not?" The Master said, "Hold out your hand." The monk held out his hand. The Master then tapped his fingers and said, "One, two, three,
<lb n="0528c13" ed="T"/>four, five complete."</p>
<lb n="0528c14" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528c1401">A monk asked, "Luzu faced the wall—what did that signify?" The Master covered his ears with his hands.</p>
<lb n="0528c15" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528c1501">A monk asked, "According to the ancients it is said, 'No one falls to the ground without rising by means of the ground.'
<lb n="0528c16" ed="T"/>What is falling?" The Master said, "To assent is it." The monk said, "What is rising?" The Master
<lb n="0528c17" ed="T"/>said, "Rising."</p>
<lb n="0528c18" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528c1801">A monk asked, "When the son returns to the father, why does the father pay no attention at all?" The Master said, "In principle it is fitting
<lb n="0528c19" ed="T"/>that it be so." The monk said, "Then where is the kindness between father and son?" The Master said, "Only then is the kindness between father and son
<lb n="0528c20" ed="T"/>fulfilled." The monk said, "What is the kindness between father and son?" The Master said, "Knives and axes cannot chop it apart."</p>
<lb n="0528c21" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528c2101">Asked, "How is it when the numinous robe is not hung up?" The Master said, "Caoshan's mourning is complete." He said, "After the mourning is complete,
<lb n="0528c22" ed="T"/>then what?" The Master said, "Caoshan enjoys being drunk."<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0528001" n="0528001"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0528001" n="0528001"/><anchor xml:id="beg0528001" n="0528001"/><anchor xml:id="end0528001"/></p>
<lb n="0528c23" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528c2301">Asked, "The teachings say, 'The great ocean does not harbor a dead corpse overnight.' What is the ocean?" The Master said,
<lb n="0528c24" ed="T"/>Contains the ten thousand things. The monk said, Why does it not lodge a corpse. The master said, One whose breath is cut off
<lb n="0528c25" ed="T"/>does not adhere. The monk said, Since it contains the ten thousand things, why does one whose breath is cut off
<lb n="0528c26" ed="T"/>not adhere. The master said, The ten thousand things are not its function; breath cut off has its own virtue. The monk said,
<lb n="0528c27" ed="T"/>Is there still a matter beyond or not. The master said, Say there is or say there is not, either is possible; but what about
<lb n="0528c28" ed="T"/>the Dragon King pressing his sword.</p>
<lb n="0528c29" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0528c2901">A monk asked, What understanding lets one skillfully answer the assembly's challenges. The master said, Do not present a phrase. The monk
<pb n="0529a" xml:id="T47.1987A.0529a" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0529a01" ed="T"/>said, Challenge what then. The master said, Swords and axes cannot chop into it. The monk said, If one can
<lb n="0529a02" ed="T"/>challenge like this, is there still anyone who will not assent or not. The master said, There is. The monk said,
<lb n="0529a03" ed="T"/>Who is it. The master said, Caoshan.</p>
<lb n="0529a04" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529a0401">A monk asked, What thing in the world is most precious. The master said, A dead cat's head is most precious.
<lb n="0529a05" ed="T"/>The monk said, Why is a dead cat's head most precious. The master said, No one can set
<lb n="0529a06" ed="T"/>a price on it.</p>
<lb n="0529a07" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529a0701">A monk asked, How does the wordless appear. The master said, Do not make it appear here. The monk said,
<lb n="0529a08" ed="T"/>Where should it appear. The master said, Last night I lost three coins by the bedside.</p>
<lb n="0529a09" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529a0901">A monk asked, What is it like before the sun comes out. The master said, Caoshan too once came like this.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0529001" n="0529001"/>
<lb n="0529a10" ed="T"/>The monk said, What about after the sun comes out. The master said, Still half a month's journey behind Caoshan
<lb n="0529a11" ed="T"/>.</p>
<lb n="0529a12" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529a1201">The master asked a monk, What are you doing. The monk said, Sweeping the ground. The master said, Sweep before the Buddha, sweep behind the Buddha.
<lb n="0529a13" ed="T"/>The monk said, I sweep front and back at one time. The master said, Bring Caoshan his straw sandals to put on.
<lb n="0529a14" ed="T"/>come.</p>
<lb n="0529a15" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529a1501">A monk asked, I bring uncut jade and cast myself before the master; please carve and polish me. The master said, I do not carve or polish. The monk
<lb n="0529a16" ed="T"/>said, Why do you not carve and polish. The master said, You must know Caoshan is a skilled hand.</p>
<lb n="0529a17" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529a1701">A monk asked, What is Caoshan's household. The master said, White hair worn all over the head, and on top
<lb n="0529a18" ed="T"/>a single flower.</p>
<lb n="0529a19" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529a1901">A monk asked, An ancient worthy said, In all the great earth there is only this one person. What sort of
<lb n="0529a20" ed="T"/>person is this. The master said, There must not be a second moon. The monk said, What is the second
<lb n="0529a21" ed="T"/>moon. The master said, That too requires you, old brother, to settle it. The monk said, Then what is the first
<lb n="0529a22" ed="T"/>moon. The master said, Perilous.</p>
<lb n="0529a23" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529a2301">A monk asked, How should a student maintain it through all twelve periods of the day. The master said, It is like passing through a land of gu poison:
<lb n="0529a24" ed="T"/>not a single drop of water may touch you.</p>
<lb n="0529a25" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529a2501">A monk asked, Who is the lord of the dharma-body. The master said, To say Qin has no people. The monk said,
<lb n="0529a26" ed="T"/>Is this then it or not. The master said, Cut.</p>
<lb n="0529a27" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529a2701">A monk asked, Intimate with what companion of the Way does one constantly hear the unheard. The master said, Sharing
<lb n="0529a28" ed="T"/>one blanket. The monk said, This is still the master's hearing. What is constantly hearing
<lb n="0529a29" ed="T"/>the unheard. The master said, It is not the same as wood or stone. The monk said, Which is first and which
<pb n="0529b" xml:id="T47.1987A.0529b" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0529b01" ed="T"/>is after. The master said, Do you not see it said: constantly hearing the unheard.</p>
<lb n="0529b02" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529b0201">A monk asked, Who is it within the country that presses the sword. The master said, Caoshan. The monk said, He intends to kill
<lb n="0529b03" ed="T"/>whom. The master said, Whatever there is, he kills it all. The monk said, If he suddenly meets his own parents,
<lb n="0529b04" ed="T"/>what then. The master said, What is there to pick and choose. The monk said, What about oneself then.
<lb n="0529b05" ed="T"/>The master said, Who can do anything to me. The monk said, Why not kill. The master said, There is no
<lb n="0529b06" ed="T"/>place to start.</p>
<lb n="0529b07" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529b0701">The master asked a monk, In such hot weather, where do you go to avoid it. The monk said, I avoid it in the cauldron
<lb n="0529b08" ed="T"/>and among the furnace coals. The master said, How do you avoid it there. The monk said, The many
<lb n="0529b09" ed="T"/>sufferings cannot reach there. The master let it rest in silence.</p>
<lb n="0529b10" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529b1001">A monk asked, When a poor household is plundered, what then. The master said, It cannot be taken completely. The monk
<lb n="0529b11" ed="T"/>said, Why can it not be taken completely. The master said, The thief is one of the family.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0529002" n="0529002"/></p>
<lb n="0529b12" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529b1201">A monk asked, When one ox drinks water and five horses do not neigh, what then. The master said, Caoshan
<lb n="0529b13" ed="T"/>knows dietary restraint. He also said separately, Caoshan's mourning piety is complete.</p>
<lb n="0529b14" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529b1401">A monk asked, Who is it that is always sinking in the sea of birth and death. The master said,
<lb n="0529b15" ed="T"/>The second moon. The monk said, Does he still seek liberation or not. The master said, He does seek
<lb n="0529b16" ed="T"/>liberation, only there is no road. The monk said, When he gets free, what person can receive him. The master
<lb n="0529b17" ed="T"/>said, One bearing an iron cangue.</p>
<lb n="0529b18" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529b1801">A monk asked, Snow covers a thousand mountains; why is the solitary peak not white. The master said, You must know
<lb n="0529b19" ed="T"/>there is a difference within difference. The monk said, What is difference within difference. The master said, Not falling into the color of
<lb n="0529b20" ed="T"/>the various mountains.</p>
<lb n="0529b21" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529b2101">A monk cited this: Yaoshan asked a monk, How old are you. He said, Seventy-two. Yaoshan said, Is it
<lb n="0529b22" ed="T"/>seventy-two. He said, Yes. Yaoshan then struck him. What is the meaning of this. The master said, The first
<lb n="0529b23" ed="T"/>arrow is still passable; the later arrow pierces a man deeply. The monk said, How can one avoid this beating.
<lb n="0529b24" ed="T"/>The master said, Once the royal command is issued, the feudal lords clear the road.</p>
<lb n="0529b25" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529b2501">A monk asked Xiangyan, What is the Way. Xiangyan said, A dragon chanting in a dead tree. The monk
<lb n="0529b26" ed="T"/>said, What is a person in the Way. Xiangyan said, Eyes in a skull. The monk did not
<lb n="0529b27" ed="T"/>understand, so he asked Shishuang, What is a dragon chanting in a dead tree. Shishuang said, It still
<lb n="0529b28" ed="T"/>carries joy. The monk said, What are eyes in a skull. Shishuang said, It still
<lb n="0529b29" ed="T"/>carries consciousness. Again he did not understand, so he reported it to the master. The master said, Old śrāvaka Shishuang
<pb n="0529c" xml:id="T47.1987A.0529c" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0529c01" ed="T"/>makes this kind of understanding here. Then he showed a verse, saying: Dragon chant in a dead tree truly sees the Way. In a skull
<lb n="0529c02" ed="T"/>eyes without consciousness first become bright. When joy and consciousness are exhausted, all traces are exhausted. How can the person there distinguish
<lb n="0529c03" ed="T"/>clarity within turbidity. The monk then again asked the master, What is a dragon chanting in a dead tree. The master
<lb n="0529c04" ed="T"/>said, The bloodline is unbroken. He said, What are eyes in a skull. The master said, It does not dry
<lb n="0529c05" ed="T"/>out completely. He said, Is there anyone who can hear it or not. The master said, Among all the people on the great earth,
<lb n="0529c06" ed="T"/>there is not one who does not hear. He said, I do not know what passage
<lb n="0529c07" ed="T"/>or phrase the dragon chant in a dead tree is. The master said, I do not know what passage or phrase it is; those who hear it all perish.</p>
<lb n="0529c08" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529c0801">A monk asked, What is the great meaning of the Buddha Dharma. The master said, Filling ditches and blocking ravines.</p>
<lb n="0529c09" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529c0901">A monk asked, What is the lion. The master said, The beasts cannot come near. The monk said,
<lb n="0529c10" ed="T"/>What is the lion cub. The master said, One able to swallow its parents. The monk said, Since
<lb n="0529c11" ed="T"/>the beasts cannot come near, why then is it swallowed by its cub. The master said, Do you not see it said:
<lb n="0529c12" ed="T"/>if the child roars, ancestors and father are all finished. The monk said, After they are finished, what then. The master
<lb n="0529c13" ed="T"/>said, The whole body returns to the father. The monk said, When the ancestors are finished, where does the father return. The master
<lb n="0529c14" ed="T"/>said, That place too is finished. The monk said, Earlier why did you say the whole body returns to the father. The master
<lb n="0529c15" ed="T"/>said, It is like a prince who can accomplish the affairs of a whole kingdom. He also said, Reverend, in this matter
<lb n="0529c16" ed="T"/>you must not become isolated and stuck; you must rub a few more flowers onto the dead tree.</p>
<lb n="0529c17" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529c1701">A monk asked, When right and wrong arise in confusion and one loses the mind, what then. The master said, Cut, cut.</p>
<lb n="0529c18" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529c1801">The master read the Dharma-body verse composed by Dushun and Layman Fu, and then said, I do not wish
<lb n="0529c19" ed="T"/>to speak that way. The disciples asked him to compose another. He then composed a verse and also annotated
<lb n="0529c20" ed="T"/>it. Its words say: He is originally not I; I am originally not he. If he<note place="inline">Not me</note><note place="inline">Not him</note>
<lb n="0529c21" ed="T"/>has no me, then he dies. If I have no he, then I remain. If he is like me, he is Buddha.<note place="inline">I rely on you to bring it to life</note><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0529003" n="0529003"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0529003" n="0529003"/><anchor xml:id="beg0529003" n="0529003"/><anchor xml:id="end0529003"/><note place="inline">There is nothing separate</note>
<lb n="0529c22" ed="T"/>If I am like he, then I am a donkey. I do not eat the Empty King's stipend. Why<note place="inline">In any case, it is not Buddha</note><note place="inline">Neither of the two is established</note><note place="inline">If you encounter imperial food, you must spit it out</note>
<lb n="0529c23" ed="T"/>rely on geese to carry a letter. I sing lying crosswise; you look at the hair on the back. It may seem like the Song of White Snow, yet I still fear it is a Ba song.<note place="inline">No letter came through</note><note place="inline">Sung for the letter</note><note place="inline">Not with
<lb n="0529c24" ed="T"/>Similar to you</note><note place="inline">I would have said it was white snow</note><note place="inline">In this transmission, this line has no note</note></p>
<lb n="0529c25" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529c2501">The master gave a saying: There is a person who, from the edge of a ten-thousand-zhang cliff, leaps and drops straight down. This
<lb n="0529c26" ed="T"/>is what kind of person. The assembly had no reply. Daoyan came forth and said, Not existing. The master said, Not existing
<lb n="0529c27" ed="T"/>what exactly. Yan said, Only then can one fall and not shatter. The master deeply approved him.</p>
<lb n="0529c28" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0529c2801">A monk cited this: One day Xiyuan was heating bath water himself. A monk asked, Why not have a novice do it.
<lb n="0529c29" ed="T"/>Xiyuan clapped his hands three times. Asked about this, the master said, It is all the same, clapping and patting the hands.
<pb n="0530a" xml:id="T47.1987A.0530a" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0530a01" ed="T"/>Yet among them Xiyuan is extraordinary. Juzhi's one-finger Chan was because, at the point of undertaking it,
<lb n="0530a02" ed="T"/>it was not fully appropriate. The monk then asked the master, Is not Xiyuan's hand-clapping a matter on the level of slaves and maidservants.
<lb n="0530a03" ed="T"/>The master said, Yes. He said, Is there a matter beyond this or not. The master said, There is.
<lb n="0530a04" ed="T"/>He said, What is the matter beyond. The master shouted, You slave and maid.</p>
<lb n="0530a05" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0530a0501">The commander of Nanzhou, King Zhong of Nanping, elegantly heard that the master had the Way and with full courtesy invited him. He did not
<lb n="0530a06" ed="T"/>go, but only wrote out Damei's verse, saying: A ruined dead tree leans in the cold forest. How many times has it met
<lb n="0530a07" ed="T"/>spring without changing its heart. Woodcutters see it and still do not look back. Why should the people of Ying bitterly pursue
<lb n="0530a08" ed="T"/>and seek it. He sent it back by the messenger and in the end did not go.</p>
<lb n="0530a09" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0530a0901">The master composed a verse on the four prohibitions, saying: Do not travel the road of mind’s activity. Do not hang on the original robe. Why
<lb n="0530a10" ed="T"/>must it be exactly thus? Most of all avoid the time before arising.</p>
<lb n="0530a11" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0530a1101">He showed the students a verse, saying: If from conditions you arrive at it, accord comes quickly. If you settle into the substance and quiet down, you gain
<lb n="0530a12" ed="T"/>strength slowly. In a flash it arises, originally with no fixed place. My teacher only provisionally spoke of the inconceivable.</p>
<lb n="0530a13" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0530a1301">He addressed the assembly and said: For those of the sangha under this patch robe, it is necessary to understand through to the matter beyond
<lb n="0530a14" ed="T"/>all this. Do not treat it lightly. If where you take it up is clear, then you turn all the sages<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0530a1401" n="0530a1401"/><anchor xml:id="beg0530a1401" n="0530a1401"/><anchor xml:id="end0530a1401"/>
<lb n="0530a15" ed="T"/>behind your own back, and only then are you free. If you cannot turn them, even if you learn
<lb n="0530a16" ed="T"/>it to the full ten parts, still you must stand behind them with folded hands. What big talk can you make? If
<lb n="0530a17" ed="T"/>you can turn it back to yourself, then when any coarse and weighty circumstance comes, you can be master of it all. Even if
<lb n="0530a18" ed="T"/>you fall to the ground in the mud, you can still be master. For example, a monk asked Yaoshan:
<lb n="0530a19" ed="T"/>In the teachings of the Three Vehicles, is there still the Patriarchs’ meaning or not? He answered: There is. The monk said: Since there is,
<lb n="0530a20" ed="T"/>why then did Bodhidharma come? Yaoshan said: Precisely because there is, he came. Is this not
<lb n="0530a21" ed="T"/>being master and turning it back to oneself? As the scripture says, Great Penetrating Wisdom Victory Buddha
<lb n="0530a22" ed="T"/>sat at the seat of enlightenment for ten kalpas; the Buddha Dharma did not appear before him, and he could not attain Buddhahood. The word
<lb n="0530a23" ed="T"/>kalpa here means obstruction. This is called tenfold completion, and also the cutting off of outflows. It is only that the ten
<lb n="0530a24" ed="T"/>avenues are cut off. Because one does not forget the great fruit, it is said: guarding and clinging to it is called grasping.
<lb n="0530a25" ed="T"/>Next, in taking it up there is no distinction of noble and base. I often see in monasteries people fond of discussing one kind and two
<lb n="0530a26" ed="T"/>kinds. Can they actually establish the matter? Such things are only talk about what lies ahead, spread out in the open.
<lb n="0530a27" ed="T"/>Have you not seen Nanquan say: Even if you reach tenfold completion, you still fall short of Teacher Wang by one
<lb n="0530a28" ed="T"/>thread. It is very difficult when the matter comes to this. You must be very careful before you can be clear and at ease.
<lb n="0530a29" ed="T"/>Do not speak of heaven, hell, hungry ghosts, or beasts; in every place, if you do not
<pb n="0530b" xml:id="T47.1987A.0530b" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0530b01" ed="T"/>shift or change, you are originally the same old person, only you no longer walk the old road. If there is delighting
<lb n="0530b02" ed="T"/>in mind, it again becomes attachment. If you are free of it, what is there to choose? The ancients said: I only fear not
<lb n="0530b03" ed="T"/>getting to revolve through birth and death. Tell me, what does that mean? People nowadays just speak of a pure and clean place.
<lb n="0530b04" ed="T"/>They love to speak of what lies ahead. This sickness is the hardest to cure. As for worldly coarse and weighty things,
<lb n="0530b05" ed="T"/>those are light. The sickness of purity and cleanliness is heavy. As for the taste of Buddha and the taste of the Patriarchs, all of it becomes obstruction and
<lb n="0530b06" ed="T"/>attachment. My former teacher said: To stir up a contrived mind is to break the precepts. To get a taste of it is to break the fast. Now
<lb n="0530b07" ed="T"/>what do you call taste? It is simply the taste of Buddha and the taste of the Patriarchs. The moment there is a mind of delight, that is
<lb n="0530b08" ed="T"/>breaking the precepts. If you now speak of breaking the fast and breaking the precepts, then right now at the time of the three karmas
<lb n="0530b09" ed="T"/>they were already broken long ago. Coarse greed, anger, and delusion may be hard to cut off, but they are still light.
<lb n="0530b10" ed="T"/>But if it is non-doing, no concerns, purity and cleanliness, this is heavy beyond anything more. The Patriarchs
<lb n="0530b11" ed="T"/>came into the world only for this, and not for you alone. At this time do not treat it
<lb n="0530b12" ed="T"/>as casual. The black slave and white ox practice more swiftly. It is not that they have Chan or the Way. But as for you,
<lb n="0530b13" ed="T"/>chasing in all ways, seeking Buddha, seeking Patriarchs, even seeking bodhi and nirvana, when will you ever stop
<lb n="0530b14" ed="T"/>and accomplish it? All of that is a mind of arising and ceasing. Therefore it is not as good as the black slave and white ox, standing there
<lb n="0530b15" ed="T"/>blank and unknowing, not knowing Buddha, not knowing Patriarchs, not even bodhi or nirvana, nor
<lb n="0530b16" ed="T"/>good and evil, cause and effect. They simply eat grass when hungry and drink water when thirsty. If you can be like this,
<lb n="0530b17" ed="T"/>do not worry that it will not be accomplished. Have you not heard it said: Calculating does not succeed. Therefore by knowing there is, one can
<lb n="0530b18" ed="T"/>then wear fur and horns, be led by the plow and pull it along. Gaining this advantage, you are at last somewhat close.
<lb n="0530b19" ed="T"/>Have you not seen that Maitreya, Akshobhya, and all those wondrous joyful worlds are called by those people of the beyond
<lb n="0530b20" ed="T"/>shameless and lazy bodhisattvas, and also called transformation birth-and-death.
<lb n="0530b21" ed="T"/>One still fears that this is only a small laziness. In the matter that is one’s own proper share, how should it be? You truly must be careful
<lb n="0530b22" ed="T"/>before you get it. Everyone has a ground for a sitting mat. Even a Buddha appearing in the world cannot encroach upon it. If you
<lb n="0530b23" ed="T"/>understand and practice in this way, do not chase quick profit. If you wish to know this matter, even if you become a Buddha
<lb n="0530b24" ed="T"/>or become a Patriarch, just this is what makes you fall into the three evil paths, hell, and the six realms.
<lb n="0530b25" ed="T"/>Though this very thing is of no use, still you cannot leave it. You must become
<lb n="0530b26" ed="T"/>its master before it will do. If you can be master of it, then there is no transformation. If you cannot be
<lb n="0530b27" ed="T"/>master, then it is transformation. Have you not seen Yongjia say: Vast and heedless,
<lb n="0530b28" ed="T"/>drifting about, one invites disaster. Someone asked, What is this vast heedless drifting that invites disaster? He said: Just
<lb n="0530b29" ed="T"/>this altogether is it. He asked: How can one avoid it? He said: Knowing there is is enough. What need is there to avoid
<pb n="0530c" xml:id="T47.1987A.0530c" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0530c01" ed="T"/>anything? Bodhi, nirvana, affliction, ignorance and the rest are all this. Do not try to avoid them.
<lb n="0530c02" ed="T"/>Even worldly coarse and weighty matters are the same. Just know there is, and that is enough. Do not avoid them. To avoid
<lb n="0530c03" ed="T"/>them is to go along with transformation. Even becoming Buddha, becoming Patriarch, bodhi, nirvana — these
<lb n="0530c04" ed="T"/>disasters are not small. Why is it like this? Only because of transformation. If there is no
<lb n="0530c05" ed="T"/>transformation, then you must be free wherever you touch, and only then is it attained.</p>
<lb n="0530c06" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0530c0601">In a dharma hall talk, a monk asked: What is a great icchantika person? The master said: One who does not fear karma. The monk
<lb n="0530c07" ed="T"/>said: What is a person of ignorance? The master said: One who from beginning to end does not awaken. The monk said:
<lb n="0530c08" ed="T"/>Which of these two is prior? The master said: The one of ignorance. The monk said: Why is the icchantika person
<lb n="0530c09" ed="T"/>later? The master said: The one going onward. The monk said: Then the one of ignorance
<lb n="0530c10" ed="T"/>does not depart starting today? The master said: Yes. The monk said: Since he does not depart from today,
<lb n="0530c11" ed="T"/>where does ignorance come from? The master said: It does not dare enter where there is light. The monk said: Then is it not
<lb n="0530c12" ed="T"/>neither bright nor dark? The master said: It is. The monk said: At just such a time, what then? The master
<lb n="0530c13" ed="T"/>said: It does not receive contact. The master then added: There are many kinds of icchantika. One kind is one who kills
<lb n="0530c14" ed="T"/>father and kills mother, draws the Buddha’s blood, breaks up the harmonious sangha, and destroys monasteries. This kind
<lb n="0530c15" ed="T"/>surely receives real retribution and undergoes all kinds of suffering. Another kind also does as above, but this one
<lb n="0530c16" ed="T"/>takes ignorance as father and craving love as mother and kills them. He does not believe there is Buddha, Dharma, or Sangha to be broken, nor
<lb n="0530c17" ed="T"/>a monastery to be destroyed. Yet he calculates that these are attained by karmic mind, and so falls and receives all kinds of false
<lb n="0530c18" ed="T"/>retributions like the former one, though the rise and fall differ. Another kind knows there is one’s own original
<lb n="0530c19" ed="T"/>matter, and calls it father and mother. It is not obtained from outside. There is no cultivation and no realization, neither cause nor
<lb n="0530c20" ed="T"/>result. It is not received from a teacher, nor gained from realization and practice. Not giving rise to a view of father is called killing.
<lb n="0530c21" ed="T"/>Not giving rise to a view of mother is called harming. This is to not dare fail to preserve the whole matter that is one’s own proper share.
<lb n="0530c22" ed="T"/>Therefore it is called killing and harming. If there is even the slightest honoring, weighting, or getting a taste, then one does not truly know there is one’s own
<lb n="0530c23" ed="T"/>matter. Therefore it is called the great icchantika. To stir and apply the subtle power in this way is precisely the family task realized and borne from
<lb n="0530c24" ed="T"/>the highest vehicle of the school. It is meant to cut off the dark path and smash all crooked byways.
<lb n="0530c25" ed="T"/>This is just what the old man of Xinfeng darkly indicated.</p>
<lb n="0530c26" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0530c2601">National Teacher Zhong suddenly called the attendant. The attendant came and stood there. The National Teacher lowered his head. The attendant
<lb n="0530c27" ed="T"/>stood for a long while, then went out. The National Teacher called the attendant again. After doing this three times, he said:
<lb n="0530c28" ed="T"/>I had thought I was failing you, but instead you are failing me. Baizhang cited this and asked Zhaozhou: The National Teacher’s
<lb n="0530c29" ed="T"/>meaning in calling the attendant three times — what is it? Zhaozhou said: It is like a person writing in the dark:
<pb n="0531a" xml:id="T47.1987A.0531a" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0531a01" ed="T"/>though the characters are not formed, their pattern is already revealed. Later someone again cited this and asked the master: The National
<lb n="0531a02" ed="T"/>Teacher’s meaning in calling the attendant three times — what is it? The master said: When the attendant came back the second time,
<lb n="0531a03" ed="T"/>he should have said, I do not believe the master is calling me.</p>
<lb n="0531a04" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0531a0401">Nanquan said: Before the embryo is complete, is there speech or not? Someone cited this and asked
<lb n="0531a05" ed="T"/>Yunfeng. Feng said: Say there is or say there is not, and you get thirty blows. He also asked Zhaoqing.
<lb n="0531a06" ed="T"/>Qing said: Let him speak for himself. He then cited it and asked the master. The master said: There is. He said: Please, master,
<lb n="0531a07" ed="T"/>give a side hint. The master said: With what thing do you hear? He said: Can the deaf still hear or not? The master
<lb n="0531a08" ed="T"/>said: If the deaf could hear, then they would possess both ears and eyes. He said: What kind of person can hear? The master
<lb n="0531a09" ed="T"/>said: One whose embryo is not yet complete.</p>
<lb n="0531a10" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0531a1001">A monk asked the master: The teaching says one phrase can swallow hundreds of thousands of meanings. What is that
<lb n="0531a11" ed="T"/>one phrase? The master said: A needle cannot pierce it.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0531001" n="0531001"/></p>
<lb n="0531a12" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0531a1201">A lecture master took leave of Nanquan. Nanquan asked: Where are you going? He replied: Down the mountain.
<lb n="0531a13" ed="T"/>Nanquan said: First of all, do not slander Teacher Wang. He replied: How would I dare slander the master?
<lb n="0531a14" ed="T"/>Nanquan sprayed water and said: How much is that worth? The lecture master then went out. The master said: Good that he did.</p>
<lb n="0531a15" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0531a1501">One day Guishan called the prior. The prior came. Guishan said: I called the prior. Why did you
<lb n="0531a16" ed="T"/>come? The prior had no reply. The master spoke on his behalf: I also know the master was not calling
<lb n="0531a17" ed="T"/>me. Guishan then had the attendant call the head monk. The head monk came. Guishan
<lb n="0531a18" ed="T"/>said: I called the head monk. Why did you come? The master spoke on his behalf: If you had the attendant call,
<lb n="0531a19" ed="T"/>I feared he would not come.</p>
<lb n="0531a20" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0531a2001">The master cited: A monk took leave of Yaoshan to return home. Yaoshan said: There is one person who lies all over,
<lb n="0531a21" ed="T"/>his whole body red and festering, lying in a thicket of thorns. The monk said: If so, then this student does not
<lb n="0531a22" ed="T"/>Go back. Yaoshan said, You only know to go back. I will give you a fasting formula. He asked, What is
<lb n="0531a23" ed="T"/>the fasting formula. Yaoshan said, Every day when ascending the hall, do not bite through a single grain of rice.
<lb n="0531a24" ed="T"/>The Master said, There was an ancient Buddha who said: a person whose whole body is festering red is simply an ugly
<lb n="0531a25" ed="T"/>and hideous person. No one can come near. There is no place to take hold or handle. He further said, lying in
<lb n="0531a26" ed="T"/>the midst of brambles. It is only said to be in today’s daily use, and still there is no place for handling
<lb n="0531a27" ed="T"/>in the business of guarding and preserving. At that time a monk asked, When the whole body is festering red, how is it
<lb n="0531a28" ed="T"/>then. The Master said, To bear it. He asked, Bear whom. The Master said, Do not let it fester red
<lb n="0531a29" ed="T"/>upon you, Acarya. Again he asked, Between the ugly person and the person all over festering red, which
<pb n="0531b" xml:id="T47.1987A.0531b" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0531b01" ed="T"/>one is heavier. The Master said, The greatly ugly person is heavier. The Master then raised this and asked a monk, One who greatly
<lb n="0531b02" ed="T"/>preserves and upholds, what is he preserving. The monk had no reply. He himself answered in his place, All day long
<lb n="0531b03" ed="T"/>it is behind one’s back, and has never been seen.</p>
<lb n="0531b04" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0531b0401">Whenever Master Judi was questioned, he only raised one finger. Later there was a boy attendant. Because
<lb n="0531b05" ed="T"/>an outsider asked, What Dharma essential does your master teach. The boy also held up one finger. Judi
<lb n="0531b06" ed="T"/>heard of it and then cut off his finger with a blade. The boy, bearing the pain, wailed and ran away. Judi again
<lb n="0531b07" ed="T"/>called him. The boy turned his head. Judi then raised a finger. The boy suddenly awakened.
<lb n="0531b08" ed="T"/>When Judi was about to pass away, he told the assembly, I obtained Tianlong’s one-finger Chan, and in a whole lifetime
<lb n="0531b09" ed="T"/>could not exhaust its use. Having said this, he passed away. The Master said, Judi was crude where he undertook it. He only
<lb n="0531b10" ed="T"/>recognized one function and one condition.</p>
<lb n="0531b11" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0531b1101">A monk asked, Vimalakirti remained silent and Manjusri praised it as good. I wonder whether that still accords with Vimalakirti’s
<lb n="0531b12" ed="T"/>meaning. The Master said, Can you bind empty space. The monk said, If so, then it does not
<lb n="0531b13" ed="T"/>accord with Vimalakirti’s meaning. The Master said, And why would he agree to that. The monk said, In the end, is there
<lb n="0531b14" ed="T"/>any place to return to. The Master said, If there is somewhere to return, then it is the same as those two gentlemen. The monk said,
<lb n="0531b15" ed="T"/>Then how is it for the master? The Master said, Wait until you fall ill with Vimalakirti’s illness, then it may be so.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0531002" n="0531002"/></p>
<lb n="0531b16" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0531b1601">On a summer night in the Xinyou year of Tianfu, the Master asked the steward, What day and month
<lb n="0531b17" ed="T"/>is today. He replied, The fifteenth day of the sixth month. The Master said, All my life, when traveling, Caoshan
<lb n="0531b18" ed="T"/>has only reckoned ninety days as one summer retreat wherever I went. Tomorrow at chen hour I will travel on.
<lb n="0531b19" ed="T"/>When the time came, he burned incense, sat upright in composure, and transformed. He lived sixty-two years in the world, and had thirty-seven years since ordination.
<lb n="0531b20" ed="T"/>They buried his whole body on the western slope of the mountain. He was posthumously titled Chan Master Yuanzheng. His stupa was named Fuyuan.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0531b21" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0531b22" ed="T"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Explanation of Dongshan’s Clear Instructions on the Five Ranks</cb:mulu><head>Explanation of Dongshan’s Clear Instructions on the Five Ranks<note place="inline">Various collations are gathered together</note></head><byline>Recompiled by Ben Guang</byline>
<lb n="0531b23" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0531b2301">A separate selection says: As for what the former master clarified regarding the partial and the upright, and the combined and contiguous, all employs the former
<lb n="0531b24" ed="T"/>master’s original intent. It was not to clarify ranks of meritorious cultivation and progress, nor to involve doctrinal phrases. It is directly
<lb n="0531b25" ed="T"/>a mysterious discourse outside conventions, whose essential point is wondrous and ultimate. It only clarifies the manifestation of the thing itself from above, in hidden accord
<lb n="0531b26" ed="T"/>with the way of the ancient sages. Now I see various scholars interpreting and sorting the former worthies’ intention and measure, and it seems
<lb n="0531b27" ed="T"/>there are mistaken displays. I cannot avoid briefly setting forth their differences. One should be ashamed not to mix up their<note place="inline">Pronounced zhang</note><note place="inline">Pronounced gui</note>
<lb n="0531b28" ed="T"/>functions. Within this there are cases of borrowing rank to clarify function and borrowing function to clarify rank, with many different threads.
<lb n="0531b29" ed="T"/>Function is in the moment at hand. Look at the force with which the words come. Do not fail the incoming occasion. The subtlety lies in apt finesse
<pb n="0531c" xml:id="T47.1987A.0531c" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0531c01" ed="T"/>like this.</p>
<lb n="0531c02" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0531c0201">The upright rank yet partial. Within the partial one discerns two meanings, namely completeness. Sorted rank by rank, it is brought out:
<lb n="0531c03" ed="T"/>It says, The upright rank yet partial means not confronting things. Though not confronting things, it nevertheless possesses
<lb n="0531c04" ed="T"/>A separate selection says: The upright rank yet partial means within the upright, no functioning is partial; total functioning is complete.
<lb n="0531c05" ed="T"/>These are the two meanings. Asked, What is total. It says, The person who has attained and is not dull. In this<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0531003" n="0531003"/>
<lb n="0531c06" ed="T"/>rank, coming is not made explicit. If a Buddha appears in the world, it is thus. If a Buddha does not appear in the world,
<lb n="0531c07" ed="T"/>it is also thus. Therefore thousands and myriads of sages all return to the upright rank to undertake it. Separate
<lb n="0531c08" ed="T"/>selection says: In the upright, the partial is nevertheless fully present. In this rank, above all one must not stir
<lb n="0531c09" ed="T"/>it.</p>
<lb n="0531c10" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0531c1001">The partial rank, though partial, is also complete in two meanings. Within conditions one discerns it as speech within no-speech
<lb n="0531c11" ed="T"/>Rank-by-rank selection says: The partial rank, though partial, is also complete in two meanings, because at the place of functioning
<lb n="0531c12" ed="T"/>there is no fixed exactness. If exactness were fixed, the true would not be in constant use. A separate selection says:
<lb n="0531c13" ed="T"/>The partial rank, though partial, is also complete, because in functioning there is no thing and no contact. These are the two meanings. Though
<lb n="0531c14" ed="T"/>clarified within functioning, in speech they do not injure. Thus all day long speaking is like not speaking.
<lb n="0531c15" ed="T"/>A separate selection says: The partial rank yet complete also fully possesses non-contact within conditions.</p>
<lb n="0531c16" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0531c1601">There are also cases of coming from within the upright rank. This is speech within no-speech. Rank-by-rank selection
<lb n="0531c17" ed="T"/>says: Coming from within the upright rank does not combine with conditions. For example, Yaoshan said, I have one phrase
<lb n="0531c18" ed="T"/>I have never spoken to anyone. Daowu said, Bring it along and come. This is his wondrous understanding
<lb n="0531c19" ed="T"/>attained. As with the words of the Hunan Inspector, there are many such examples. They must be distinguished and brought out, and one must not<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0531004" n="0531004"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0531004" n="0531004"/><anchor xml:id="beg0531004" n="0531004"/><anchor xml:id="end0531004"/>
<lb n="0531c20" ed="T"/>confuse higher and lower. This is called speech within no-speech. A separate selection says: The upright rank
<lb n="0531c21" ed="T"/>coming from within means every phrase is no-speech. It does not establish nobility and does not fall to either side. Therefore it is called
<lb n="0531c22" ed="T"/>coming from the upright. Also, examples of sayings from within the upright include: When black beans have not yet
<lb n="0531c23" ed="T"/>sprouted, how is it. Also the saying, I have one phrase never spoken to anyone. Also such sayings as
<lb n="0531c24" ed="T"/>There is one person without inhalation or exhalation. Also, before the embryo is fully formed, is there still
<lb n="0531c25" ed="T"/>any speech or not. There are many such examples. They are called speech within no-speech. Separate
<lb n="0531c26" ed="T"/>selection says: Coming from the upright clarifies that the upright rank does not involve conditions. There is also coming from within the upright rank,
<lb n="0531c27" ed="T"/>speech within no-speech, as in saying: before black beans sprout; the place from which the Buddhas of the ten directions
<lb n="0531c28" ed="T"/>emerge. And also, I have one phrase I have never spoken to anyone. These phrases
<lb n="0531c29" ed="T"/>must be answered by the respondent accordingly and without angular deviation. If one deviates, one does not know what is there.</p>
<pb n="0532a" xml:id="T47.1987A.0532a" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0532a01" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0532a0101">There are also cases of coming from within the partial rank. This is no-speech within speech. Rank-by-rank selection
<lb n="0532a02" ed="T"/>says: Coming from within the partial then combines with conditions. For example, saying: That which now comes and goes, what shall it be called
<lb n="0532a03" ed="T"/>so that it is right. Dongshan said, Not permissible, not permissible. There are many such examples. This is called
<lb n="0532a04" ed="T"/>no-speech within speech. A separate selection says: Coming from within the partial rank means speech comes
<lb n="0532a05" ed="T"/>from the four great elements and from sound and form. It does not dwell in right and wrong. Therefore it is said: within conditions one discerns
<lb n="0532a06" ed="T"/>this as coming from within the partial rank. Examples of sayings from within the partial rank include:
<lb n="0532a07" ed="T"/>What thing comes thus. Also, when both light and object are forgotten, what thing is it then. Also
<lb n="0532a08" ed="T"/>cultivating samadhi and wisdom equally makes one clearly see Buddha-nature. There are many such examples. They are called speech
<lb n="0532a09" ed="T"/>with no-speech within it. There are also cases carrying function to the ultimate, called coming from within the partial rank. These are hard
<lb n="0532a10" ed="T"/>to distinguish and must be sorted out. A separate selection says: Coming from the partial clarifies that the partial rank involves
<lb n="0532a11" ed="T"/>conditions. The nature of conditions has no substance and all alike return to the upright rank. Coming from within the partial rank means clarifying the body through things.
<lb n="0532a12" ed="T"/>As in saying, What thing comes thus. Also, when both light and object are forgotten, what then is
<lb n="0532a13" ed="T"/>the thing. This class of examples lodges function to clarify rank, as I formerly cited. Again, What thing
<lb n="0532a14" ed="T"/>comes thus. Though this type of saying is attained within conditions, it is not the same as going onward. Again, as in
<lb n="0532a15" ed="T"/>cultivating samadhi and wisdom equally and clearly seeing Buddha-nature, this type of saying too is among my earlier cited examples.
<lb n="0532a16" ed="T"/>Also, as for both light and object forgotten, that is a rule within doctrine and is not the same as mysterious learning.
<lb n="0532a17" ed="T"/>One only needs to bring it out from within those doctrinal rules into the Chan gate’s matter beyond speculative learning. For example, exhalation
<lb n="0532a18" ed="T"/>does not rely on manifold conditions; inhalation does not abide in the aggregates and realms. This saying is wholly
<lb n="0532a19" ed="T"/>function and is not something recognized within conditions. This too is one of my former examples. It also lets the host draw
<lb n="0532a20" ed="T"/>it into the upright rank, saying: There is one person without inhalation or exhalation, making him know there is an upright rank.
<lb n="0532a21" ed="T"/>There are also cases of borrowing an affair for coming from within the upright rank. In this rank, the respondent must from the side of the partial
<lb n="0532a22" ed="T"/>clarify its body. One must not enter the upright rank to explain it. This phrase must
<lb n="0532a23" ed="T"/>be like this: The former master asked a Silla monk, Before crossing the sea, where were you. He had no reply.
<lb n="0532a24" ed="T"/>He answered in his place, Right now crossing the sea, where is it. Also, the former master answered for Elder Shenwei
<lb n="0532a25" ed="T"/>when he presented the staff, saying: Now that it is brought forth, is there anyone who can discern it.
<lb n="0532a26" ed="T"/>Though these examples are recognized within conditions, they are not the same as going onward. If they are not distinguished, I fear later people
<lb n="0532a27" ed="T"/>will gather them into meritorious traces and take them for the matter above.</p>
<lb n="0532a28" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0532a2801">There are also cases of coming with mutual combination and contiguity. Here one does not speak of speech or no-speech. Within speech
<lb n="0532a29" ed="T"/>one must go straight by the front face. Here one cannot avoid complete turning. The matter must turn completely.
<pb n="0532b" xml:id="T47.1987A.0532b" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0532b01" ed="T"/>Still, words while on the road are all sickness. A person must first discern the front face of the phrases
<lb n="0532b02" ed="T"/>and then go on. Speech comes thus. No-speech goes thus. In the house of adepts,
<lb n="0532b03" ed="T"/>there is not no speech, yet it does not involve speech or no-speech. This is called combined
<lb n="0532b04" ed="T"/>contiguity speech. It is wholly without fixed exactness. When Senior Monk Taizhi was nearing death, he said to people
<lb n="0532b05" ed="T"/>He said, "Yunyan did not know there was such a thing. I regret that at the time I did not tell him." Even so,
<lb n="0532b06" ed="T"/>though it is thus, it still does not go against Yaoshan's intent. Look how Senior Monk Zhi was to act
<lb n="0532b07" ed="T"/>as an old granny. Nanquan called this "moving among other kinds." Moreover, Master Mi did not
<lb n="0532b08" ed="T"/>know. In the item-by-item selections he said: "What comes with mutual inclusion is speech-force neither biased nor
<lb n="0532b09" ed="T"/>upright, neither existent nor nonexistent. Like complete yet not complete, like lacking yet not lacking. One only attains the direct face
<lb n="0532b10" ed="T"/>and goes forth. Then the target is not established. When the target is not established, this is supremely subtle speech. The realm is not
<lb n="0532b11" ed="T"/>rounded according to ordinary feeling. For example, the late master in the Manjusri tea-drinking saying said, "Borrow
<lb n="0532b12" ed="T"/>this and see if you can see." It is also like Cuiwei saying, "What do you eat every day?" There is also
<lb n="0532b13" ed="T"/>inclusion within merit-function. It resembles the matter of going upward. At the moment, discern it. As for the point where one falls into pure
<lb n="0532b14" ed="T"/>subtlety, one must know there is something there. If one wants to go, then go. If one wants to stop, then stop.
<lb n="0532b15" ed="T"/>In all ways, turning and revolving must not be crude. As for one deeply in ignorance, it is because of the whole body.
<lb n="0532b16" ed="T"/>This is not the same as an icchantika. An icchantika knows there is something, yet covers it over. Though covered over, it still becomes filial
<lb n="0532b17" ed="T"/>support. One who covers it over does not preserve the patriarchs and buddhas, nor one's own original father and mother. A rotten-red
<lb n="0532b18" ed="T"/>sort of person fails to return and wholly bear it, and does not establish the utmost honored one. One of great preserving-and-trusting
<lb n="0532b19" ed="T"/>is one who pricks the feet and enters the mud. It is no small protection and support. Another selection says: mutual inclusion
<lb n="0532b20" ed="T"/>and carrying-along does not fall into speech or no-speech. Like Yaoshan's "wearing a sword" saying, this is
<lb n="0532b21" ed="T"/>an inclusion-saying. At the moment, look at the force with which the words arrive. Sometimes it goes straight at the head, face-on. Sometimes
<lb n="0532b22" ed="T"/>within otherness it is empty. If this is not subtly understood, then it is a thousand miles, ten thousand miles away. It also cites<note place="inline">line</note><note place="inline">line</note>
<lb n="0532b23" ed="T"/>examples of sayings that come with mutual inclusion, like the Manjusri tea-drinking saying, and "Where has this person
<lb n="0532b24" ed="T"/>gone?" Yunyan said, "How? How?" And again said, "Right now, how is it?"
<lb n="0532b25" ed="T"/>There are many examples like this. Another time a selection said: mutual inclusion does not involve the two paths of bias and uprightness.
<lb n="0532b26" ed="T"/>This one position is cut off from all comparisons. The subtle meaning is hard to distinguish. It is called inclusion, all for
<lb n="0532b27" ed="T"/>clarifying this single matter. How much more so since the upright position is not the same. A scholar's selection says:
<lb n="0532b28" ed="T"/>Asked, "What is the Patriarch's meaning?" Answer: "When a barren cow gives birth, then I will tell you." The selection says this
<lb n="0532b29" ed="T"/>comes from within the upright position. This example of speech absolutely must not be called "coming from within the upright position."
<pb n="0532c" xml:id="T47.1987A.0532c" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0532c01" ed="T"/>It may be called question and answer on the road of dark learning. Both are so. It is a separate route. Again,
<lb n="0532c02" ed="T"/>it must not be called mutual inclusion, for the sake of clarity. Even if host and guest interchange,
<lb n="0532c03" ed="T"/>it can only be called flawed inclusion. Again, asked about the dark meaning, answer: "Like a dead man's tongue."
<lb n="0532c04" ed="T"/>Again, as when asked, "Throughout the twelve hours, what is offered?" and the answer was, "No thing." These two examples
<lb n="0532c05" ed="T"/>of speech must not be called coming from the biased position. Each must be distinguished. As for the "dark meaning" example,
<lb n="0532c06" ed="T"/>that speech-example may be grouped with the Patriarch's meaning. Again, as in "Throughout the twelve hours, what
<lb n="0532c07" ed="T"/>is offered?" answer: "No thing." This example of speech may be grouped with merit-function. These two
<lb n="0532c08" ed="T"/>examples must not be called either the biased position or inclusion. This was already clearly refuted before.
<lb n="0532c09" ed="T"/>They are "borrowing function to clarify position" and "borrowing position to clarify function," the same as this. Again, "alone released
<lb n="0532c10" ed="T"/>beyond things, rising before the multitude of sages" is called the upright position, yet complete. In truth, it bends the upright position.
<lb n="0532c11" ed="T"/>This example is such that the traces remain after the ancients spoke it. It still has not attained no-speech within speech.
<lb n="0532c12" ed="T"/>Therefore this is again called not the upright position, because within the speech there is speech. This may
<lb n="0532c13" ed="T"/>be called flawed inclusion, because within the speech there is speech. It must not be called mutually
<lb n="0532c14" ed="T"/>inclusive carrying-along. As for what comes with mutual carrying and inclusion, it must be just like the Manjusri tea-drinking saying,
<lb n="0532c15" ed="T"/>and the late master's reply to Yunyan's hoeing-ginger saying, and Master An's dharma-hall saying, and
<lb n="0532c16" ed="T"/>Yaoshan's patched-robe monk washing the Buddha saying. Among these, the finest inclusion is none beyond Yaoshan's
<lb n="0532c17" ed="T"/>reply to Yunyan's "wearing a sword" saying. And when Baizhang descended the hall, as the assembly was about to disperse but had not yet dispersed,
<lb n="0532c18" ed="T"/>Suo said, "What is this?" Yaoshan heard these words from afar and said, "Here." Then one can speak of
<lb n="0532c19" ed="T"/>hidden-head inclusion: borrowing function to clarify the thing, borrowing the thing to clarify function, borrowing transgression to clarify function, borrowing
<lb n="0532c20" ed="T"/>function to clarify transgression, and the like. As for what was brought out by Yaoshan, Xinfeng, and the various worthies before them,
<lb n="0532c21" ed="T"/>it surpasses and enters the upright position. These are dark-discourse, extraordinary phrases already. Next, when it comes to those with only slight
<lb n="0532c22" ed="T"/>attainment of power, then for the moment draw it into the upright position. This kind of example I often use. Because I, due to
<lb n="0532c23" ed="T"/>the many affairs of abbacy, cannot go into fine detail, I have only roughly clarified a small portion. All of you
<lb n="0532c24" ed="T"/>should not lightly treat this with contempt. If there are further doubts about inclusion, they should soon be settled. You must simply
<lb n="0532c25" ed="T"/>exert strength in practice so that it does not cease through future ages. This matter must not be negligently divulged. If
<lb n="0532c26" ed="T"/>you meet one of pure reflection, that is a rare vessel; it also should not be concealed.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0532001" n="0532001"/></p></cb:div>
<lb n="0532c27" ed="T"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Verses on each position, with notes and separate selections</cb:mulu><head>Verses on each position, with notes and separate selections</head>
<lb n="0532c28" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0532c2801">Bias within the upright. Selection says: a clever head in the dark.</p>
<lb n="0532c29" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0532c2901">At the third watch, early in the night, before moonlight. Selection says: discern it when black and white have not yet met.
<pb n="0533a" xml:id="T47.1987A.0533a" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0533a01" ed="T"/>Again it says: when the sprout has not yet emerged. Another separate selection says: right now, what
<lb n="0533a02" ed="T"/>time is it? Again it says: here there is no sun or moon; one does not speak of before or after.</p>
<lb n="0533a03" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533a0301">Do not blame us for meeting and not recognizing one another. Selection says: forgotten. Again it says: reached.
<lb n="0533a04" ed="T"/>Another separate selection says: from what kalpa did this estrangement come? If so, then depart with folded hands.</p>
<lb n="0533a05" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533a0501">Faintly, there is still a lingering of former grace. Selection says: these two lines are one meaning, yet in the end they are not
<lb n="0533a06" ed="T"/>alike. Again it says: if complete, then one cannot deceive oneself. Another separate selection says: today
<lb n="0533a07" ed="T"/>what is weighty? Again it says: thus.</p>
<lb n="0533a08" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533a0801">The upright within bias. Selection says: understanding within conditions.</p>
<lb n="0533a09" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533a0901">A senile old woman at dawn meets an ancient mirror. Selection says: exposed. Just now she remembered again.
<lb n="0533a10" ed="T"/>Another separate selection says: what kind of appearance is this? Again it says: if so, then no separate form is displayed
<lb n="0533a11" ed="T"/>at all.</p>
<lb n="0533a12" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533a1201">Facing the divided moon, there is no other truth. Selection says: right now, understood. Again it says: this
<lb n="0533a13" ed="T"/>very thing is it. Another separate selection says: lost. Again it says: if so, then before there was
<lb n="0533a14" ed="T"/>truth, it was a bit better.</p>
<lb n="0533a15" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533a1501">Stop again confusing the head and taking the shadow for it. Selection says: it is not the original head. Again it says:
<lb n="0533a16" ed="T"/>do not take the shadow as it. Another separate selection says: in the end, not remembered. Again it says: if so,
<lb n="0533a17" ed="T"/>then it cannot be changed.</p>
<lb n="0533a18" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533a1801">Coming from within the upright. Selection says: passing through.</p>
<lb n="0533a19" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533a1901">Within the nonexistent there is a road, separated from dust. Selection says: within the no-phrase there is a phrase. Again it says:
<lb n="0533a20" ed="T"/>it comes along together. Another separate selection says: how is the matter from the beginning? Again it says: if so,
<lb n="0533a21" ed="T"/>then they do not borrow from one another.</p>
<lb n="0533a22" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533a2201">If only one can avoid touching the present taboo. Selection says: alongside this. Again it says: already this is
<lb n="0533a23" ed="T"/>beside it. Again it says: if so, then throughout the whole earth there is no second person.</p>
<lb n="0533a24" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533a2401">It still surpasses the former dynasty's tongue-cutting talent. Selection says: not silence. Again it says: even closer than
<lb n="0533a25" ed="T"/>this. Another separate selection says: in the end, no gnashing of teeth. Again it says: such repeated urging is not
<lb n="0533a26" ed="T"/>permitted.</p>
<lb n="0533a27" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533a2701">Arrival within bias. Selection says: coming from within the phrase.</p>
<lb n="0533a28" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533a2801">Two blades cross at the point and do not avoid each other. Selection says: host and guest do not strike one another. Again it says:
<lb n="0533a29" ed="T"/>each does not wound the other. Arrow against arrow braces each other. Pulse to pulse is unbroken. Another separate selection says:
<pb n="0533b" xml:id="T47.1987A.0533b" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0533b01" ed="T"/>they are not opposed as enemies. Again it says: if so, then they do not govern one another.</p>
<lb n="0533b02" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533b0201">A skilled hand is like a lotus in fire. Selection says: it cannot be damaged. Again it says: who is
<lb n="0533b03" ed="T"/>the one who gains the advantage? Another separate selection says: weaker than whom? Again it says: if so, then in the end
<lb n="0533b04" ed="T"/>one does not become a second person.</p>
<lb n="0533b05" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533b0501">Plainly, it naturally has a sky-piercing spirit. Selection says: not obtained from another. Again it says: if so,
<lb n="0533b06" ed="T"/>then it is not borrowed. Another separate selection says: not originally possessed. Again it says: if so, then
<lb n="0533b07" ed="T"/>the self also does not remain. Again it says: not owned by the self.</p>
<lb n="0533b08" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533b0801">Arrival within inclusion. Selection says: subtle interfolding.</p>
<lb n="0533b09" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533b0901">Not falling into being or nonbeing, who dares harmonize with it? Selection says: not face-to-face. Again it says: he is
<lb n="0533b10" ed="T"/>a true adept. Another separate selection says: just right. In discussion, what do you call discussion? Speak it
<lb n="0533b11" ed="T"/>out. It says: ask.</p>
<lb n="0533b12" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533b1201">Everyone wants to go beyond the common current. Selection says: all want to stand out from the ordinary kind. Again it says: what
<lb n="0533b13" ed="T"/>place is there to stick one's head out? Another separate selection says: move and you die. Again it says: if so, then
<lb n="0533b14" ed="T"/>everywhere is lively freedom.</p>
<lb n="0533b15" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533b1501">Folded back together, one returns to sit in the charcoal. Selection says: then it can be known. It is also about to be known.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0533001" n="0533001"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0533001" n="0533001"/><anchor xml:id="beg0533001" n="0533001"/><anchor xml:id="end0533001"/>
<lb n="0533b16" ed="T"/>How should it be? Another separate selection says: you cannot fool him. Again it says: if so, then
<lb n="0533b17" ed="T"/>Luckily, I still have this one.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0533b18" ed="T"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Essential Instructions on the Five Ranks</cb:mulu><head>Essential Instructions on the Five Ranks</head>
<lb n="0533b19" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533b1901">Coming within the Correct is excess. The whole body stands alone revealed, the root-source of the ten thousand dharmas, without blame
<lb n="0533b20" ed="T"/>and without praise. Arrival within the Biased is inner trust. Following things, it is unobstructed; like a wooden boat with
<lb n="0533b21" ed="T"/>emptiness inside, empty and open, free and at ease. The Biased within the Correct is Xun. Space is shattered into fragments; in every
<lb n="0533b22" ed="T"/>place there is perfect penetration, faculties and dusts are thus still. The Correct within the Biased is Dui. The moon in water, the image in a mirror,
<lb n="0533b23" ed="T"/>originally have no arising or ceasing; how could there be tracks? Attainment in both together is doubled Li.
<lb n="0533b24" ed="T"/>The Correct need not be empty; the Biased need not be solid. No turning away, no turning toward. It is also said: the contrivances of mind are extinguished,
<lb n="0533b25" ed="T"/>cut off; form and emptiness are both forgotten. In the end there is no concealment. There has never been any change, still less<note place="inline">This is called the upright</note><note place="inline">This is called the middle</note>
<lb n="0533b26" ed="T"/>any covering up. The whole body appears exposed: this is called the Biased within the Correct. Mountain is mountain,<note place="inline">This is called the biased</note>
<lb n="0533b27" ed="T"/>water is water. No one assigns names; no thing can be compared to it. This is called the Correct within the Biased.
<lb n="0533b28" ed="T"/>Pure, naked, bare, bright and clean; the face and features dignified and stately. Filling heaven and filling earth, alone honored,
<lb n="0533b29" ed="T"/>without a second. This is called Coming within the Correct. Just like the Son of Heaven within the realm, not borrowing the commands of Yu, Tang,
<pb n="0533c" xml:id="T47.1987A.0533c" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0533c01" ed="T"/>Yao, or Shun. Eye sees, ear hears, yet in the end borrows no other power. The ear does not enter into sound,
<lb n="0533c02" ed="T"/>and sound does not block the ear-root. As soon as one turns around inside, amid dust one has not yet carried a name.
<lb n="0533c03" ed="T"/>This is called Arrival within the Biased. It is not mind, not object, not affair, not
<lb n="0533c04" ed="T"/>principle. From the beginning it is apart from names and marks; natural and true, forgetting essential characteristics. This is called Attainment in both together.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0533c05" ed="T"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Three Kinds of Falling</cb:mulu><head>Three Kinds of Falling</head>
<lb n="0533c06" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533c0601">The master said: ordinary feelings and saintly views melt away the mysterious road like gold. One must directly turn and interpenetrate. As for taking
<lb n="0533c07" ed="T"/>the food of right livelihood, one must possess the three kinds of falling: the water buffalo, not accepting food, and not cutting off
<lb n="0533c08" ed="T"/>sounds and forms, just falling away. On whose part is this matter? Selection says: If you wish<note place="inline">Present collation note</note>
<lb n="0533c09" ed="T"/>to know, it is entering among the different kinds, not acknowledging matters on the monk's side. Therefore the ancients
<lb n="0533c10" ed="T"/>provisionally borrowed the water buffalo as an image of a different kind. It is only a different kind in terms of affairs, not in speech
<lb n="0533c11" ed="T"/>as a different kind.<note place="inline">One must look into the four kinds of the different class</note></p>
<lb n="0533c12" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533c1201">At that time Chou Bunna asked: What kind of falling is the water buffalo? He said: Wearing hair and horns
<lb n="0533c13" ed="T"/>is the monk's falling. What kind of falling is not accepting food? He said: It is the noble falling. Not
<lb n="0533c14" ed="T"/>cutting off sounds and forms, what kind of falling is that? He said: It is falling along with the kind. The master also said: If it is
<lb n="0533c15" ed="T"/>a different kind within language, then all coming and going language is still classed as kind. Therefore Nanquan
<lb n="0533c16" ed="T"/>said: Where wisdom does not reach, strictly avoid speaking of it. Speak of it, and horns and head appear. To call it
<lb n="0533c17" ed="T"/>thusness is already change. One must go straight through the different. Right now you must, within the different,
<lb n="0533c18" ed="T"/>speak and take up the affairs of the different. In speech there must be no speech before it is so. When Nanquan
<lb n="0533c19" ed="T"/>was ill, someone asked: After the master passes away, where will you go? Nanquan
<lb n="0533c20" ed="T"/>said: I will go to a patron's house below the mountain and become a water buffalo. I
<lb n="0533c21" ed="T"/>intend to follow the master there; may I? Nanquan said: If you follow me, hold a single stalk of grass in your mouth
<lb n="0533c22" ed="T"/>and come. Selection says: This is the monk's turning-body speech. Therefore it is said: If you intend
<lb n="0533c23" ed="T"/>to approach him, bring a stalk of grass in your mouth and draw near him. This is called undefiled, and only then is one fit to make
<lb n="0533c24" ed="T"/>offerings to him.</p>
<lb n="0533c25" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0533c2501">It is also said: Falling along with the kind means right now, amid every sound, form, and thing, turning
<lb n="0533c26" ed="T"/>the body and not falling into ranks and stages. This is called falling along with the kind. It is also said: The noble falling is this:
<lb n="0533c27" ed="T"/>dharma-body and dharma-nature belong to the side of nobility, yet one must turn away from even that. This is the noble falling.
<lb n="0533c28" ed="T"/>For example, the white ox in the open ground is the ultimate of dharma-body, yet one must still turn away from it to avoid
<lb n="0533c29" ed="T"/>sitting in a one-colored place without discernment. All this is spoken of as matters on the side of cut-off offering. If one wishes to
<pb n="0534a" xml:id="T47.1987A.0534a" ed="T"/>
<note place="inline">Dharma-body white ox</note>
<lb n="0534a01" ed="T"/>make offerings, one must attain this food. Therefore the flavorless flavor is also called the undefiled, which is
<lb n="0534a02" ed="T"/>fit for offering. All other foods touched and defiled are not the food of undefiled liberation.
<lb n="0534a03" ed="T"/>Someone asked Baizhang: What do you take as food? He said: The undefiled is food. Yunyan said:
<lb n="0534a04" ed="T"/>Do not take flavor as offering. Daowu said: Wherever there is knowing and safeguarding, all of it is
<lb n="0534a05" ed="T"/>offering.</p>
<lb n="0534a06" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0534a0601">It is also said: Not accepting food, the noble falling, means that food is a matter of one's own proper share. Knowing it is there
<lb n="0534a07" ed="T"/>yet not taking it, therefore it is called noble falling. Wearing hair and horns, the monk's falling, means not clinging
<lb n="0534a08" ed="T"/>to matters on the monk's side nor to the reward-positions of the saints. Not cutting off sounds and forms, the falling along with the kind,<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534001" n="0534001"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534001" n="0534001"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534001" n="0534001"/><anchor xml:id="end0534001"/><note place="inline">One must look at the teaching on the different class</note>
<lb n="0534a09" ed="T"/>means that beginners first know their own proper matter, and when turning the light back,
<lb n="0534a10" ed="T"/>they cast out forms, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and dharmas, attaining quietude. Then, after merit is accomplished,
<lb n="0534a11" ed="T"/>they no longer cling to the six dusts, falling yet not deluded, letting it be without obstruction. Therefore it is said: The six teachers of the outsiders
<lb n="0534a12" ed="T"/>are your teachers; where those teachers fall, you also fall along. Only then may you take food.
<lb n="0534a13" ed="T"/>That food is the food of right livelihood, and also a matter of one's proper share. It is simply at the gateway of the six
<lb n="0534a14" ed="T"/>roots, in seeing, hearing, sensing, and knowing, not being stained by them. This is called falling. It is not like before,
<lb n="0534a15" ed="T"/>when one feared them. If one does not even take one's proper matter, how much less the rest. Therefore it says: Be<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534002" n="0534002"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534002" n="0534002"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534002" n="0534002"/><anchor xml:id="end0534002"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534003" n="0534003"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534003" n="0534003"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534003" n="0534003"/>
<lb n="0534a16" ed="T"/>careful, careful. Selection says: Becoming a water buffalo, what falling is that? In place of an answer: Not<anchor xml:id="end0534003"/>
<lb n="0534a17" ed="T"/>abiding in the correct position, not discriminating about the body itself, only then is it called the monk's falling. Not cutting off sounds and forms,
<lb n="0534a18" ed="T"/>what falling is that? In place of an answer: Ordinary feelings are exhausted, saintly measures too are forgotten; amid the dusts of sound and form
<lb n="0534a19" ed="T"/>one should not cut off further. Then one may take food. This is called falling along with the kind. Not accepting food,
<lb n="0534a20" ed="T"/>what falling is that? In place of an answer: Thoroughly understanding the true cause, not retaining superior understanding; therefore it is called the noble
<lb n="0534a21" ed="T"/>falling. It is also said: In the monk's falling, activity is not absent, and stillness is not absent;
<lb n="0534a22" ed="T"/>though there is stillness, there is always no stillness; though there is activity, there is always no
<lb n="0534a23" ed="T"/>activity. In this matter you absolutely must know the proper time and season; do not go east or west.</p>
<lb n="0534a24" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0534a2401">Asked: What is falling along with the kind? He said: Not cutting off sounds and forms, yet not losing fragrance and flavor.
<lb n="0534a25" ed="T"/>What are those teachers? He said: The six sense-fields. What is the place where those teachers fall? He said: A field-
<lb n="0534a26" ed="T"/>hut old man entering the village, with eyes, ears, nose, and tongue all lost. What is meant by your<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534004" n="0534004"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534004" n="0534004"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534004" n="0534004"/><anchor xml:id="end0534004"/>
<lb n="0534a27" ed="T"/>also falling along? He said: Preserving. Preserving what? He said: Do not stir or touch it, yet do not depart from
<lb n="0534a28" ed="T"/>sounds and forms. Also Guishan said: After I pass away, I will become a water buffalo. On its left
<lb n="0534a29" ed="T"/>flank will be written one line of characters: Monk So-and-so of Guishan. Tell me, when you see it,
<pb n="0534b" xml:id="T47.1987A.0534b" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0534b01" ed="T"/>what will you call it? There was no answer. Later Caoshan answered in place: Call it a water buffalo. Asked:
<lb n="0534b02" ed="T"/>Does this water buffalo still know how to plow and farm? He said: Certainly. What kind
<lb n="0534b03" ed="T"/>is it? He said: One wearing hair and horns. In the four seasons, what water and grass does it eat? He said: That which does not enter the mouth.
<lb n="0534b04" ed="T"/>What is the water buffalo? He said: It does not certify to sagehood. What is holding a single stalk
<lb n="0534b05" ed="T"/>of grass? He said: Going where hair, feathers, and roots are alike. Is that transcending saints or transcending kinds? He said: It is transcending saints.
<lb n="0534b06" ed="T"/>Asked: What is the water buffalo? He said: Dark and dim, obscure and murky. What is holding in the mouth a
<lb n="0534b07" ed="T"/>stalk of grass and coming? He said: The ancients already said it: go where hair and feathers are alike. It is also said: One stalk of grass simply clarifies the unchanging. It is also said: Patriarchs<note place="inline">Heyu himself stated this as a reply to an old saying
<lb n="0534b08" ed="T"/>What can be done</note><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534005" n="0534005"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534005" n="0534005"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534005" n="0534005"/><anchor xml:id="end0534005"/>
<lb n="0534b09" ed="T"/>and Buddhas do not know of it, yet the civet-cat and white ox do know. Why do the civet-cat and white
<lb n="0534b10" ed="T"/>ox know of it? He said: Simply because they understand nothing at all. Then why do patriarchs and Buddhas
<lb n="0534b11" ed="T"/>not know of it? He said: Patriarchs are attached to the seal; Buddhas are likeness. As for the civet-cat
<lb n="0534b12" ed="T"/>and white ox, what is it that they know? He said: They only know the civet-cat and white ox. What is
<lb n="0534b13" ed="T"/>the matter known by the civet-cat and white ox? He said: It does not come from west or east. It is not obtained from<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534006" n="0534006"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534006" n="0534006"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534006" n="0534006"/><anchor xml:id="end0534006"/>
<lb n="0534b14" ed="T"/>the thirty-two marks. What is the patriarch? He said: There is above. What is the Buddha? He said:
<lb n="0534b15" ed="T"/>A likeness, and off it goes.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0534b16" ed="T"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Four Kinds of the Different</cb:mulu><head>Four Kinds of the Different</head>
<lb n="0534b17" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0534b1701">First is the different kind of coming and going. This means that all sounds, forms, speech, ranks, and levels now<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534007" n="0534007"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534007" n="0534007"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534007" n="0534007"/><anchor xml:id="end0534007"/>
<lb n="0534b18" ed="T"/>and stations abandon the father and flee away, and all of them instead turn back upward to the ancestral father, thereby becoming different<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534008" n="0534008"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534009" n="0534009"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534009" n="0534009"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534009" n="0534009"/><anchor xml:id="end0534009"/>
<lb n="0534b19" ed="T"/>kinds. Also heaven, hell, hungry ghosts, beasts, asuras, and the like are all different kinds.</p>
<lb n="0534b20" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0534b2001">Second is the bodhisattva sharing the different kind: first illuminating and realizing oneself, then entering again into the
<lb n="0534b21" ed="T"/>different kinds within birth and death to gather in others. Though having realized the fruit of nirvana, one does not abandon the realm of birth and death,
<lb n="0534b22" ed="T"/>benefiting oneself and benefiting others, vowing that all sentient beings without exception become Buddhas, while I myself from the very last<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534010" n="0534010"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534010" n="0534010"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534010" n="0534010"/><anchor xml:id="end0534010"/>
<lb n="0534b23" ed="T"/>will become Buddha only afterward. Therefore, if a great bodhisattva of skillful means does not first transform sentient beings, his own matter
<lb n="0534b24" ed="T"/>has no way to be completed. Thus Nanquan said: First cross over there and know that there is, then come back
<lb n="0534b25" ed="T"/>to this side and set your pack in motion. It is also said: A bodhisattva possesses the six perfections and ten thousand practices. The teaching says: If there is
<lb n="0534b26" ed="T"/>even a single sentient being not yet delivered, I will never realize perfect awakening. Vows are boundless; sentient
<lb n="0534b27" ed="T"/>beings are boundless. Practicing and upholding in this way is therefore called the bodhisattva sharing the different kind.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534011" n="0534011"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534011" n="0534011"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534011" n="0534011"/><anchor xml:id="end0534011"/><note place="inline">Below it says the different class within sameness is sameness</note></p>
<lb n="0534b28" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0534b2801">Third, the śramaṇa other-kind means first knowing there is the fundamental matter and finishing it.<note place="inline">Later it says fur-clad and horn-cut</note><anchor xml:id="beg_1" type="star"/><anchor xml:id="end_1"/>
<lb n="0534b29" ed="T"/>One loses utterly all present worldly and holy causes and effects and virtuous practices; only then does one accord with the one body.
<pb n="0534c" xml:id="T47.1987A.0534c" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0534c01" ed="T"/>In this way one is called a person who stands alone, also called the śramaṇa matter of cutting off labels. Only then does one gain the outer and
<lb n="0534c02" ed="T"/>inner, forgetting all feelings; the affairs of the three times are ended. One attains without remainder or leakage, and this is called the Buddha-side matter. It is also
<lb n="0534c03" ed="T"/>said to be pointing to heaven and earth with one hand. It is also said to be fully a great śramaṇa. Turning away from the side of the śramaṇa labels-and-cutting,
<lb n="0534c04" ed="T"/>not entering the various superior reward stations, only then is it called śramaṇa practice.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534012" n="0534012"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534012" n="0534012"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534012" n="0534012"/><anchor xml:id="end0534012"/>
<lb n="0534c05" ed="T"/>It is also called the śramaṇa turning the body. It is also called wearing fur and bearing horns. It is also called a water buffalo,
<lb n="0534c06" ed="T"/>and only at such a time does one enter the other kind. It is also called the matter on the side of form-kind. Therefore
<lb n="0534c07" ed="T"/>the ancients said, head three feet long, neck two inches short. It is just<note place="inline">In the handwritten legacy of the Auspicious lineage ancestors, it does not say long</note>
<lb n="0534c08" ed="T"/>this principle and must not be understood otherwise.</p>
<lb n="0534c09" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0534c0901">Fourth, the other-kind within the school means as Nanquan said: where knowledge does not reach, strictly<anchor xml:id="beg_2" type="star"/><anchor xml:id="end_2"/>
<lb n="0534c10" ed="T"/>avoid speaking of it. If spoken of, horns sprout. Calling it suchness is already a change.
<lb n="0534c11" ed="T"/>One must directly practice the Way within the other kind and take up the matters within the other kind. Dongshan said, this
<lb n="0534c12" ed="T"/>matter must be subtly understood. The matter lies in its subtlety. The body lies in the subtle place. Caoshan himself<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534013" n="0534013"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534013" n="0534013"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534013" n="0534013"/><anchor xml:id="end0534013"/>
<lb n="0534c13" ed="T"/>said, this matter must be the empty one position, wholly without fixed marks. Face to face, carrying both,
<lb n="0534c14" ed="T"/>only thus is it attained. The words of a master are not biased, not upright, not existent, not nonexistent; this is called
<lb n="0534c15" ed="T"/>emptiness within the other kind. In this matter one must, as a true adept, place the body crosswise: meeting wood, attach to wood.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534014" n="0534014"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534014" n="0534014"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534014" n="0534014"/><anchor xml:id="end0534014"/>
<lb n="0534c16" ed="T"/>Meeting bamboo, attach to bamboo. One must guard against offense and collision. Take care, take care, take care, take care. A monk asked, what is the different. I said, if I were to tell you, then in the year of the donkey<note place="inline">From here on, the questions and answers all use tongueless speech
<lb n="0534c17" ed="T"/>The wording takes the middle and lower way to explain the above four different classes</note>
<lb n="0534c18" ed="T"/>would you get the different. Therefore someone asked Master Nanquan, after a hundred years, to what place<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534015" n="0534015"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534015" n="0534015"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534015" n="0534015"/><anchor xml:id="end0534015"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534016" n="0534016"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534016" n="0534016"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534016" n="0534016"/><anchor xml:id="end0534016"/>
<lb n="0534c19" ed="T"/>will you go. Quan said, to the donor household below the mountain, to become a water buffalo<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534017" n="0534017"/>
<lb n="0534c20" ed="T"/>there. He said, may I follow the master there. Quan said, if you<note place="inline">The wording differs here and there, but how could the school differ</note>
<lb n="0534c21" ed="T"/>would follow me, come holding a blade of grass in your mouth. I said, this water buffalo is not the same as<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534018" n="0534018"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534018" n="0534018"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534018" n="0534018"/><anchor xml:id="end0534018"/>
<lb n="0534c22" ed="T"/>the śramaṇa water buffalo. You must be very careful, only then will you not be confused at the time.</p>
<lb n="0534c23" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0534c2301">Asked, what is the other-kind of coming and going. I said, not yet knowing one has oneself. Then asked,
<lb n="0534c24" ed="T"/>all speech, sounds, forms, right and wrong are altogether the other-kind of coming and going. What is
<lb n="0534c25" ed="T"/>the other-kind within sameness. I said, not choosing its body. What is the fur-wearing and horn-bearing<note place="inline">bodhisattva</note>
<lb n="0534c26" ed="T"/>other-kind. I said, not setting up contact and purity. Also, at another time I answered: on meeting contact, contact;<note place="inline">śramaṇa</note><note place="inline">should be</note>
<lb n="0534c27" ed="T"/>on meeting purity, purity. What is the other-kind in the school. I said, if you want your head,
<lb n="0534c28" ed="T"/>then grind it off and take it away.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0534019" n="0534019"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0534019" n="0534019"/><anchor xml:id="beg0534019" n="0534019"/><anchor xml:id="end0534019"/></p>
<lb n="0534c29" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0534c2901">A monk brought this up. Because a monk asked Great Master Dongshan about śramaṇa practice, the Master said, head
<pb n="0535a" xml:id="T47.1987A.0535a" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0535a01" ed="T"/>three feet long, neck two inches short. What is this meaning. I said, a surpassing<note place="inline">The new and old editions have no difference</note>
<lb n="0535a02" ed="T"/>phrase, a wondrous phrase. What is called a surpassing phrase, a wondrous phrase. I said, surpassing and wondrous phrases
<lb n="0535a03" ed="T"/>have three kinds. First, the World-Honored One appeared in the world and for forty-nine years set forth expedient means.
<lb n="0535a04" ed="T"/>The twelve divisions of teaching, the hundred thousand samadhi wondrous gates, penetrating each gate to the end, all are<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0535001" n="0535001"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0535001" n="0535001"/><anchor xml:id="beg0535001" n="0535001"/><anchor xml:id="end0535001"/>
<lb n="0535a05" ed="T"/>surpassing phrases and wondrous phrases. This is speech from the side of transcendence. Second, going from ordinary to holy, thoroughly
<lb n="0535a06" ed="T"/>penetrating oneself and being no different from Buddha, attaining no remainder or leakage, only then attaining the whole body, only then called
<lb n="0535a07" ed="T"/>one mote, one thought, the ten-direction Bhagavans, one road, the gate of nirvana. When one reaches
<lb n="0535a08" ed="T"/>such a time, one does not abide in the proper position and does not choose one’s body, but instead enters the other kind, wearing
<lb n="0535a09" ed="T"/>fur and bearing horns without a thought of difference. Therefore it is said, no class of things can compare with it.
<lb n="0535a10" ed="T"/>All Buddhas and patriarchs cannot reckon or measure it. Therefore the ancients said, in śramaṇa speech one must not<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0535002" n="0535002"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0535002" n="0535002"/><anchor xml:id="beg0535002" n="0535002"/><anchor xml:id="end0535002"/>
<lb n="0535a11" ed="T"/>use measurements and dimensions to speak to people. Therefore it is called a surpassing phrase, a wondrous phrase. This is on the side of form-kind
<lb n="0535a12" ed="T"/>speech. Third, when nothing whatsoever can be compared to it, only then is it called a surpassing
<lb n="0535a13" ed="T"/>phrase, a wondrous phrase. Therefore the ancients said, a thousand kinds cannot compare, and the ten thousand things cannot illustrate it.
<lb n="0535a14" ed="T"/>The wise cannot know it; those of highest capacity also do not recognize it. It is also said to be originally without<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0535003" n="0535003"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0535003" n="0535003"/><anchor xml:id="beg0535003" n="0535003"/><anchor xml:id="end0535003"/>
<lb n="0535a15" ed="T"/>likeness. Therefore it is a surpassing phrase, a wondrous phrase. A surpassing phrase, a wondrous phrase, is that which heaven and humanity cannot measure.
<lb n="0535a16" ed="T"/>It is a matter beyond measurement. Therefore the ancients called it the phrase surpassing beginning and end. Borrowing this
<lb n="0535a17" ed="T"/>as speech from the side of language-kind, Xingchou the patched-robe monk asked, what is form-kind.<note place="inline">Further below it is more detailed</note>
<lb n="0535a18" ed="T"/>I said, wearing fur and bearing horns. What is language-kind. He said, Caoshan has only one
<lb n="0535a19" ed="T"/>pair of eyebrows. What is the water buffalo. He said, dim and muddled-eyed. What is the meaning of this.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0535004" n="0535004"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0535004" n="0535004"/><anchor xml:id="beg0535004" n="0535004"/><anchor xml:id="end0535004"/>
<lb n="0535a20" ed="T"/>He said, not knowing there is heaven and earth.</p>
<lb n="0535a21" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0535a2101">Chou further cited: a senior monk asked Yunju, the ancient Buddha Dongshan said, from youth<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0535005" n="0535005"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0535005" n="0535005"/><anchor xml:id="beg0535005" n="0535005"/><anchor xml:id="end0535005"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0535006" n="0535006"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0535006" n="0535006"/><anchor xml:id="beg0535006" n="0535006"/><anchor xml:id="end0535006"/>
<lb n="0535a22" ed="T"/>I raised one son. His head is three feet long and his neck two inches short. Up to<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0535007" n="0535007"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0535007" n="0535007"/><anchor xml:id="beg0535007" n="0535007"/><anchor xml:id="end0535007"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0535008" n="0535008"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0535008" n="0535008"/><anchor xml:id="beg0535008" n="0535008"/>
<lb n="0535a23" ed="T"/>now I can do nothing about him. What is that son raised from youth. Ju said,<anchor xml:id="end0535008"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0535009" n="0535009"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0535009" n="0535009"/><anchor xml:id="beg0535009" n="0535009"/><anchor xml:id="end0535009"/>
<lb n="0535a24" ed="T"/>daily provision, hard to forget. What is head three feet long. He said, no way to manage it. What
<lb n="0535a25" ed="T"/>is neck two inches short. He said, up to now can you still do anything about it or not. Asked, what is daily provision hard to forget. I said, it is just always present. What<note place="inline">One edition has later it raises a question to the master. One
<lb n="0535a26" ed="T"/>One edition connects it above and still treats it as Yunju's words</note>
<lb n="0535a27" ed="T"/>is always present. He said, not turning away from it is it. What is no way to manage it. He said,
<lb n="0535a28" ed="T"/>when it reaches such a time, what person could do anything about it. Up to now, can you still do anything about it or not.
<lb n="0535a29" ed="T"/>What is the meaning of this. He said, the Buddhas of the three times cannot do anything about it. What
<pb n="0535b" xml:id="T47.1987A.0535b" ed="T"/>
<note place="inline">One edition ends Yunju Mountain's words here</note>
<lb n="0535b01" ed="T"/>is head three feet long, neck two inches short. He said, it is not a matter from the very beginning. What
<lb n="0535b02" ed="T"/>is the matter from the very beginning. He said, what would you call it.</p>
<lb n="0535b03" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0535b0301">Asked, what practice does the śramaṇa practice. He said, the practice of beasts. What is the beast
<lb n="0535b04" ed="T"/>practice. He said, wearing fur and bearing horns. What is śramaṇa practice. He said, in each and every thing<note place="inline">Fur-clad and horned</note>
<lb n="0535b05" ed="T"/>without interruption. What is the uninterrupted matter. He said, only then is it practice. What is
<lb n="0535b06" ed="T"/>the person who wears fur and bears horns. He said, not fearing karma. Why does one arrive at such a place.
<lb n="0535b07" ed="T"/>He said, if one does not fear karma, what place could one fail to reach.</p>
<lb n="0535b08" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0535b0801">Asked, I do not ask about going from ordinary to holy. What about going from holy into ordinary. He said, a water
<lb n="0535b09" ed="T"/>buffalo. What is the water buffalo. He said, dim and muddled-eyed. What is the meaning of this.
<lb n="0535b10" ed="T"/>He said, it only thinks of water and grass and knows nothing else. What side-matter does that accomplish. He said,
<lb n="0535b11" ed="T"/>it is simply meeting grass and eating grass, meeting water and drinking water. The Master again said, this saying has
<lb n="0535b12" ed="T"/>force. If you wish to know its force, this person does not cling to matters on the śramaṇa side, nor does he enter the various
<lb n="0535b13" ed="T"/>holy reward positions. This is precisely entering the other kind. This other kind is wearing fur and bearing horns, called
<lb n="0535b14" ed="T"/>śramaṇa practice. It is also called the baggage-place of śramaṇa practice. It is also called head
<lb n="0535b15" ed="T"/>three feet long, neck two inches short. If you wish to know this meaning, when one comes to śramaṇa practice one does not wish
<lb n="0535b16" ed="T"/>to use measurements to divide near and far. One must not speak of Zhang Three or Li Four. And head three
<lb n="0535b17" ed="T"/>feet long means one only reaches it by going from small to great, and today the work is complete. When one reaches such a time,
<lb n="0535b18" ed="T"/>it is called a surpassing phrase, a wondrous phrase. Neck two inches short means not sitting in the śramaṇa position,
<lb n="0535b19" ed="T"/>and also not abiding in the various holy reward positions. Therefore it is neck two inches short. At such a time one must not<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0535010" n="0535010"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0535010" n="0535010"/><anchor xml:id="beg0535010" n="0535010"/><anchor xml:id="end0535010"/>
<lb n="0535b20" ed="T"/>speak in terms of fitting or not fitting. Therefore it is said, do not bring measurements here to
<lb n="0535b21" ed="T"/>calculate and think. Even so, this is still a matter on the side of kind. You must know there is a matter within the other
<lb n="0535b22" ed="T"/>kind. Did you not see it said: where knowledge does not reach, one must not speak of it. If spoken of, then
<lb n="0535b23" ed="T"/>horns sprout. Calling it suchness is already change. One must proceed within the other kind.
<lb n="0535b24" ed="T"/>This is called the empty one position. It is called face-to-face carrying both. It is wholly without fixed marks.<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0535011" n="0535011"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0535011" n="0535011"/><anchor xml:id="beg0535011" n="0535011"/><anchor xml:id="end0535011"/>
<lb n="0535b25" ed="T"/>Asked, what is kind. He said, wearing fur and bearing horns. What is the different. He said, what to do,
<lb n="0535b26" ed="T"/>what to do. What is practice. He said, if you want your head, then chop it off and take it away. As for the other kind,
<lb n="0535b27" ed="T"/>what side-matter does it accomplish. He said, this matter has two kinds of other-kind. One is
<lb n="0535b28" ed="T"/>śramaṇa other-kind. The second is situational other-kind. Situational other-kind is the civet-cat
<lb n="0535b29" ed="T"/>and white ox, that sort of thing. As for śramaṇa other-kind, one gains freedom wherever one touches, and only then does one become unchanging.
<pb n="0535c" xml:id="T47.1987A.0535c" ed="T"/>
<lb n="0535c01" ed="T"/>It is not like that other one. My former teacher asked me, where are you going. I said, to the unchanging
<lb n="0535c02" ed="T"/>place. He further said, this unchanging matter has two kinds. First, every<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0535012" n="0535012"/><anchor xml:id="nkr_note_mod_0535012" n="0535012"/><anchor xml:id="beg0535012" n="0535012"/><anchor xml:id="end0535012"/>
<lb n="0535c03" ed="T"/>person has the fundamental matter. Second, a person who knows this does not abandon any sounds,
<lb n="0535c04" ed="T"/>forms, rights and wrongs, and is not stuck on any thing whatsoever. This is called unchanging in every place.
<lb n="0535c05" ed="T"/>It is also called wearing fur and bearing horns. It is also called entering mud and entering water.<note place="inline">Probably a difference in the departing-tone pronunciation</note>
<lb n="0535c06" ed="T"/>It is also called a fellow of the traveling gear. Asked, what is entering mud and entering water. He said, not
<lb n="0535c07" ed="T"/>changing. Does he turn the body or not. He said, he does not turn the body. What are this person’s household matters.
<lb n="0535c08" ed="T"/>He said, the various sages cannot measure them. Why can they not measure them. He said, because he is not the same as
<lb n="0535c09" ed="T"/>the various sages. This is still a matter on the side of kind. Is there still a higher matter. He said, yes. What
<lb n="0535c10" ed="T"/>is the higher matter. He said, if I tell you, I fear it will fall onto the side of kind.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0535c11" ed="T"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu level="1" type="其他">Third, Lamp-Lighting</cb:mulu><head>Third, Lamp-Lighting<note place="inline">The upright three before and after</note></head>
<lb n="0535c12" ed="T"/><p xml:id="pT47p0535c1201">The Master said, as for before Lamp-Lighting, there are two kinds. First, not yet knowing there is, the same as the blood of kind.
<lb n="0535c13" ed="T"/>milk. Second is knowing that there is, like obtaining the original thing before intention has even sprouted. This is called the Lamp-Before.
<lb n="0535c14" ed="T"/>Before the Lamp. One kind of knowing that there is, in comings and goings, speech, sounds, forms, and right and wrong, also does not belong
<lb n="0535c15" ed="T"/>to the functioning of correct illumination, and also does not receive prediction. It is like blood in the same class as milk. This is a matter on the side of leakage and loss.
<lb n="0535c16" ed="T"/>This is called the Lamp-After. It is simply that the affairs of the three times are exhausted, inner and outer sentiments are forgotten, and one attains no
<lb n="0535c17" ed="T"/>interruption. Only then does it first deserve the name of the true Lamp-Lighting, and thus it is said to receive prediction.</p></cb:div>
<lb n="0535c18" ed="T"/><cb:juan n="001" fun="close"><cb:jhead>Recorded Sayings of Chan Master Caoshan Yuanzheng of Fuzhou<note place="inline">End</note></cb:jhead></cb:juan>
</body>
<back>
<cb:div type="apparatus">
<head>Collation notes</head>
<p>Therefore it says, zi<app from="#beg0528b0901" to="#end0528b0901"><lem wit="#wit.cbeta" resp="#resp4">闍<note type="cf1">T47n1987Bp0538a25</note><note type="cf2">X66n1297_p0659c10</note></lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">闇</rdg></app><app from="#beg0528001" to="#end0528001"><lem wit="#wit.orig">好</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">愛</rdg></app><app from="#beg0529003" to="#end0529003"><lem resp="#resp2" wit="#wit.orig">余</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="correctionRemark">餘</rdg></app><app from="#beg0530a1401" to="#end0530a1401"><lem wit="#wit.cbeta" resp="#resp4">閒</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">間</rdg></app><app from="#beg0531004" to="#end0531004"><lem wit="#wit.orig">觀</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">官</rdg></app><app from="#beg0533001" to="#end0533001"><lem wit="#wit.orig">歸</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">來</rdg></app><app from="#beg0534001" to="#end0534001"><lem wit="#wit.orig">聖</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">勝</rdg></app><app from="#beg0534002" to="#end0534002"><lem wit="#wit.orig">他</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">也</rdg></app>
<lb n="0534a16" ed="T"/>Carefully, carefully, straight through to<rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark"><space quantity="0"/></rdg><app from="#beg0534004" to="#end0534004"><lem wit="#wit.orig">老</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark"><space quantity="0"/></rdg></app><app from="#beg0534005" to="#end0534005"><lem wit="#wit.orig">又</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">余</rdg></app><app from="#beg0534006" to="#end0534006"><lem wit="#wit.orig">西東</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">東西</rdg></app><app from="#beg0534007" to="#end0534007"><lem wit="#wit.orig">謂</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">者</rdg></app><app from="#beg0534009" to="#end0534009"><lem wit="#wit.orig">父</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">又</rdg></app><app from="#beg0534010" to="#end0534010"><lem wit="#wit.orig">我</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark"><space quantity="0"/></rdg></app><app from="#beg0534011" to="#end0534011"><lem wit="#wit.orig">行持</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">誓願</rdg></app><app from="#beg_1" to="#end_1" corresp="#0534007"><lem wit="#wit.orig">謂</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">者</rdg></app><app from="#beg0534012" to="#end0534012"><lem wit="#wit.orig">勝</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">聖</rdg></app><app from="#beg_2" to="#end_2" corresp="#0534007"><lem wit="#wit.orig">謂</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">者</rdg></app><app from="#beg0534013" to="#end0534013"><lem wit="#wit.orig">曹山</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">余</rdg></app><app from="#beg0534014" to="#end0534014"><lem wit="#wit.orig">類</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit2" type="variantRemark"><space quantity="0"/></rdg></app><app from="#beg0534015" to="#end0534015"><lem wit="#wit.orig">麼</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">否</rdg></app><app from="#beg0534016" to="#end0534016"><lem wit="#wit.orig">和尚</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark"><space quantity="0"/></rdg></app><app from="#beg0534018" to="#end0534018"><lem wit="#wit.orig">余</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">師</rdg></app><app from="#beg0534019" to="#end0534019"><lem wit="#wit.orig">研</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">斫</rdg></app><app from="#beg0535001" to="#end0535001"><lem wit="#wit.orig">究</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">穴</rdg></app><app from="#beg0535002" to="#end0535002"><lem wit="#wit.orig">語</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">邊語</rdg></app><app from="#beg0535003" to="#end0535003"><lem wit="#wit.orig">本來</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark"><space quantity="0"/></rdg></app><app from="#beg0535004" to="#end0535004"><lem wit="#wit.orig">originally</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">問如</rdg></app><app from="#beg0535005" to="#end0535005"><lem wit="#wit.orig">thus</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">asks thus</rdg></app><app from="#beg0535006" to="#end0535006"><lem wit="#wit.orig">Chou again cited</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">先師</rdg></app><app from="#beg0535007" to="#end0535007"><lem wit="#wit.orig">Dongshan, the Ancient Buddha</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">former teacher</rdg></app>
<lb n="0535a23" ed="T"/>Now there is nothing to be done<rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark"><space quantity="0"/></rdg><app from="#beg0535009" to="#end0535009"><lem wit="#wit.orig">attain</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark"><space quantity="0"/></rdg></app><app from="#beg0535010" to="#end0535010"><lem wit="#wit.orig">straight on until
<lb n="0535a23" ed="T"/>up to now, there is nothing to be done</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark"><space quantity="0"/></rdg></app><app from="#beg0535011" to="#end0535011"><lem wit="#wit.orig">from youth</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark"><space quantity="0"/></rdg></app><app from="#beg0535012" to="#end0535012"><lem wit="#wit.orig">position</lem><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark"><space quantity="0"/></rdg><rdg resp="#resp2" wit="#wit1" type="variantRemark">師曰</rdg></app></p>
</cb:div>
<cb:div type="cbeta-notes">
<head>CBETA textual notes</head>
<p>
<note n="0528001" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0528001">good in Taisho, love in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0529003" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0529003">yu in Taisho, yu alternate form in the textual criticism source</note>
<note n="0531004" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0531004">observe in Taisho, official in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0533001" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0533001">return in Taisho, come in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534001" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534001">sage in Taisho, victory in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534002" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534002">he or other in Taisho, also in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534003" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534003">the phrase therefore it says carefully, carefully appears in Taisho and is omitted in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534004" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534004">old appears in Taisho and is omitted in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534005" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534005">again in Taisho, yu in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534006" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534006">west east in Taisho, east west in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534007" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534007">says in Taisho, the one who in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534009" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534009">father in Taisho, again in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534010" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534010">I in Taisho and omitted in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534011" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534011">practice and uphold in Taisho, vows in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534012" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534012">victory in Taisho, sage in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534013" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534013">Caoshan in Taisho, yu in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534014" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534014">category or kind in Taisho and omitted in the Jia variant note</note>
<note n="0534015" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534015">interrogative mo in Taisho, no or not in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534016" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534016">和尚 in Taisho and omitted in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534018" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534018">yu in Taisho, master in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0534019" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0534019">grind in Taisho, chop in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0535001" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0535001">investigate in Taisho, cave in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0535002" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0535002">speech in Taisho, side speech in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0535003" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0535003">originally appears in Taisho and is omitted in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0535004" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0535004">thus in Taisho, asks thus in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0535005" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0535005">Chou again cited appears in Taisho and is omitted in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0535006" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0535006">Dongshan Ancient Buddha in Taisho, former teacher in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0535007" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0535007">attain appears in Taisho and is omitted in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0535008" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0535008">the phrase straight on until now there is nothing to be done appears in Taisho and is omitted in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0535009" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0535009">from youth appears in Taisho and is omitted in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0535010" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0535010">position appears in Taisho and is omitted in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0535011" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0535011">also appears in Taisho and is omitted in the variant-source note</note>
<note n="0535012" resp="#resp3" type="mod" target="#nkr_note_mod_0535012">also said appears in Taisho, omitted in the variant-source note, where it reads the master said</note>
</p>
</cb:div>
<cb:div type="taisho-notes">
<head>Taisho canon textual notes</head>
<p>
<note n="0526001" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0526001">Original source, Meiwa year 3 printed copy held by Komazawa University</note>
<note n="0527001" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0527001">The original note says these verses on ruler and minister and the five aspects could be compiled in the final miscellany, but this follows the old printing</note>
<note n="0527002" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0527002">The original note says this story already appears in the Dongshan Record</note>
<note n="0528001" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0528001">good equals love in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0529001" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0529001">The original note says the Caoshang leiju preserves the four characters thirty years before</note>
<note n="0529002" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0529002">The original note says this is a huatou phrase that by chance resembles the wording of Qingxi</note>
<note n="0529003" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0529003">yu equals the alternate form yu in the original source, uncertain reading</note>
<note n="0531001" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0531001">The original note says zha should be written as zha, with the pronunciation and explanation given in brief</note>
<note n="0531002" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0531002">The original note says from here onward the master's comments on Dongshan old cases are already recorded in the Xinfeng Record, so they are not included here</note>
<note n="0531003" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0531003">The original note says the Wan Guanghui annotated edition reads gu</note>
<note n="0531004" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0531004">observe equals official in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0532001" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0532001">The original note says Elder Tianzhen's selected sayings are omitted here for brevity</note>
<note n="0533001" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0533001">return equals come in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0534001" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534001">sage equals victory in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0534002" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534002">he or other equals also in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0534003" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534003">the phrase therefore it says carefully, carefully is omitted in the original source</note>
<note n="0534004" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534004">old is omitted in the original source</note>
<note n="0534005" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534005">again equals yu in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0534006" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534006">west east equals east west in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0534007" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534007">says equals the one who in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0534008" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534008">The original note says various editions write bei for this character, but according to the old oral formula it should be jie, all</note>
<note n="0534009" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534009">father equals again in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0534010" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534010">I is omitted in the original source</note>
<note n="0534011" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534011">practice and uphold equals vows in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0534012" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534012">victory equals sage in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0534013" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534013">Caoshan equals yu in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0534014" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534014">kind is omitted in the Jia source</note>
<note n="0534015" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534015">mo equals no or not in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0534016" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534016">和尚 is omitted in the original source</note>
<note n="0534017" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534017">The original note says in the Three Falls passage this place has the characters I turn toward</note>
<note n="0534018" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534018">yu equals master in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0534019" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0534019">grind equals chop in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0535001" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0535001">investigate equals cave in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0535002" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0535002">adds speech after side in the original source</note>
<note n="0535003" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0535003">originally is omitted in the original source</note>
<note n="0535004" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0535004">adds thus after ask in the original source</note>
<note n="0535005" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0535005">Chou again cited is omitted in the original source</note>
<note n="0535006" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0535006">Dongshan Ancient Buddha equals former teacher in the original source variant</note>
<note n="0535007" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0535007">attain is omitted in the original source</note>
<note n="0535008" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0535008">the phrase straight on until now there is nothing to be done is omitted in the original source</note>
<note n="0535009" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0535009">from youth is omitted in the original source</note>
<note n="0535010" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0535010">position is omitted in the original source</note>
<note n="0535011" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0535011">also is omitted in the original source</note>
<note n="0535012" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0535012">again equals master in the original source variant, and the phrase also said is omitted in the original source</note>
</p>
</cb:div>
<cb:div type="add-notes">
<head>newly added textual notes</head>
<p>
<note n="0528b0901" resp="#resp3" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0528b0901">du in CBETA, dark in Taisho</note>
<note n="0530a1401" resp="#resp3" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0530a1401">leisure in CBETA, interval in Taisho</note>
</p>
</cb:div>
</back></text></TEI>